[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "For the examination of microbial cells we require the use of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High-power microscope",
            "b) Low-power microscope",
            "c) High-power microscope at a magnification of about 1,000 diameters",
            "d) Low-power microscope at a magnification of about 1,000 diameters"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Microorganisms are very small and their size is usually expressed in micrometers. So for routine examination of microbial cells we require the use of a high-power microscope, usually at a magnification of about 1,000 diameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "Lipopolysaccharide in cell walls is characteristic of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gram-positive bacteria",
            "b) Gram-negative bacteria",
            "c) Fungi",
            "d) Algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The occurrence of lipopolysaccharide in cell walls is characteristic of Gram-negative bacteria; whereas Gram-positive bacteria have cell walls that contain teichoic acid. Fungal and algal cell walls are very different in composition from those of bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which microorganism(s) among the following perform photosynthesis by utilizing light?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cyanobacteria",
            "b) Fungi",
            "c) Viruses",
            "d) Cyanobacteria, Fungi and Viruses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cyanobacteria require light as a source of energy to perform photosynthesis. Fungi and viruses are unable to perform photosynthesis and are heterotrophic."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Growth of microbes in a solid media is identified by the formation of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pellicle at the top of media",
            "b) colonies",
            "c) sediment at the bottom",
            "d) turbidity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: On solid media, microbes grow as colonies – distinct, compact masses of cells that are macroscopically visible. When microbes grow in liquid media, the media becomes turbid and growth may either occur only as sediment at the bottom or only as a thin film or pellicle at the top."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "Which among the following are produced by microorganisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fermented dairy products",
            "b) Breads",
            "c) Alcoholic beverages",
            "d) Fermented dairy products, breads and alcoholic beverages"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Microorganisms are used in many industries for the production of food we eat, like fermented dairy products (sour cream, yogurt), as well as fermented foods as pickles, breads and alcoholic beverages."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "What are the blood serum proteins produced by animals called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enzymes",
            "b) Antibodies",
            "c) Amino acids",
            "d) Toxins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Certain chemical compounds of microbial cells are called antigens. If microbial cells enter the animal body, the animal responds to these antigens by forming specific blood serum proteins called antibodies, which bind to the antigens."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "The DNA molecule of microorganisms is made up of base pairs of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) guanine-cytosine",
            "b) adenine-thymine",
            "c) adenine-cytosine",
            "d) guanine-cytosine and adenine-thymine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The DNA molecule has a base composition of the following sequence as base pairs; guanine-cytosine and adenine-thymine. The ratio of A:T= the ratio of G:C."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "The DNA of Klebsiella pneumonia has a moles % G+C content of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70-71",
            "b) 50-53",
            "c) 56-58",
            "d) 32-35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sequence of nucleotide bases in the DNA is unique for each kind of microorganism.\n\n\nSpecies\nMoles % G+C content of DNA\n\n\nKlebsiella pneumonia\n56-58\n\n\nAzospirillum brasilense \n70-71\n\n\nCampylobacter fetus\n32-35\n\n\nNeisseria gonorrhoeae \n50-53\n\n\n "
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "Bdellovibrios come under which group of microorganisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viruses",
            "b) Bacteria",
            "c) Fungi",
            "d) Algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In addition to chromosomal DNA, plasmid DNA may sometimes be present in microbial cells. Plasmids are circular DNA molecules that are capable of autonomous replication within bacterial cells that contain them and their presence can confer special characteristics on the cells that contain them."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "Type strain is used for referring to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) species",
            "b) genus",
            "c) family",
            "d) division"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bacterial species consists of a special strain called type strain which have similar characteristics. Bacterial genus is composed of a collection of similar species and is referred to as type species."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "The correct order of taxonomic groups from higher to lower rank is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kingdom—Order—Class—Family",
            "b) Order—Class—Division—Family—Genus—Species",
            "c) Kingdom—Order—Division—Family—Class—Genus—Species",
            "d) Kingdom—Division—Class—Order—Family—Genus—Species"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Taxonomists have made the classification based on two qualities—stability and predictability. The order of taxonomic groups from higher rank to lower rank is: Kingdom—Division—Class—Order—Family—Genus—Species."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "% Similarity (%S) of each strain to every other strain is calculated by which method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intuitive Method",
            "b) Numerical Taxonomy",
            "c) Genetic Relatedness",
            "d) DNA homology experiments"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: %S = NS\n                     NS+ND\n  where, %S is % similarity of each strain to every other strain, NS is the number of characteristics that are the same for the two strains, and ND is the number of characteristics that are different. Thus this is determined by numerical taxonomy."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "Two organisms which are very closely related to each other have which of the following property?",
        "Options": [
            "a) similar mol% G+C values",
            "b) different mol% G+C values",
            "c) similar mol% G+C values and heteroduplexes are formed",
            "d) different mol% G+C values and heteroduplexes are not formed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two organisms of the same species that are very closely related to each other will have very similar mol% G+C values and their single strands of DNA molecules combine to form heteroduplexes. Organisms which are not closely related have different mol% G+C values and hence do not form heteroduplexes."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "What are ribosomes composed of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proteins",
            "b) DNA",
            "c) RNA",
            "d) Proteins and RNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ribosomes, the small granular-appearing structures within the cell which manufacture proteins, are composed of proteins and RNA. The ribosomal RNA (rRNA) is coded for by only a small fraction of the DNA molecule, the rRNA cistrons."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "Which of the following are characteristics of archaebacterial different from eubacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) methane-producers",
            "b) extreme halophiles",
            "c) thermoacidophiles",
            "d) methane-producers, extreme halophiles, and thermoacidophiles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The nucleotide sequence of rRNA genes has been found to be highly conserved. So even if two organisms are only distantly related and show no significant DNA homology, there still maybe similarity in the nucleotide sequences of their rRNA cistrons. The degree of similarity that exists can then be used as a measure of relatedness between organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "Which among the following come under Gram-positive eubacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clostridium",
            "b) Actinomyces",
            "c) Rhizobium",
            "d) Clostridium, Actinomyces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Eubacteria are the traditional, familiar ones that have received the most study. Archaebacteria the other group consists of methane producers, extreme halophiles and thermoacidophiles."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "Which among the following kingdoms were proposed by Whittaker?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monera",
            "b) Protista, Fungi",
            "c) Plantae, Animalia",
            "d) Monera,Protista,Fungi,Plantae,Animalia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Based on rRNA oligonucleotide, Clostridium and Actinomyces come under Gram-positive eubacteria. Rhizobium belongs to Purple eubacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "According to Bergey’s Manual of Systematic Bacteriology, prokaryotes that lack a cell wall belong to the group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gracilicutes",
            "b) Firmicutes",
            "c) Tenericutes",
            "d) Mendosicutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: R.H.Whittaker classified microorganisms on the basis of nutritional requirements and formed Whittaker’s Five Kingdom and they are Monera (bacteria and cyanobacteria), Protista (microalgae and protozoa), Fungi (yeasts and molds), Plantae (multicellular green plants and higher algae) and Animalia (multicellular animals)."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "Which part of the compound microscope helps in gathering and focusing light rays on the specimen to be viewed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eyepiece lens",
            "b) Objective lens",
            "c) Condenser lens",
            "d) Magnifying lens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Compound microscope contains three separate lens systems. The condenser lens is placed between the light source and the specimen and it gathers and focuses the light rays in the plane of the microscopic field to view the specimen."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "What is the minimum distance for the eye to focus any object?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11 cm",
            "b) 25 cm",
            "c) 32 cm",
            "d) 4 2 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The eye cannot focus on objects brought closer to it less than 25 cm; this is, accordingly the distance of maximal effective magnification. An object must also subtend an angle at the eye of 1 degree or greater."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "Resolving power of a microscope is a function of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wavelength of light used",
            "b) Numerical aperture of lens system",
            "c) Refractive index",
            "d) Wavelength of light used and numerical aperture of lens system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ability of a microscope to distinguish two adjacent points as distinct and separate is known as resolving power. Resolving power is a function of wavelength of light used and the numerical aperture (NA) of the lens system. NA refers to the refractive index of the medium multiplied with the sine value of the half-aperture angle."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "The greatest resolution in light microscopy can be obtained with ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longest wavelength of visible light used",
            "b) An objective with minimum numerical aperture",
            "c) Shortest wavelength of visible light used",
            "d) Shortest wavelength of visible light used and an objective with the maximum numerical aperture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The relationship between numerical aperture (NA) and resolution is:-\n                      Resolution (d) = wavelength / 2(NA)\nThus maximum resolution is obtained with the shortest wavelength of visible light and an objective with the maximum NA."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "Oil immersion objective lens has an NA value of____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.65",
            "b) 0.85",
            "c) 1.33",
            "d) 1.00"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: NA = refractive index * sine (half-aperture angle).\nThe maximum NA for a dry objective is less than 1.0 as the refractive index of air is 1. The values of NA for oil immersion lens is slightly greater than 1.0 in the range of (1.2 to 1.4) as the refractive index of oil is 1.56."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "In fluorescence microscopy, which of the following performs the function of removing all light except the blue light?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exciter filter",
            "b) Barrier filter",
            "c) Dichroic mirror",
            "d) Mercury arc lamp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In fluorescence microscopy, the function of the exciter filter is to remove all but the blue light; the barrier filter blocks out blue light and allows any other light emitted by the fluorescing specimen to pass through and reach the eye."
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "Total Magnification is obtained by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnifying power of the objective lens",
            "b) Magnifying power of eyepiece",
            "c) Magnifying power of condenser lens",
            "d) Magnifying power of both the objective lens and eyepiece"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The total magnification is determined by multiplying the magnifying power of the objective by that of the eyepiece. Generally, an eyepiece having a magnification of 10X is used although eyepieces of higher or lower magnifications are available."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "In light microscopy, which of the following is used as fixatives prior to staining technique?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Osmic acid",
            "b) Glutaraldehyde",
            "c) Heat",
            "d) Osmic acid, glutaraldehyde, heat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Most staining techniques kill cells and so preliminary to staining, the cells are sometimes fixed. Commonly used chemical fixatives include osmic acid and mainly glutaraldehyde. But for light microscopy heat is the most commonly used fixative."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "In Phase contrast microscopy, the rate at which light enters through objects is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant",
            "b) Inversely proportional to their refractive indices",
            "c) Directly proportional to their refractive indices",
            "d) Exponentially related to their refractive indices"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Phase contrast microscopy is based on the fact that the rate at which light travels through objects is inversely related to their refractive indices. Since the frequency of light waves is independent of the medium through which they travel, the phase of a light ray passing through an object of the higher refractive index than the surrounding medium will be relatively retarded."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "Which part of the light microscope controls the intensity of light entering the viewing area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coarse adjustment screw",
            "b) Fine adjustment screw",
            "c) Diaphragm",
            "d) Condenser lens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: On the condenser is mounted a shutter like an apparatus called the diaphragm which opens and closes to permit more or less light into the viewing area. Condenser lens just helps in condensing the light rays. Coarse and fine adjustment screws are used for focusing under different power lens."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used in electron microscope?",
        "Options": [
            "a) electron beams",
            "b) magnetic fields",
            "c) light waves",
            "d) electron beams and magnetic fields"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Electron Microscope uses electron beams and magnetic fields to produce the image, whereas the light microscope uses light waves and glass lenses. In electron microscopy, a much higher resolution is obtained with extremely short wavelength of the electron beam."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "Electron Microscope can give a magnification up to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 400,000X",
            "b) 100,000X",
            "c) 15000X",
            "d) 100X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resolving power of the electron microscope is more than 100 times that of the light microscope, and it produces useful magnification up to 400,000X. It is possible to resolve objects as small as 10 Angstrom."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "Which of the following are true for electron microscopy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) specimen should be thin and dry",
            "b) image is obtained on a phosphorescent screen",
            "c) electron beam must pass through evacuated chamber",
            "d) specimen should be thin and dry, image is obtained on a phosphorescent screen and electron beam must pass through evacuated chamber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Since electrons can travel only in high vacuum, the entire electron path through the instrument must be evacuated; specimens must be completely dehydrated prior to examination. Only very thin specimens can be observed in the conventional electron microscope since the penetrating power of electrons through matter is weak. The magnified image may be viewed on a phosphorescent or fluorescent screen."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "Degree of scattering in transmission electron microscope is a function of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) wavelength of electron beam used",
            "b) number of atoms that lie in the electron path",
            "c) number and mass of atoms that lie in the electron path",
            "d) mass of atoms that lie in the electron path"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In a transmission electron microscope, contrast results from the differential scattering of electrons by the specimen, the degree of scattering being a function of the number and mass of atoms that lie in the electron path."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Negative Staining is used for examining _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) virus particles",
            "b) protein molecules",
            "c) bacterial flagella",
            "d) virus particles, protein molecules and bacterial flagella"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In negative-staining the electron opacity of the surrounding field is increased by using an electron-dense material such as phosphotungstic acid as a stain. Negative staining is particularly valuable for the examination of very small structures such as virus particles, protein molecules and bacterial flagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "Which among the following helps us in getting a three-dimensional picture of the specimen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transmission Electron Microscope",
            "b) Scanning Electron Microscope",
            "c) Compound Microscope",
            "d) Simple Microscope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The scanning electron microscope lacks the resolving power obtainable with the transmission electron microscope but has the advantage of revealing a striking three-dimensional picture. The surface topography of a specimen can be revealed with clarity and depth of field not possible by any other method."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "The secondary electrons radiated back in scanning microscope is collected by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) specimen",
            "b) anode",
            "c) vacuum chamber",
            "d) cathode"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In scanning electron microscope (SEM), the surface of the specimen is irradiated with a very narrow beam of electrons. Such irradiations causes low energy (secondary) electrons to be ejected from the specimen which can then be collected on a positively-charged plate or anode thereby generating an electric signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "On what factors do the intensity of secondary electrons depend upon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) shape of the irradiated object",
            "b) chemical composition of the irradiated object",
            "c) number of electrons ejected",
            "d) size and chemical composition of the irradiated object, number of electrons ejected and on the number of electrons reabsorbed by surrounding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The irradiations in SEM causes secondary electrons to be ejected from the specimen thereby generating a signal that is proportional to the number of electrons striking the anode. The intensity or the number of secondary electrons depends on the shape and the chemical composition of the irradiated object and also on the number of electrons ejected and the number of electrons reabsorbed by surrounding."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Where do we obtain the magnified image of the specimen in SEM?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cathode ray tube",
            "b) phosphorescent screen",
            "c) anode",
            "d) scanning generator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In TEM, the image is obtained on a phosphorescent screen but in SEM the magnified image of the surface topography of the specimen is obtained on the cathode ray tube. The electronic signals generated scan the specimen in a raster pattern in the manner of a television system to produce an image on a cathode ray tube."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "Which of the following techniques are used in Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM) for examining cellular structure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Negative-Staining",
            "b) Shadow Casting",
            "c) Ultrathin Sectioning",
            "d) Negative-Staining, Shadow Casting, Ultrathin Sectioning, Freeze-Etching"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Numerous techniques are available for use with electron microscopy which extends its usefulness in characterizing cellular structure. Some of them are Negative-Staining (which increases the electron opacity of surrounding), Shadow Casting (helps in producing three-dimensional structure of the object), Ultrathin Sectioning and Freeze-Etching."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "The dye eosinate of methylene blue belongs to which group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acidic dye",
            "b) Basic dye",
            "c) Neutral dye",
            "d) Oxazine dye"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A neutral dye is a complex salt of a dye acid with a dye base so eosinate of methylene blue is an example of a neutral dye. An acidic dye is one in which the charge on the dye ion is negative and a basic dye is one in which the charge carried by the dye ion is positive."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "What is the correct order of staining reagents in Gram-Staining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crystal violet, alcohol, iodine solution, safranin",
            "b) Crystal violet, iodine solution, alcohol, safranin",
            "c) Crystal violet, safranin, alcohol, iodine solution",
            "d) Iodine solution, crystal violet, alcohol, safranin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gram staining is a type of differential staining. In this process the fixed bacterial smear is subjected to the following staining reagents in the order listed: crystal violet, iodine solution, alcohol (decolorizing agent), and safranin."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "Which bacteria appears purple-violet colour after staining?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gram-positive",
            "b) Gram-negative",
            "c) Both Gram-positive and Gram-negative",
            "d) Neither Gram-positive nor Gram-negative"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gram-positive bacteria retain the crystal violet and hence appear deep purple-violet colour as it has a higher content of the peptidoglycan layer. Gram-negative bacteria have lesser amount of peptidoglycan layer and on treatment with alcohol it loses the purple-violet colour, are counterstained by safranin and hence appears red."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "Which of the following are true for Gram-negative bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) upon alcohol treatment, the permeability of the cell wall increases",
            "b) crystal violet-iodine (CV-I) complex is extracted",
            "c) pore size decreases and the CV-I complex cannot be extracted",
            "d) alcohol treatment increases the permeability of the cell wall and the CV-I complex can be extracted"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Experimental evidence suggests that during staining of Gram-negative bacteria the alcohol treatment extracts the lipid, which results in increased permeability of the cell wall. Thus the crystal violet-iodine (CV-I) complex can be extracted and the Gram-negative organism is decolorized. These cells subsequently take on the color of the safranin counterstain."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "Gram-positive bacteria are usually more susceptible to?",
        "Options": [
            "a) streptomycin",
            "b) tetracyclin",
            "c) penicillin",
            "d) ampicillin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Gram-positive bacteria are usually more susceptible to penicillin and less susceptible to disintegration by mechanical treatment or exposure to some enzymes than Gram-negative bacteria. Gram-negative bacteria are more susceptible to other antibiotics like streptomycin."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "Which of the staining technique helps in demonstrating spore structure in bacteria as well as free spores?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acid-fast stain",
            "b) Endospore stain",
            "c) Capsule stain",
            "d) Flagella stain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are numerous other staining techniques designed to identify some particular feature of cell structure or composition. Endospore staining demonstrates spore structure in bacteria as well as free spores."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "In Gram-staining, iodine is used as a ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) fixative",
            "b) mordant",
            "c) solublizer",
            "d) stain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Gram-staining, iodine acts as a mordant i.e. it combines with the dye or stain and thereby fixes it on the material. It increases the interaction between the stain solution and the bacterial cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the example of Gram-negative bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lactobacillus",
            "b) Eschericia coli",
            "c) Staphylococcus aureus",
            "d) Bacillus subtilis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Eschericia coli is an example of Gram-negative bacteria. Others are all examples of Gram-positive bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "In the classification of bacteria according to shape, which among the following refers to cuboidal arrangement of bacterial cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tetrads",
            "b) Staphylococci",
            "c) Sarcinae",
            "d) Streptococci"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the Sarcinae group of bacteria, the cells divide in three planes, in a regular pattern, producing a cuboidal arrangement of cells. In Staphylococci, cells divide in three planes, in an irregular pattern, producing bunches of cocci."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "Which group of bacteria among the following have the largest area of contact?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Palisades",
            "b) Trichomes",
            "c) Streptobacilli",
            "d) Diplobacilli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trichomes are similar to chains but have a much larger area of contact between the adjacent cells whereas in palisade arrangement, the cells are in side by side at angles to one another."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "Which among the following are “Spirochetes”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spirillum volutans",
            "b) Corynebacterium diphtheriae",
            "c) Streptomyces sp.",
            "d) Treponema pallidum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Spirochetes are flexible and can twist and contort their shape, whereas spirilla are relatively rigid. Treponema palldium belongs to the spirochetes group and Spirillum volutans belong to the spirilla group."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "What is the approximate size of the bacterial cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2mm in diameter",
            "b) 1mm in diameter",
            "c) 2 micrometer in diameter",
            "d) 0.5 to 1.0 micrometer in diameter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bacteria are very small, most being approximately 0.5 to 1.0 micrometer in diameter. This is the reason why they cannot be seen by naked eyes and can be observed under the microscope."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "When rod shaped bacteria appears in pairs, it is known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diplobacilli",
            "b) Streptobacilli",
            "c) Diplococci",
            "d) Staphylococci"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When bacilli occur in pairs, it is known as diplobacilli but when they form chains it is known as streptobacilli. Cocci are spherical shaped bacteria and not rod shaped."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "Bacteria with less than a complete twist or comma shaped is known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) spirilla",
            "b) helical",
            "c) vibrioid",
            "d) spirochetes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Due to the small size of microorganisms, the surface area/volume ratio of bacteria is exceedingly high compared to the same ratio for larger organisms of similar shape. A relatively large surface through which nutrients can enter (or waste products leave) compared to a small volume of cell substance to be nourished accounts for the unusually high rate of growth and metabolism of bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Which of the following are functions of the stalk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) nutrient absorption",
            "b) motility",
            "c) attachment of the cells to surfaces",
            "d) human infection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacteria with less than a complete twist or turn have a vibrioid shape, whereas those with one or more complete turns have a helical shape. Spirilla are rigid helical bacteria whereas spirochetes are highly flexible."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "Bacteria having clusters of flagella at both poles of cells are known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lophotrichous",
            "b) Peritrichous",
            "c) Amphitrichous",
            "d) Monotrichous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In amphitrichous, flagella occur either singly or in clusters at both cell poles. Lophotrichous refers to a cluster of polar flagella, peritrichous is surrounded by lateral flagella and monotrichous is for a single polar flagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "Salmonella typhi has which type of flagella arrangement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amphitrichous",
            "b) Peritrichous",
            "c) Monotrichous",
            "d) Lophotrichous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Salmonella typhi has peritrichous type of flagella arrangement. In peritrichous, the bacteria are surrounded by lateral flagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "The L Ring in Gram-Negative bacterium flagella is associated with _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peptidogycan",
            "b) Outer Membrane",
            "c) Cytoplasmic Membrane",
            "d) Cell Membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flagella in Gram-Negative bacteria has four basal rings. The L Ring of flagella is associated with the outer membrane. The P ring is associated with the peptidoglycan layer and both the M and S rings are associated with the cytoplasmic membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Which among the following acts as a transport protein for protons in flagellar motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fli protein",
            "b) cGMP",
            "c) atp",
            "d) mot protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The proton binds to the Mot protein and this changes the conformation of Mot protein. It results in releasing the ring and helps in flagellar motion. The fli protein helps in changing the direction of flagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "F pilus has a major role as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) motility of the cell",
            "b) port of entry of genetic material during mating",
            "c) attachment to host cell",
            "d) human infection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pili are hollow, filamentous appendages that are thinner and shorter. They do not function in motility and have other different functions. One type known as F plus or sex plus serves as the port of entry of genetic material during bacterial mating."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Prosthecae helps in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) motility",
            "b) nutrient absorption and attachment to surfaces",
            "c) human infection",
            "d) protection from the environment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Prosthecae increases the surface area of the cells for nutrient absorption, which is advantageous in dilute environments. Some prosthecate bacteria have an adhesive substance at the end of a prostheca that aids in attachment to surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "When a bacteria swim towards a chemical, it is termed as__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) positive chemotaxis",
            "b) phototaxis",
            "c) negative chemotaxis",
            "d) magnetotaxis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heteroploysaccharides are usually synthesized from sugar precursors that are activated within the cell, attached to a lipid carrier molecule, transported across the cytoplasmic membrane and polymerized outside the cell. The capsule of Klebsiella pneumoniae is an example of heteropolysaccharides. "
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Which type of force drives the flagellar motion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protonmotive force",
            "b) ATP driven",
            "c) Protonmotive and ATP driven",
            "d) No protonmotive nor ATP driven"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When a bacteria swim towards or away from chemical compounds, the phenomenon is known as bacterial chemotaxis. Swimming towards a chemical is termed as positive chemotaxis; swimming away is negative chemotaxis."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Peptidoglycan layer is present in large quantity in?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gram-positive bacteria",
            "b) Gram-negative bacteria",
            "c) Fungi",
            "d) Algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gram-positive bacteria usually have a much greater amount of peptidoglycan in their cell walls than do Gram-negative bacteria. It may account for 50 percent or more of the dry weight of the wall of some Gram-positive species, but only about 10 percent of the wall of Gram-negative bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "Peptidoglycan is made up of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) N-acetylglucosamine",
            "b) N-acetylmuramic acid",
            "c) N-acetylglucosamine, N-acetylmuramic acid",
            "d) N-acetylglucosamine, N-acetylmuramic acid, amino acids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Peptidoglycan differs somewhat in composition and structure from one species to another, but it is basically a polymer of N-acetylglucosamine, N-acetylmuramic acid, Amino acids like-L-alanine, D-alanine, D-glutamate, and a diamino acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "Teichoic acid present in Gram-positive bacteria can bind to which ion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fe ions",
            "b) Phosphorus ions",
            "c) Mg ions",
            "d) Sulphur ions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Teichoic acid bind magnesium ions and there is some evidence that they help to protect bacteria from thermal injury by providing an accessible pool of these cations for stabilization of the cytoplasmic membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "Cord factor is a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) protein",
            "b) teichoic acid derivative",
            "c) mycolic acid derivative",
            "d) carbohydrate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cord factor (trehalose dimycolate) is a mycolic acid derivative which is toxic and plays an important role in the diseases caused by C.diphtheriae and M.tuberculosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "The outer membrane of the Gram-negative cell wall is anchored to the underlying peptidoglycan by means of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Braun’s Lipoprotein",
            "b) Phospholipids",
            "c) Proteins",
            "d) Lipopolysaccharide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: The outer membrane of the Gram-negative cell wall is anchored to the underlying peptidoglycan by means of Braun’s lipoproteins. The membrane is a bilayered structure consisting mainly of phospholipids, proteins and lipopolysaccharides(LPS)."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "Which among the following acts as receptors for bacteriophage attachment in Gram-negative bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cilia",
            "b) O antigens",
            "c) Lipid A",
            "d) Teichoic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The polysaccharide O antigens which extend like whiskers from the membrane surface into the surrounding medium. Many of the serological properties of Gram-negative bacteria are attributable to O antigens like they can serve as receptors for bacteriophage attachment."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "NAG and NAM of peptidoglycan layer is linked by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) beta-(1,4) glycosidic linkage",
            "b) alpha-(1,4) glycosidic linkage",
            "c) alpha-(1,6) glycosidic linkage",
            "d) beta-(1,6) glycosidic linkage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The outer membrane can allow smaller molecules such as nucleosides, oligosaccharides, monosaccharides, peptides and amino acids to pass across by means of channels in special proteins called porins."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "Gram-negative bacteria are more resistant to antibiotics due to the presence of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thin peptidoglycan wall",
            "b) Outer lipopolysaccharide layer",
            "c) Porin proteins",
            "d) Teichoic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: N-acetylglucosamine (NAG) and N-acetylmuramic acid (NAM) of peptidoglycan layer are linked by beta-(1, 4) glycosidic linkage. Each strand contains from 10 to 65 disaccharide units."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "Which of the following are present in teichoic acids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ribitol residues",
            "b) glycerol residues",
            "c) glucose residues",
            "d) ribitol or glycerol residues"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Gram-negative bacteria consists of an outer membrane made up of lipopolysaccharides beneath the thin peptidoglycan layer. The outer membrane serves as a barrier to various external chemicals and enzymes that could damage the cell. It also protects the bacteria from antibiotics."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "Bayer’s junctions are sites which help in joining which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cytoplasmic membrane and outer membrane",
            "b) outer membrane and capsule",
            "c) cytoplasmic membrane and periplasmic space",
            "d) peptidoglycan layer and cytoplasmic membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The teichoic acids are water soluble polymers, containing ribitol or glycerol residues joined through phosphodiester linkages. The glycerol or ribitol is joined to a sugar residue such as glucose, galactose or N-acetyl glucosamine."
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "Polyisoprenoid branched-chain lipids, are present in which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Archaebacteria",
            "b) Eubacteria",
            "c) Archaebacteria and Eubacteria",
            "d) Cannot be determined"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Archaebacteria, the lipids are polyisoprenoid branched-chain lipids, in which long-chain branched alcohols(phytanols) are ether linked to glycerol. In Eubacteria, the phospholipids are phosphoglycerides, in which straight-chain fatty acids are ester-linked to glycerol."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "Cytoplasmic membrane and the cell material bounded by it plus the outer membrane of cell is known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Protoplast",
            "b) Cytoplast",
            "c) Spheroplast",
            "d) Cell membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A protoplast is that portion of a bacterial cell consisting of the cytoplasmic membrane and the cell material bounded by it. When the cell has two membranes, the cytoplasmic membrane of the protoplast plus the outer membrane of the cell wall, the cell is called a spheroplast rather than protoplast."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Which among the following is associated with the export of exocellular enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) central mesosomes",
            "b) peripheral mesosomes",
            "c) thylakoids",
            "d) nucleus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Peripheral mesosomes show only a shallow penetration into the cytoplasm, are not restricted to a central location, and are not associated with nuclear material and they are involved in the export of exocellular enzymes such as penicillinase."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "Ribosomes of prokaryotes have a sedimentation coefficient of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 90S",
            "b) 80S",
            "c) 50S",
            "d) 70S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ribosomes of prokaryotes have a sedimentation coefficient of 70S and are composed of two subunits, a 50S and a 30S subunit. But the ribosomes of eukaryotes have a sedimentation coefficient of 80S and are composed of a 60S and a 40S subunit."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "Poly-beta-hydroxybutyrate(PHB) present in aerobic bacteria can serve as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) a reserve carbon and energy source",
            "b) a reserve source of phosphate",
            "c) acceptor of oxygen",
            "d) provides buoyancy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A polymer found in aerobic bacteria, especially under high-carbon,low-nitrogen culture conditions, is a chlorofoam-soluble, lipid like material, poly-beta-hydroxybutyrate(PHB), which can serve as a reserve carbon and energy source."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "Which among the following compound when added to cytoplasmic membrane helps in maintaining the rigidity of cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lipopolysaccharide",
            "b) hopanoid",
            "c) phosphoglycerides",
            "d) amino acids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hopanoids are hydrophobic chemical compounds which when added to the cytoplasmic membrane forms a stable and hard compound that helps in maintaining the rigidity of cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "The nucleoid can be made visible under the light microscope by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Methylene blue",
            "b) Iodine",
            "c) Nile blue",
            "d) Feulgen staining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bacteria consist of nucleotide, consisting of a single, circular DNA molecule in which all the genes are linked and it is not a discrete nucleus. The nucleoid can be made visible under the light microscope by Feulgen staining,which is specific for DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "What helps in the heat resistance of the endospore?",
        "Options": [
            "a) calcium-DPA complex",
            "b) water",
            "c) methylene",
            "d) calcium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All endospores contain large amounts of dipicolinic acid (DPA). It occurs in combination with large amounts of calcium and is probably located in the central part of the spore. The calcium-DPA complex plays a role in the heat resistance of endospores."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods can be utilized for removing peripheral proteins of the cytoplasmic membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) treatment by detergents",
            "b) osmotic shock",
            "c) heat application",
            "d) destruction of the membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cysts are dormant, thick-walled, desiccation-resistant forms that develop by differentiation of a vegetative cell and which can later germinate under suitable conditions. In some ways cysts resemble endospores but they do not have the high heat resistance of endospores."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "Which of the following are true for cytoplasmic membrane?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hydrophilic barrier",
            "b) hydrophobic barrier",
            "c) site of generation of protonmotive force",
            "d) hydrophobic barrier and site of generation of protonmotive force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Peripheral proteins are loosely attached to cytoplasmic membrane and can be removed by mild treatments such as osmotic shock. On the other hand, integral proteins can be removed only by the destruction of the membrane, as with treatment by detergents."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "The organisms which can use reduced inorganic compounds as electron donors are known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chemotrophs",
            "b) organotrophs",
            "c) lithotrophs",
            "d) phototrophs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Organisms that can use reduced inorganic compounds as electron donors are termed as lithotrophs. Some organisms which use organic compounds as electron donors are called organotrophs."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the nutritional characterization of Escherichia coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemotrophic",
            "b) Organotrophic",
            "c) Autotrophic",
            "d) Chemotrophic, Organotrophic, Heterotrophic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Escherichia coli are chemotrophic, organotrophic, and heterotrophic organisms. This means they rely on chemical compounds for their energy and uses organic compounds as electron donors. They also require organic compounds as their carbon source and are hence heterotrophic."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Which of the following amino acids require sulphur for their synthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tryptophan",
            "b) methionine",
            "c) cystine",
            "d) methionine and cystine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sulphur is needed for synthesis of certain amino acids like methionine and cystine. Some bacteria require organic sulphur compounds, some are capable of utilizing inorganic sulphur compounds and some can even use elemental sulphur."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Phosphorus is essential component of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) teichoic acid",
            "b) nucleotides",
            "c) phospholipids",
            "d) teichoic acid, nucleotides, phospholipids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Phosphorus, usually supplied in the form of phosphate, is an essential component of nucleotides, nucleic acids, phospholipids, teichoic acids, and other components."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "Which of the following are trace elements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Potassium ion",
            "b) Sodium ion",
            "c) Copper ion",
            "d) Magnesium ion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Trace elements are those elements that are needed at very low concentrations such as Zinc ion, Copper ion, Manganese ion, Nickel ion, Cobalt ion, Boron ion, Molybdenum ion. They always occur as contaminants of other components of culture media in amounts sufficient to support bacterial growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Which of the following ions are cofactors for various enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Potassium ion",
            "b) Iron ion",
            "c) Magnesium ion and Iron ion",
            "d) Calcium ion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Among the trace elements, iron ion, magnesium ion, zinc ion, manganese ion and copper ion are known to be cofactors for various enzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "Which of the following are functions of water in the culture medium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) nutrients must be in aqueous solution",
            "b) cofactor of enzymes",
            "c) provides resistance to sudden transient temperature changes",
            "d) it is a chemical reactant, nutrients must also be present in aqueous solution and provide resistance to sudden temperature changes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most bacteria do not require Na ion, but certain marine bacteria, cyanobacteria and photosynthetic bacteria do require it. For those members of the archaeobacteria known as the “red extreme halophiles”, the requirement is astonishing: they cannot grow with less than 12 to 15 percent NaCl. They require this high level of NaCl for maintenance of the integrity of their cell walls and for the stability and activity of certain of their enzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "Chromatium okenii uses which of the following compound as electron donor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrogen sulphide",
            "b) Fatty acids",
            "c) Alcohol",
            "d) Succinate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:d\nExplanation: In the case of bacteria, all nutrients must be in aqueous solution before they can enter the cells. The high specific heat of water provides resistance to sudden, transient temperature changes in the environment. Water is also a chemical reactant, being required for the many hydrolytic reactions carried out by a cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Which of the following bacteria can grow both as chemolithotrophs or as chemoorganotrophs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrosomonas sp.",
            "b) Pseudomonas pseudoflava",
            "c) Rhodospirillum rubrum",
            "d) Chromatium okenii"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chromatium okenii are photolithotrophs i.e., they are phototrophic bacteria that uses inorganic compounds as their source of electrons. They use Hydrogen Sulphide as its electron donor, oxidizing it to elemental sulphur."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of beef extract?",
        "Options": [
            "a) product resulting from the digestion of proteinaceous materials",
            "b) aqueous extract of lean beef tissue",
            "c) aqueous extract of yeast cells",
            "d) complex carbohydrate obtained from certain marine algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Beef extract, a complex raw material used as ingredient for preparing bacteriological media is an aqueous extract of lean beef tissue concentrated to a paste."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used as a solidifying agent for media?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beef extract",
            "b) Peptone",
            "c) Agar",
            "d) Yeast extract"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Agar is used as a solidification agent for media and is not considered a source of nutrient to the bacteria. Agar dissolved in aqueous solutions, gels when the temperature is reduced below 45 degrees Celsius."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a rich source of B vitamins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peptone",
            "b) Yeast extract",
            "c) Beef extract",
            "d) Agar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Yeast extract which is an aqueous extract of yeast cells is a very rich source of the B vitamins and it also contains apart from it organic nitrogen and carbon compounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "The isolation of gonorrhea-causing organism, Neisseria gonorrhoeae by the use of certain antibiotics in media is an example of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Selective media",
            "b) Differential media",
            "c) Enriched media",
            "d) Assay media"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The isolation of gonorrhea-causing organism, Neisseria gonorrhoeae, from a clinical specimen is facilitated by the use of media containing certain antibiotics; these antibiotics do not affect N.gonorrhoeae but do inhibit the growth of contaminating bacteria. This is an example of selective media as it allows the growth of only a particular microorganism."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "Nutrient broth, a liquid media contains beef extract and peptone respectively in how much amounts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2%, 0.4%",
            "b) 0.1%, 0.6%",
            "c) 0.3%, 0.5%",
            "d) 0.7%, 0.3%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nutrient broth which is the most widely used media in general bacteriological work, contains 0.3 percent beef extract and 0.5 percent peptone. It may also contain if required 0.8 percent NaCl to maintain the salt concentration."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "Which of the following instrument is used for sterilizing the media after it has been prepared?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autoclave",
            "b) Laminar Air Flow Chamber",
            "c) Inoculum Needle",
            "d) Incubator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Autoclave is a type of pressure cooker which has steam at 121.5 degree Celsius and under 15 psi pressure. This steam kills all the microbes present in the media and sterilizes it."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a Complex media for fungal growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nutrient broth",
            "b) Luria-Bertani media",
            "c) Potato Dextrose Agar(PDA) media",
            "d) Mac Conkey Agar media"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If microbial growth is found in liquid media, then the media shows turbidity but no colony formation can be observed. But in solid media microbial growth can be observed by colony formation as the media is already turbid due to the presence of agar powder."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "Which of the following are functions of Maintenance Media?",
        "Options": [
            "a) used for assay of vitamins, amino acids",
            "b) used for determining the bacterial content",
            "c) used for determining the type of growth produced by bacteria",
            "d) used for the maintenance of the viability and physiological characteristics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Complex media is a chemically undefined media where the exact composition is not known. For fungal growth, complex media used is Potato Dextrose Agar(PDA) media."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "Which of the following bacteria requires nicotinic acid as a growth factor in their media?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proteus vulgaris",
            "b) Nitrosomonas sp.",
            "c) E. coli",
            "d) Leuconostoc mesenteroides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Satisfactory maintenance of the viability and physiological characteristics of culture over time may require a medium different from that which is optimum for growth. Prolific, rapid growth may also be associated with rapid death of the cells at the end of the growth phase. Thus, a maintenance medium is required then."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "The temperature that allows for most rapid growth during a short period of time is known as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum Temperature",
            "b) Maximum Temperature",
            "c) Optimum Temperature",
            "d) Growth Temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The temperature that allows for the most rapid growth during a short period of time(12 to 24 hrs) is known as the optimum temperature. Maximum temperature for growth lies very close to the optimum temperature whereas minimum temperature for growth is usually much lower than the optimum."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "Mesophiles are group of bacteria that grow within the temperature range of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-20 degree Celsius",
            "b) 25-40 degree Celsius",
            "c) 45-60 degree Celsius",
            "d) more than 60 degree Celsius"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mesophiles grow best within a temperature range of 25 to 40 degree Celsius. All bacteria that are pathogenic for humans and warm-blooded animals are mesophiles, most growing best at about body temperature(37 degree Celsius)."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Which of the following factors are responsible for the stability of thermophiles at high temperatures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) increased leakage of cell components",
            "b) presence of large no. of polar amino acids and alpha-helix protein",
            "c) thermal stability of ribosomes",
            "d) presence of Inositol diphosphate and thermal stability of ribosomes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Factors that have been implicated in the ability to grow at high temperature is increased thermal stability of ribosomes. The cytoplasmic membrane of thermophiles also contains Inositol diphosphate or Inositol triphosphate which can tolerate high temperature and maintains the fluidity of the membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "The bacterium Staphylococcus aureus is which type of bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Psychrophile",
            "b) Mesophile",
            "c) Thermophile",
            "d) Mesophile and psychrophile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Staphylococcus aureus is a mesophilic bacteria which can grow in the temperature range of 6.5-46 degree Celsius and has an optimum temperature at 30-37 degree Celsius."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "The Reactive Oxygen Species(ROS) produced by some bacteria are degraded by which of the following enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peroxidase",
            "b) Lyase",
            "c) Catalase",
            "d) Superoxide dismutase, Catalase and Peroxidase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Microaerophilic bacteria require low levels of oxygen for growth but it cannot tolerate the level of oxygen present in an air atmosphere."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "Which of the following ROS is a powerful oxidizing agent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superoxide radical",
            "b) Hydrogen peroxide",
            "c) Hydroxyl radical",
            "d) Singlet oxygen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In some cases, oxygen may accept large number of free electrons and produces Reactive Oxygen Species (ROS). They are harmful as they degrade macromolecules required for growth and nutrition. But aerobic bacteria contains three different enzymes-Superoxide dismutase, Catalase and Peroxidase which eliminates the different ROS."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "The GasPak system is suitable for which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aerobic bacteria",
            "b) Anaerobic bacteria",
            "c) Facultatively anaerobic bacteria",
            "d) Microaerophilic bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Superoxide radicals form toxic substances such as hydrogen peroxide. Hydrogen peroxide is not a free radical, but it is a powerful oxidizing agent."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "Which of the following are functions of phosphates used in the preparation of media?",
        "Options": [
            "a) they act as buffer",
            "b) source of phosphorous",
            "c) act as “reserve alkali”",
            "d) they act as buffer and is a source of phosphorous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: GasPak Jar is a system for anaerobic bacteria. In this jar media is inoculated and placed in the jar. To this water is added, causing the evolution of Hydrogen gas and Carbon dioxide. Hydrogen gas reacts with oxygen on the surface of the palladium catalyst, forming water and establishing anaerobic conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "The optimum pH for the growth of most bacteria lies between _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5-9",
            "b) 6.5-7.5",
            "c) 2-3.5",
            "d) 9-9.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The phosphates are used widely in the preparation of media because they are the only inorganic agents that buffer in the physiologically important range around neutrality and that are relatively non-toxic to microorganisms. In addition, they provide a source of phosphorous, which is an essential element of growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "Growth of bacteria or microorganisms refer to __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) an increase in the size of an individual organism",
            "b) an increase in the mass of an individual organism",
            "c) changes in the total population",
            "d) an increase in number of cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Growth denotes the increase in number of cells beyond that present in the original inoculum. It does not refer to an increase in size or mass of an individual organism."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "Which of the following bacterial species divides by fragmentation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacillus subtilis",
            "b) Streptococcus faecalis",
            "c) Rhodopseudomonas acidophila",
            "d) Nocardia sp."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most important mode of cell division in the usual growth of bacterial population is transverse binary fission, in which a single cell divides after developing a transverse septum(crosswall)."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "Rhodopseudomonas acidophila reproduces by which of the following methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Binary fission",
            "b) Budding",
            "c) Fragmentation",
            "d) Sporulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bacteria that produce extensive filamentous growth, such as Nocardia sp. reproduce by fragmentation of the filaments into small bacillary or coccoid cells, each of which gives rise to new growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "The synthesis of new membrane material during reproduction in Gram-positive cells is performed by which of the following organelles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nucleus",
            "b) Mesosome",
            "c) Endoplasmic Reticulum",
            "d) Cytoplasmic membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rhodopseudomonas acidophila reproduces by budding, a process in which a small protuberance(bud) develops at one end of the cell; this enlarges and eventually develops into a new cell which separates from the parent."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "Equatorial ridge formation in the cell wall takes place in which of the following bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptomyces sp.",
            "b) Bacillus subtilis",
            "c) Streptococcus faecalis",
            "d) Escherichia coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Streptomyces sp. produce many spores per organism by developing crosswalls(septation) at the hyphen tips and then each spore gives rise to a new organism."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "When septum formation occurs near the pole of cell then it results in the formation of daughter cell known as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) microcell",
            "b) macrocell",
            "c) minicell",
            "d) daughter cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first step in reproduction is an inward growth of the cytoplasmic membrane at the middle of the cell. A mesosome which is usually attached to the cytoplasmic membrane in Gram-positive cells have a role in the synthesis of new membrane material."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "A bleb or fold like formation occurs in which of the following bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhodopseudomonas acidophila",
            "b) Bacillus subtilis",
            "c) E.coli",
            "d) Streptococcus faecalis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Streptococcus faecalis, all of the new wall material formed by the dividing cell is made during synthesis of the septum which begins beneath an equatorial ridge in the cell wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not occur during binary fission in bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell elongation",
            "b) Cytokinesis",
            "c) DNA duplication",
            "d) Spindle formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In some mutants of E.coli and B.subtilis, septum forms near the pole resulting in a very small daughter cell termed as minicell which lacks DNA and therefore cannot multiply."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "The portion of the growth curve where rapid growth of bacteria is observed is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lag phase",
            "b) Logarithmic phase",
            "c) Stationary phase",
            "d) Decline phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A typical growth curve has four regions. An initial period of no growth known as the lag phase, followed by rapid growth known as logarithmic phase. No growth is observed in the stationary phase and death phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "In the growth equation: n = 3.3 (log10 N – log10 No), n stands for ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) total population",
            "b) initial population",
            "c) number of generations",
            "d) growth constant"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bacteria show growth by following binary fission as means of reproduction. Thus, if we start with a single bacterium, the increase in population is by geometric progression."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "Lag phase is also known as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) period of initial adjustment",
            "b) transitional period",
            "c) generation time",
            "d) period of rapid growth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the above formula, n stands for the number of generations that have taken place after the growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "The generation time for E.coli is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 minutes",
            "b) 35 minutes",
            "c) 2 minutes",
            "d) 13 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the lag phase, the bacteria maybe deficient in enzymes or coenzymes which must first be synthesized and thus time is required for adjustments in the physical environment. So it is also known as a period of initial adjustment."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "During exponential phase, growth rate is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) same as generation time",
            "b) reciprocal of generation time",
            "c) time required for population to double",
            "d) rate of doubling population"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The generation time for E.coli at a temperature of 37 degrees Celsius lies in the range of 15-20 minutes generally."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "In which of the following phase secondary metabolites are produced during growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lag phase",
            "b) Log/Exponential phase",
            "c) Stationary phase",
            "d) Death phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: During exponential growth, the growth rate (R) i.e., the number of generations per hour, is the reciprocal of the generation time g. Growth rate is the slope of the straight line obtained when the log number of cells is plotted against time."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "Which phase shows the reproduction rate equal to the equivalent death rate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Log phase",
            "b) Stationary phase",
            "c) Death phase",
            "d) Lag phase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During the stationary phase, there is complete utilization of the nutrients present in media and thus produce secondary metabolites which are then used in different industries."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "Which of the following is used to grow bacterial culture continuously?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemostat",
            "b) Hemostat",
            "c) Coulter-Counter",
            "d) Turbidostat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the stationary phase there is a complete cessation of division and thus the reproduction rate is balanced by an equivalent death rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "The average size of the cells in the exponential phase is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) larger than the initial size",
            "b) smaller than the initial size",
            "c) equal to the initial size",
            "d) maybe smaller or larger than the initial size"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chemostat is used for continuous cultivation. This system depends on the fact that the concentration of an essential nutrient within the culture vessel will control the growth rate of the cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an indirect method for measuring bacterial growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell count",
            "b) Cell mass",
            "c) Cell activity",
            "d) Both Cell mass and Cell activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cell activity is an indirect method for measuring bacterial growth by relating the degree of biochemical activity to the size of the population."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "Which of the following instrument is used for the bacterial count?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Petroff-Hausser counting chamber",
            "b) Microscope",
            "c) Chemostat",
            "d) Turbidostat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bacteria can be counted easily and accurately with the Petroff-Hausser counting chamber. This is a special slide accurately ruled into squares that are 1/400 mm2  in area. A suspension of unstained bacteria can be counted in the chamber, using a phase contrast microscope."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used for a viable count of a culture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct microscopic count",
            "b) Plate-count method",
            "c) Membrane-filter count",
            "d) Plate-count method and membrane-filter count"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main disadvantage of direct counting of cell numbers is that there is no way to determine whether the cells being counted are viable. To determine the viable count of culture, we must use a technique that allows viable cells to multiply, such as the plate-count method or membrane-filter method."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the relationship between optical density and cell mass?",
        "Options": [
            "a) exponentially proportional",
            "b) linearly proportional",
            "c) inversely proportional",
            "d) not related"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the plate count method, the formula used is as follows:\nNumber of bacteria per ml = Number of colonies counted on plate X dilution of sample.\nThus number of bacteria directly depends on the dilution of sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "How many cells present per milliliter in a bacterial culture can make the culture turbid?",
        "Options": [
            "a)1 cell",
            "b)1000 cells",
            "c)1 lakh cells",
            "d)107-108  cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The photoelectric colorimeter used for measuring bacterial population, measures optical density (a function of light intensity) which is almost linearly proportional to cell mass."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a direct measurement of growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Determination of nitrogen content",
            "b) Turbidimetric methods",
            "c) Determination of Dry weight of cells",
            "d) Measurement of a specific chemical change produced on a constituent of the medium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bacteria in a suspension absorb and scatter the light passing through them so that a culture of more than 107 to 108 cells per milliliter appears turbid to the naked eye. Then a spectrophotometer or colorimeter can be used for turbidimetric measurements."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used for enumeration of bacteria in vaccines and cultures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Microscopic Count",
            "b) Membrane filter",
            "c) Plate count",
            "d) Dry weight determination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Both dead as well as living cells contribute to turbidity. However, turbidity cannot be measured for cultures grown in deeply colored media or cultures that contain suspended material other than bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "Colony-forming units per ml is the unit of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Microscopic count",
            "b) Electronic enumeration",
            "c) Plate count",
            "d) Turbidimetric measurement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To measure the dry weight of cells is the most direct approach for quantitative measurement. All others are indirect methods and is applicable only in special circumstances."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "Isolation of pure culture refers to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) purification of culture",
            "b) introduction of inoculum",
            "c) separation of a single colony",
            "d) to grow microorganisms on a surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To study the characteristics of one species, that species must be separated from all the other colonies of species, i.e., it must be isolated in pure culture."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a physical method for selection of pure culture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat treatment",
            "b) pH of the media",
            "c) Cell size and motility",
            "d) Use of dilute media"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enrichment media is a selective method used for the enhancement of the growth of a particular bacterial species."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "In physical method of selection, endospore-forming bacteria can be obtained by heating the mixed culture to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70 degree C for 10 minutes",
            "b) 80 degree C for 10 minutes",
            "c) 60 degree C for 10 minutes",
            "d) 90 degree C for 10 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Use of dilute media is a chemical method of selection in which a mixed culture was inoculated into a very dilute medium to isolate a particular bacterial colony."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "Vibrio cholerae can grow in a medium with a pH of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.5",
            "b) 7.0",
            "c) 8.5",
            "d) 2.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: To select for endospore-forming bacteria, a mixed culture can be heated to 80 degrees C for 10 minutes before being used to inoculate culture media. Vegetative cells will be killed by this treatment but endospores will survive and subsequently germinate and grow."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "Disease-producing species occurring in a mixed culture can be selected by taking advantage of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) its pathogenic properties",
            "b) special carbon source",
            "c) special nitrogen source",
            "d) toxic chemicals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vibrio cholerae, cholera causing bacterium can be selected from a medium with a ph of 8.5; most intestinal bacteria are unable to grow at this pH."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "Treponema sp. can be selected by taking advantage of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) small cell size",
            "b) motility",
            "c) dilute media",
            "d) small cell diameter and bacterial motility"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the biological method of selection, a disease producing species occurring in a mixed culture can often be selected by taking advantage of its pathogenic properties. Others are chemical methods of selection."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "Roll-tube technique is used to isolate ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) aerobes",
            "b) anaerobes",
            "c) facultatives",
            "d) stringent anaerobes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Roll-tube technique which is a modification of streak-plate technique is used to isolate stringent anaerobes."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "In pour-plate method, the medium should be maintained at what temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 37 degree C",
            "b) 67 degree C",
            "c) 45 degree C",
            "d) 0 degree C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In pour plate method, the medium is maintained in a liquid state at a temperature of 45 degrees C to allow thorough distribution of inoculum."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "Which of the following method can be used to determine the number of bacteria quantitatively?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streak-plate",
            "b) Spread-plate",
            "c) Pour plate",
            "d) Pour-plate and spread plate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Due to a higher degree of dilution, pour-plate and spread-plate techniques may be performed in a quantitative manner to determine the number of bacteria present in a specimen."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not performed in lyophilization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) agar slant is covered with mineral oil",
            "b) cell suspension is frozen at -60 degree to -78 degree C",
            "c) vials are connected to high-vacuum line",
            "d) bacterial sample is dehydrated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The streak-plate technique does not require dilution as a portion of the mixed culture is placed on the surface of an agar medium and streaked across the surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a function of cryoprotective agents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) for long-term preservation of cultures",
            "b) prevents cell damage due to ice crystal formation",
            "c) prevents formation of ice",
            "d) to trap the liquid nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In lyophilization or freeze-drying, a dense cell suspension is placed in small vials and frozen at -60 degree to -78 degree C. The vials are then connected to a high-vacuum line. The ice present in the frozen suspension sublimes under the vacuum and results in dehydration of the bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "What is the temperature of liquid nitrogen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) -120 degree C",
            "b) 0 degree C",
            "c) -150 degree C",
            "d) -196 degree C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For preservation at low temperatures the cells are prepared as a dense suspension in a medium containing cryoprotective agents such as glycerol or dimethyl sulphoxide which prevents cell damage due to ice crystal formation."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "Nichrome loop wire is used in which of the following techniques?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pour-plate",
            "b) Streak-plate",
            "c) Spread-plate",
            "d) Roll-tube technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Liquid nitrogen has a temperature of -196 degree C and is used for the storage of culture medium."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "Which device is used to pick a single bacterial cell from a mixed culture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) microscope",
            "b) micropipette",
            "c) microprobe",
            "d) micromanipulator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the streak plate technique, with the help of a nichrome loop wire, a portion of mixed culture is placed on the surface of an agar medium and streaked across the surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "The National Collection of Type Cultures is situated in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) France",
            "b) England",
            "c) Germany",
            "d) Japan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In England, the National Collection of Type Culture is in London which is a large central collection whose main purpose would be the acquisition, preservation, and distribution of authentic cultures of living organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "The American Type Culture Collection, located in Rockville, Maryland in the year 1980 has a collection of bacterial strain in what numbers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10,000",
            "b) 11,000",
            "c)  500",
            "d) 11,500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the US the major collection is the American Type Culture Collection, located in Rockville, Maryland. In 1980 the collection included the following number of strains: bacteria-11,500; bacteriophages-300; algae-130; protozoa-720; fungi and fungal viruses-13700 etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "Which of the following has a larger diameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) well-separated colonies",
            "b) crowded colonies",
            "c) young colonies",
            "d) old colonies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Well-separated colonies have a larger diameter than those which are crowded together because widely separated colonies are subject to less competition for nutrients and less inhibition by toxic products of metabolism."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "What is the color of colonies of Staphylococcus aureus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pink",
            "b) Red",
            "c) Violet",
            "d) Gold"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For several species of pathogenic species, the surface texture of colonies may bear a relation to virulence. For example, Smooth colonies of S.pneumoniae or of Salmonella species are usually virulent, whereas Rough colonies are not."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Pyoverdin is which type of pigment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) water-insoluble pigment",
            "b) water-soluble pigment",
            "c) fluorescent pigment",
            "d) sparingly water-soluble pigment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Staphylococcus aureus produces and retains water-insoluble pigments which give golden color to their colonies."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "Growth in broth cultures occurs mainly in the form of__________",
        "Options": [
            "a) slightly turbid",
            "b) heavy surface pellicle",
            "c) sediment",
            "d) viscous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pyoverdin is a fluorescent pigment and is water-soluble in which the agar medium around the colonies glows white or blue-green when exposed to ultraviolet light. It is produced by P.aeruginosa."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "Which bacteria among the following produces a water-insoluble pigment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mycobacterium kansasii",
            "b) Pseudomonas aeruginosa",
            "c) Chromobacterium violaceum",
            "d) Pseudomonas chlororaphis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Growth in broth cultures occurs mainly in the form of a heavy surface pellicle and the medium below the pellicle is only slightly turbid."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "The respiratory chain of bacteria is associated with the _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mitochondrial membrane",
            "b) cytoplasmic membrane",
            "c) cell wall",
            "d) cytoplasm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The respiratory chain of bacteria is associated with the cytoplasmic membrane and that of eukaryotes is present in the mitochondrial membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "The prosthetic group of a cytochrome contains how many iron atoms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) two",
            "c) three",
            "d) four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cytochromes are a major class of oxidative enzymes whose prosthetic group is a derivative of heme and contains a single iron atom, which is responsible for the oxidative or reductive properties of the enzyme."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Among the following which can directly react with oxygen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cytochrome c",
            "b) cytochrome c1",
            "c) cytochrome a",
            "d) cytochrome a3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cytochrome a and a3 together are called cytochrome oxidase, both of them contain copper. But only cytochrome a3 can react directly with oxygen."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "How many ATP molecules are formed for per molecule of FADH2 reoxidized?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Three ATP are formed per molecule of NADH2 reoxidized but only two ATP molecules are formed per molecule of FADH2 reoxidized, because of the high energy of NADH2."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "In photosynthesis by green plants, algae, cyanobacteria which of the following acts as terminal electron acceptor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Oxygen",
            "c) NADP+",
            "d) FAD+"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In aerobic respiration the terminal electron acceptor is oxygen; in anaerobic respiration the final electron acceptor is nitrate, sulphate and carbonate."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "Keq is greater than 1.0 depending on which of the following conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) standard free energy change is negative",
            "b) standard free energy change is positive",
            "c) chemical reaction proceeds in reverse direction",
            "d) products are not formed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In photosynthesis by green plants, algae and cyanobacteria, water serves as a primary electron donor and NADP+ as a terminal electron acceptor."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "Glycolysis can occur in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) aerobic cells",
            "b) anaerobic cells",
            "c) both aerobic and anaerobic cells",
            "d) neither aerobic and anaerobic cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Glycolysis does not require the presence of oxygen and therefore can occur in both aerobic and anaerobic cells. In anaerobic cells glucose is degraded into fermentation products and in aerobic cells glucose is degraded into carbon dioxide and water."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "Xylulose-5-phosphate is an intermediate in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Glycolysis",
            "b) Pentose Phosphate Pathway",
            "c) Entner-Doudoroff Pathway",
            "d) Fermentation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The step where glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate is oxidized to 1,3-Biphosphoglycerate is oxidative-level phosphorylation where a pair of electrons (two hydrogen atoms) is removed."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "How many molecules of glucose-6-phosphate are regenerated in pentose-phosphate pathway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Epimerization of ribulose-6-phosphate yields xylulose-5-phosphate and ribulose-5-phosphate in Pentose-phosphate pathway. These two compounds are the starting point for a series of transketolase and transaldolase reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "Which of the following are propionic acid bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptococcus",
            "b) Acetobacter",
            "c) Clostridium",
            "d) Veillonella"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: From 6 molecules of ribulose-5-phosphate, 5 molecules of glucose-6-phosphate are again regenerated."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "What is the other name of glycolysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PPP cycle",
            "b) TCA cycle",
            "c) C4 cycle",
            "d) EMP pathway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Entner-Doudoroff pathway is found both in aerobic and anaerobic procaryotes, particularly among Gram-negative bacteria but not in eukaryotes."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "How many ATPs are paid back during the Pentose phosphate Pathway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Veillonella is a propionic acid bacteria that produce propionic acid, acetic acid and carbon dioxide as fermentation products."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "Stickland reaction is the alternative name for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lactic acid fermentation",
            "b) Alcoholic fermentation",
            "c) Mixed acid fermentation",
            "d) Amino acid fermentation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: EMP is named after the scientists that proposed the pathway, and they are Embden, Meyerhof, Parnas. It involves the conversion of glucose into pyruvic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "The TCA Cycle is an _____________ pathway.",
        "Options": [
            "a) catabolic",
            "b) anabolic",
            "c) amphibolic",
            "d) respiratory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The TCA cycle is an amphibolic cycle which means that it functions not only in catabolic (breakdown) but also in anabolic (synthesis) reactions."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "Which of the following intermediates of TCA cycle act as amino acid precursors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxaloacetic acid",
            "b) succinic acid",
            "c) citric acid",
            "d) acetyl CoA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oxaloacetic acid and alpha-ketoglutaric acid are some of the intermediates of TCA cycle which act as amino acid precursors.Oxaloacetate forms aspartate which then gives us lysine and threonine."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "Which pathway will result in the production of four carbon dioxide molecules, two ATP molecules, NADH2 and FADH2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) glycolysis",
            "b) Krebs cycle",
            "c) Calvin cycle",
            "d) electron transport system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Krebs Cycle is another name for TCA cycle whose overall reaction is as follows:\n2Acetyl CoA+ 3H2O + 3NAD+ + FAD+ ADP+ Pi———> 4CO2+ 2CoA+ 2NADH2+ 2FADH2+ ATP."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "The TCA cycle is regulated by which of the following enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) citrate synthase",
            "b) isocitrate dehydrogenase",
            "c) malate dehydrogenase",
            "d) succinate dehydrogenase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: TCA cycle is regulated by the enzyme isocitrate dehydrogenase which is sensitive to feedback inhibition by high concentration of ATP and NADH2 and stimulation by high concentration of ADP and NAD. "
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "Which of the following pathway is common for oxidation of carbohydrates, lipids and amino acids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calvin cycle",
            "b) Electron transport chain",
            "c) TCA cycle",
            "d) Pentose phosphate pathway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Protein molecules are too large to pass into the cell, bacteria secrete exoenzymes called proteases that hydrolyze exogenous proteins to peptides, which are then transported into the cell cytoplasm."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "The enzymes present in glyoxylate cycle are which type of enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) reductase enzymes",
            "b) anaplerotic enzymes",
            "c) transferase enzymes",
            "d) hydrolase enzymes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Since acetyl-CoA is a common intermediate of carbohydrate, lipid, and amino acid metabolism so it enters the TCA cycle and hence TCA cycle is a common pathway for oxidation of carbohydrates, lipids and amino acids."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "Which molecule will combine with the four-carbon oxaloacetate in the TCA cycle to form the six-carbon citrate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lactic acid",
            "b) NADH",
            "c) ATP",
            "d) acetyl-CoA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: PEP is converted to oxaloacetate by the enzyme PEP carboxylase. This is a type of carbon dioxide fixing reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "The number of ATP molecules generated in TCA cycle is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 34",
            "b) 38",
            "c) 24",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specific enzymes for glyoxalate cycle are isocitrate lyase and malate synthase which carry out replenishment of the pool of intermediates of the TCA cycle and hence are known as anaplerotic enzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as a chemical reductant in bacterial photosynthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxygen",
            "b) water",
            "c) hydrogen sulphide",
            "d) ammonia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacteria that performs photosynthesis utilises inorganic compound H2S or organic compounds as chemical reductant instead of water."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "The region in which bacteriochlorophyll can absorb light is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ultraviolet region",
            "b) infrared region",
            "c) visible region",
            "d) microwave region"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Anoxygenic photosynthetic bacteria possess bacteriochlorophyll which absorbs light in the infrared region (725 to 1035 nm)."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Where are bacteriochlorophyll present in the cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) chloroplast",
            "b) cytoplasm",
            "c) mitochondria",
            "d) membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bacteriochlorophyll are not contained in the chloroplasts but are found in extensive membrane systems like the cytoplasmic membrane throughout the bacterial cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "Which of the following steps during electron transfer in anoxygenic photosynthesis is the ATP production step?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ferredoxin to ubiquinone",
            "b) ubiquinone to cyt b",
            "c) cyt b to cyt f",
            "d) cyt f to excited bacteriochlorophyll"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The energy released in electron transfer between cytochrome b and cytochrome f is used for photophosphorylation i.e., the generation of ATP from ADP and inorganic phosphate."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "An essential process connected with photosynthesis is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) photolysis",
            "b) synthesis of glucose",
            "c) photophosphorylation",
            "d) electron transfer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In cyclic photophosphorylation electron lost by pigment system II is not cycled back instead they are replaced by the light-generated breakdown of water, called photolysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "Chlorobium sp. is which type of bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Purple Sulphur Bacteria",
            "b) Purple Non-sulphur Bacteria",
            "c) Green Sulphur bacteria",
            "d) Green Non-sulphur bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Purple Sulphur bacteria contains bacteriochlorophyll a and bacteriochlorophyll b and it utilizes sulphur containing compound as chemical reductant."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "RuBisCO enzyme plays an important role in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) light phase",
            "b) dark phase",
            "c) electron transport chain",
            "d) TCA cycle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chlorobium sp. is a Green sulphur bacteria that contain bacteriochlorophyll c and d and utilizes sulphur as a chemical reductant in photosynthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "The final product of Calvin cycle is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RuBP",
            "b) Glucose",
            "c) Dihydroxy acetone phosphate",
            "d) Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the enzymatic reactions take place in the dark phase which does not depend on light. RuBisCO helps in the reaction between RuBP and carbon dioxide to form 3-phosphoglycerate."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "The dark reaction in photosynthesis is governed by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO2, temperature, and light",
            "b) CO2, light, and water",
            "c) water, temperature, and CO2",
            "d) oxygen, water, and temperature"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate is the final product of the Calvin cycle which again regenerates RuBP."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "Which of the following has no detectable ATPase activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cilia",
            "b) eukaryotic flagella",
            "c) bacterial flagella",
            "d) endoflagella"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacterial flagella appears to have no machinery for interconverting chemical and mechanical energy. Flagellin, the flagellar protein molecule, has no enzymatic activity i.e. no detectable ATPase activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Which force drives the flagellar rotation in bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ATP",
            "b) protonmotive force",
            "c) electrons",
            "d) water gradient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flagellar motor is driven by the protonmotive force, i.e., the force derived from the electric potential and the hydrogen gradient across the cytoplasmic membrane and not ATP."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "Rotary motor of flagella is associated with _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) M ring",
            "b) P ring",
            "c) L ring",
            "d) M and S ring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The rotary motor is believed to be the two elements in the basal body, the M ring and the S ring. The rod (which is connected to the filament by the hook) is fixed rigidly to the M ring, which rotates freely in the cytoplasmic membrane. The S ring is mounted rigidly on the cell wall."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "The entry of glycerol into the bacterial cells is by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) passive diffusion",
            "b) facilitated diffusion",
            "c) group translocation",
            "d) active diffusion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In passive diffusion no substance in the membrane interacts specifically with the solute molecules. The difference in concentration gradient governs the rate of the inward flow of solute molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "Porter or permease is located in the _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cytoplasmic membrane",
            "b) cell membrane",
            "c) nuclear membrane",
            "d) outer membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The entry of glycerol into the bacterial cells is an example of facilitated diffusion which involves the use of a specific protein carrier molecule called a porter for the diffusion of solutes."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "The reaction for the transfer of phosphoryl group of phosphoenol pyruvate to the sugar molecule requires which ion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mg2+",
            "b) Fe2+",
            "c) O",
            "d) PO42-"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Porter or permease is a specific protein carrier molecule that is required in facilitated diffusion which combines reversibly with the solute molecules and releases it into the inside of cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "HPr stands for ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) heat-stable carrier protein",
            "b) hydrogen carrier protein",
            "c) pyruvate dehydrogenase",
            "d) high-energy protein"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Both the passive diffusion and facilitated diffusion does not require metabolic energy."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "In phosphotransferase system(PTS), the sugar-phosphate is released inside the cell by which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enzyme I",
            "b) Enzyme II",
            "c) Enzyme III",
            "d) HPr"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reaction for the transfer of phosphoryl group of phosphoenol pyruvate to the sugar molecule requires Mg2+, the products formed are sugar phosphate and pyruvate."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "Mannitol enzyme II has been purified from _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) E.coli",
            "b) Salmonella typhimurium",
            "c) Saccharomyces cerevisiae",
            "d) Lactobacillus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Heat-stable protein (HPr) is activated first by transfer of phosphate group from the high-energy compound phosphoenol pyruvate inside the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "The biosynthesis of proline takes place from ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) aspartic acid",
            "b) glutamic acid",
            "c) pyruvic acid",
            "d) alpha-keto glutaric acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The biosynthesis of proline takes place from glutamic acid in which the initial step utilizes metabolic energy in the form of ATP."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as a precursor for the activation of peptidoglycan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TP",
            "b) UDP",
            "c) NADPH",
            "d) GTP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sugars such as acetylglucosamine are activated by the attachment of a UDP to form a sugar-UDP precursor which is a general method involved in the biosynthesis of peptidoglycan."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "Bactoprenol is a ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) membrane phospholipid",
            "b) amino acid carrier",
            "c) fatty acid",
            "d) enzyme"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bactoprenol is a membrane phospholipid to which the AMA-UDP precursor is coupled during the synthesis of peptidoglycan."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "ATP dependent NADPH2 production is a process found in ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrosomonas",
            "b) Nitrobacter",
            "c) Rhizobium",
            "d) E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Electrons entering the respiratory chain from the oxidation of inorganic substrates by chemoautotrophic bacteria usually enter the chain at a higher point than those electrons from the oxidation of organic substrates by chemoheterotrophs. Thus chemoautotrophs are at a considerable energetic disadvantage for this reason."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "Each turn of Calvin cycle results in the fixation of ________ molecule of carbon dioxide.",
        "Options": [
            "a) one",
            "b) two",
            "c) four",
            "d) six"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nitrobacter is a chemiautotrophic bacteria that follows the process of ATP-dependent-NADPH2 production for the production of NADPH2 to be used with ATP for carbon dioxide fixation."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "The peptidoglycan layer of Staphylococcus aureus consists of a bridge between muramic acid peptides which is composed of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) alanine",
            "b) lysine",
            "c) proline",
            "d) gycine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Each turn of the Calvin cycle results in the fixation of one molecule of carbon dioxide. Carbon dioxide is fixed in a reaction with the acceptor molecule ribulose diphosphate."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "Binding proteins for active transport systems of Gram-negative bacteria are associated with ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cell membrane",
            "b) cytoplasmic membrane",
            "c) periplasmic space",
            "d) nuclear membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In Staphylococcus aureus a bridge composed of five glycine molecules can link two muramic acid peptides together. "
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "RNA consists of which combination of bases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thymine, Guanine, Cytosine",
            "b) Guanine, Cytosine, Uracil",
            "c) Thymine, Adenine, Guanine",
            "d) Adenine, Cytosine, Thymine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In DNA the nitrogenous bases like adenine binds with thymine, and guanine binds with cytosine. As a consequence, the ratio of adenine to thymine or of guanine to cytosine in double stranded DNA is always 1:1. So the amount of purines is equal to the amount of pyrimidines."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "Which of the following are features of semiconservative replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA replicates DNA molecule",
            "b) The DNA molecule produced contains two old templates",
            "c) One new DNA helix is formed",
            "d) DNA duplicates itself and the new chain contains old template strand and new complementary strand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: RNA is composed of nitrogenous bases adenine, guanine, cytosine and uracil. They do not contain thymine as present in DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "The chromosome of a typical bacterium is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) circular double-stranded DNA",
            "b) circular single-stranded DNA",
            "c) double-helix DNA",
            "d) single stranded DNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In semiconservative replication DNA duplication occurs in which one polynucleotide chain acts as a template to direct the synthesis of a new chain complementary to itself. It results in two daughter helices, each containing one old template strand and one new complementary strand."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "If the chromosome were extended linearly then it would approximately measure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 13500 micrometre",
            "b) 1000 micrometre",
            "c) 1250 micrometre",
            "d) 500 micrometre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The chromosome of a typical bacterium is a circular double-stranded DNA molecule; that is, the double helix for a complete genome has no free ends."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "The Lambda Bacteriophage carries out which of the following replication methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Theta mode",
            "b) Sigma mode",
            "c) Linear mode",
            "d) Does not carry out replication"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the chromosome were extended linearly then it would measure approximately 1250 micrometers or 1.25 mm which is several hundred times longer than the bacterial cell that contains it."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "Which of the following replication methods leads to the production of two circular daughter chromosomes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Theta mode",
            "b) Sigma mode",
            "c) Linear mode",
            "d) Rolling circle method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Lambda Bacteriophage follows sigma mode of replication in which the intermediate structures of DNA have sigma conformation. In this replication begins with the cleavage of a phosphodiester bond in one strand of the circular DNA molecule to produce a nick with 3’-OH and 5’-PO4 ends on that strand."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "DNA gyrase is a ______________ protein.",
        "Options": [
            "a) helix-unwinding",
            "b) helix-destabilizing",
            "c) helix-relaxing",
            "d) helix-winding"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Theta mode of replication a circular parental chromosome is replicated to two circular daughter chromosomes, in each of which one strand of the parental DNA molecule is conserved and a complementary strand is newly synthesized."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzyme removes the RNA primer with its 5’-nuclease activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA polymerase I",
            "b) DNA polymerase II",
            "c) DNA polymerase III",
            "d) RNA polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Procaryotes replicate their DNA from one origin or growing point per molecule while eukaryotes replicate from many origins per molecule. Replication may occur in either a unidirectional or bidirectional manner from each origin."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "Which of the following bacteria can synthesize all of the amino acids required for protein synthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E.coli",
            "b) Lactobacillus bravis",
            "c) Saccharomyces cerevisiae",
            "d) Bacillus subtilis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: According to the central dogma of molecular genetics, the first step is DNA replication, the second is a transcription and the last step is translation."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "RNAase is a single polypeptide chain of __________ amino acid residues.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 350",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 124"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Microorganisms differ widely in their ability to synthesize amino acids like E.coli can synthesize all of the amino acids required for protein synthesis, whereas lactic acid bacteria cannot."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "Protein synthesis in bacteria takes place on which of the following organelles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Endoplasmic Reticulum",
            "b) Golgi body",
            "c) Ribosomes",
            "d) Mitochondria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: RNAase is a single polypeptide chain of 124 amino acid residues; it is folded, bent and twisted into a globular shape in its active form."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "Which of the following RNA constitutes 90 percent of the total cellular RNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) rRNA",
            "b) tRNA",
            "c) mRNA",
            "d) hnRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Protein synthesis in bacteria takes place on the ribosomes, which are larger RNA-protein particles in the cytoplasm of the bacterial cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "The synthesis of polynucleotide chain of mRNA is catalyzed by the enzyme _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RNA helicase",
            "b) RNA polymerase",
            "c) DNA polymerase",
            "d) DNA helicase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ribosomal RNA (rRNA) constitutes about 90 percent of the total cellular RNA and this is important from all other types of RNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "Which of the following is responsible for the initiation of RNA polymerase activity?",
        "Options": [
            "a) initiation site",
            "b) promoter region",
            "c) sigma factor",
            "d) rho factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The synthesis of polynucleotide chain of mRNA is catalyzed by the enzyme RNA polymerase. The process in which a single-stranded mRNA is synthesized complementary to one DNA strand is called transcription."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "Which of the following are non-sense codons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) AUG",
            "b) GUG",
            "c) UAA",
            "d) UCU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In bacteria, the initiation of RNA polymerase activity at the initiation site is due to an initiation factor called the sigma factor, which is a component of the enzyme."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "The amino acids for protein synthesis is activated by the enzyme ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) rna synthetase",
            "b) aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase",
            "c) tRNA synthetase",
            "d) aminoacyl-mRNA synthetase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first step in protein synthesis is the activation of amino acids. The amino acids are activated by amino-acid activating enzymes called aminoacyl-tRNA synthetase."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "tRNA has a _______________ structure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) strand-like",
            "b) ball-like",
            "c) clover-leaf",
            "d) leaf-like"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The activation of amino acids for protein synthesis requires energy in the form of ATP. There is a specific activating enzyme for each kind of amino acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Transfer RNA is a single chain of ___________ nucleotides.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 340",
            "b) about 100",
            "c) about 80",
            "d) 200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: tRNA has a clover-leaf structure.The tRNA functions in protein synthesis to carry amino acids to, and recognize codons in, mRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "The terminal sequence of nucleotides in all tRNA is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ACC",
            "b) UGC",
            "c) UCC",
            "d) AGC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Transfer RNA is a single chain of about 80 nucleotides that is folded back upon itself and held in a clover-leaf arrangement by means of hydrogen bonding due to complementary base pairing."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "6.The tRNA carries amino acids to the ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) rRNA",
            "b) mRNA",
            "c) sRNA",
            "d) hnRNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The terminal sequence of nucleotides is adenylic-cytidylic-cytidilic (ACC) and is found in all tRNA. The amino acid to be carried is linked to the terminal nucleotide containing adenine."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "The ribosome of E.coli is made up of which two subunits?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60S and 40S",
            "b) 60S and 30S",
            "c) 50S and 40S",
            "d) 50S and 30S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The tRNA carries amino acid to the mRNA attached to the surface of the ribosome. Here the amino acid is added to a growing polypeptide chain."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "S,the Svedberg unit is a measure of ____________________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the size of the ribosome",
            "b) the composition of the ribosome",
            "c) how fast a particle sediments during ultracentrifugation.",
            "d) how the subunits combine in a ribosome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ribosomes of E.coli have been studied extensively and have been found to consist of two subunits. The larger subunit is a 50S particle, while the smaller unit is a 30S particle."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The ribosome binds to any end of a mRNA",
            "b) CTP is required for activation of amino acids",
            "c) Activated amino acids bind to the 5’ end of a respective tRNA molecule",
            "d) The protein chain dissociates from the last tRNA molecule"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: S is the Svedberg unit, a measure of how fast particle sediments during ultracentrifugation. The association of a 30S and 50S subunit to form a 70S ribosome shows that the sedimentation behavior of the 70S ribosome is not a simple addition of the units of the smaller particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "The endoflagella is present in which class of bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spirilla",
            "b) Spirochetes",
            "c) Bacillus",
            "d) Coccus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spirochetes have an ability to twist or contort their shape due to the occurrence of a special kind of flagella termed periplasmic flagella or endoflagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "Where is the endoflagella located in Spirochetes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) In the cell membrane",
            "b) In the cytoplasm",
            "c) In the peptidoglycan layer",
            "d) In the periplasmic space"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In spirochetes, the endoflagella or as it is called periplasmic flagella is located between the outer membrane and the protoplasmic cylinder; thus they are located in the periplasmic space of the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods is used for viewing spirochetes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bright-field microscopy",
            "b) Phase-contrast microscopy",
            "c) Dark-field microscopy",
            "d) Electron microscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spirochetes because of the added advantage of having an endoflagella swims best in media of high viscosity, whereas bacteria with ordinary flagella swim best in media of low viscosity."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "Which among the following are microaerophilic bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spirochaeta",
            "b) Cristispira",
            "c) Treponema",
            "d) Borrelia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Most spirochetes are so thin that they cannot be easily seen by light microscopy, even when Gram-stained; however, dark-field microscopy does provide sufficient contrast and is the method of choice for visualizing these organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "Which of the following bacteria causes syphilis in humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Treponema dysenteriae",
            "b) Treponema pallidum",
            "c) Leptospira biflexa",
            "d) Leptospira interrogans"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The family Leptospiraceae of spirochetes are aerobes who use long-chain fatty acids as the carbon and energy source."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "Which of the following have bipolar tufts of flagella?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aquaspirillum",
            "b) Azospirillum",
            "c) Cristispira",
            "d) Borrelia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Borrelia is the genus of bacteria belonging to the class Spirochaetaceae and are microaerophilic."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "Which of the following causes diarrhea in humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A.lipoferum",
            "b) L.interrogans",
            "c) C.jejuni",
            "d) E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Treponema pallidum causes syphilis in humans and is microaerophilic. They belong to the family Spirochaetaceae and are found in the mouth, intestinal tract, and genital areas of humans and animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "Which genus among the following has certain similarities to the genus Bdellovibrio?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Azospirillum",
            "b) Oceanospirillum",
            "c) Campylobacter",
            "d) Vamprirovibrio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aquaspirilla are helical or vibroid organisms that typically possess bipolar tufts of flagella. They may be aerobic or microaerophilic and occur in a stagnant stream or pond water."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Which group of bacteria among the following give a positive reaction by the oxidase test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spirochetes",
            "b) Aerobic/Microaerophilic, Motile, Helical/Vibroid, Gram-negative bacteria",
            "c) Non-motile, Gram-negative, Curved bacteria",
            "d) Aerobic, Gram-negative rods and cocci"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: C.jejuni causes diarrhea in humans and belong to the genus Campylobacters. They are microaerophilic parasites and occur in the reproductive organs, intestinal tract, and oral cavity of humans and other mammals."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Pseudomonas bacteria uses which of the following as an electron acceptor for anaerobic respiration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oxygen",
            "b) Nitrate",
            "c) Phosphate",
            "d) Sulphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All pseudomonads can grow aerobically, but some can also grow anaerobically by using nitrate as an electron acceptor."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "Pyocyanin, a blue water-soluble pigment is produced by which of the following pseudomonads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P.mallei",
            "b) P.syringae",
            "c) P.fluorescens",
            "d) P.aeruginosa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pseudomonas maltophilia is a non-fluorescent species that is also frequently isolated from clinical specimens."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "Which of the following are important plant pathogens?",
        "Options": [
            "a) P. aeruginosa",
            "b) P.maltophilia",
            "c) P.syringae",
            "d) P.pseudomallei"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pseudomonas aeruginosa produces a water-soluble blue pigment, pyocyanin. The organism is mainly a soil and water saprophyte but can also be isolated from wound, burn etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "What is the color of the pigment xanthomonadin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blue",
            "b) Yellow",
            "c) Fluorescent",
            "d) Red"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: P. syringae are important plant pathogens, causing diseases such as leaf spot, leaf stripe, wilt, and necrosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an important characteristic of bacteria belonging to Zoogloea?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They are plant pathogens",
            "b) Cells are embedded in a gelatinous matrix",
            "c) Cause diseases in humans",
            "d) Useful for industrial applications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Xanthomonadin is a yellow pigment formed by bacteria of the genus Xanthomonas of the family Pseudomonadaceae."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "Which of the following family of bacteria fix nitrogen under aerobic conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pseudomonadaceae",
            "b) Azotobacteraceae",
            "c) Rhizobiaceae",
            "d) Methylcoccaceae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The outstanding characteristic of the genus Zoogloea is the embedment of cells in a gelatinous matrix to form slimy masses with a fingerlike morphology. They are mainly used in the sewage treatment plant."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "Methylococcus and Methylomonas are all _______________ methane-oxidizers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) aerobic",
            "b) facultative",
            "c) obligate",
            "d) anaerobic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The family Azotobacteraceae have organisms that can fix nitrogen under aerobic conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "Which of the following have peritrichous flagella?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acetobacter",
            "b) Gluconobacter",
            "c) Agrobacteria",
            "d) Rhizobium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Agrobacteria do not fix atmospheric nitrogen. The organisms are plant pathogens that incite tumors when they invade roots, crown and stems."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Bacteria belonging to the genus Legionella contains which of the following amino acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lysine",
            "b) Arginine",
            "c) Glycine",
            "d) Cysteine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Methylococcus and Methylomonas are all obligate methane-oxidizers i.e., carbon-sources such as glucose cannot be used for growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "Which of the following organism causes whooping cough in humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E.coli",
            "b) Bordetella pertussis",
            "c) Francisella tularensis",
            "d) F.meningosepticum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Acetobacter possesses peritrichous flagella. They belong to the family Acetobacteraceae."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "The cell diameter of bacteria belonging to family Enterobacteriaceae is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 m",
            "b) 1 cm",
            "c) .3-1.5 micrometre",
            "d) 5 micrometer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A distinctive feature of the family Enterobacteriaceae is that the cell diameter is 0.3 to 1.5 micrometers."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "What is the cell shape of the organisms belonging to the family Enterobacteriaceae?",
        "Options": [
            "a) vibrio",
            "b) coccus",
            "c) bacillus",
            "d) straight rod"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cell shape of organisms belonging to the family Enterobacteriaceae is that of a straight rod."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus of bacteria causes gastroenteritis in humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Salmonella",
            "b) Enterobacter",
            "c) Escherichia",
            "d) Shigella"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enterobacteriaceae possesses lateral flagella and moves by means of it. It does not possess endoflagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus of bacteria under the family Enterobacteriaceae is mainly associated with plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Erwinia",
            "b) Serratia",
            "c) Proteus",
            "d) Yersinia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Some bacteria of genus Escherichia causes gastroenteritis and some others can also cause urinary tract infections."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the causative agent of the plague?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Y.enterocolitica",
            "b) Y.pestis",
            "c) P.mirabilis",
            "d) E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enterobacter sp. gives positive results for Voges-Proskauer test by giving a reddish-pink colouration."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "The family Vibrionaceae is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxidase-positive",
            "b) oxidase-negative",
            "c) coccus shaped",
            "d) non-motile"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bacteria belonging to the genus Erwinia differ from most other Enterobacteriaceae by being mainly associated with plants. They are often plant pathogens, causing diseases such as blights, leaf spot, wilts, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus shows the characteristic of bioluminescence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aeromonas",
            "b) Zymomonas",
            "c) Vibrio",
            "d) Haemophilus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Yersiniae are parasites of animals but can also cause infections in humans. For example, Y.pestis is the causative agent of the plague."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "Among the given families, which family contains organisms that are non-motile?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enterobacteriaceae",
            "b) Vibrionaceae",
            "c) Pseudomonadaceae",
            "d) Pasteurellaceae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A distinctive feature of the family Vibrionaceae is that they are usually oxidase-positive. They are motile by means of polar flagella and cell shape is that of curved or straight rods."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "The X factor and/or the V factor is required by which genus of bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pasteurella",
            "b) Haemophilus",
            "c) Actinobacillus",
            "d) Zymomonas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Some species of genus Vibrio can emit light of a blue-green color(bioluminescence), an oxygen-dependent reaction catalyzed by the enzyme luciferase."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "Bacteria belonging to the family Bacteriodaceae uses which of the following compounds as electron acceptors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxygen",
            "b) inorganic sulphur",
            "c) nitrate",
            "d) phosphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacteriodaceae do not respire anaerobically by using inorganic sulphur as electron acceptors; some do respire anaerobically with nitrate or fumarate."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "The organic acids produced by bacteria belonging to the family Bacteriadaceae is identified by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) distillation",
            "b) gas chromatography",
            "c) spectrophotometer",
            "d) ion-exchange chromatography"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The bacteria of Bacteriadaceae differ in the kinds of organic acid end products they produce. The organic acids are identified by means of a gas chromatograph."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus of bacteria do not have a fermentative type of metabolism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacteroides",
            "b) Fusobacterium",
            "c) Wolinella",
            "d) Selenomonas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Wolinella do not have a fermentative type of metabolism. They respire anaerobically with hydrogen or formate as electron donors and fumarate or nitrate as electron acceptors."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "Which of the following possess peritrichous flagella?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacteroides",
            "b) Anaerovibrio",
            "c) Succinimonas",
            "d) Fusobacterium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bacteroides are straight-rod shaped. They are nonmotile or motile by means of peritrichous flagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "Propionate and acetate are produced as an end product of fermentation in which of the following bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fusobacterium",
            "b) Succinimonas",
            "c) Wolinella",
            "d) Anaerovibrio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Anaerovibrio are slightly curved rod shaped bacteria that are motile by means of a single polar flagellum. They produce propionate and acetate as organic acid end products of the fermentation process."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "The violet pigement, violacein, is produced by which of the following bacterial genus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zymomonas",
            "b) Gardnerella",
            "c) Streptobacillus",
            "d) Chromobacterium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Desuphuromonas is one genus of sulphur reducing bacteria that can respire with elemental sulphur as the electron acceptor. The other genera cannot use sulphur but can use sulphate, thiosulphate, or other oxidized sulphur compounds."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "Which of the following infect arthropods only?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rickettsieae",
            "b) Ehrlichieae",
            "c) Wolbachieae",
            "d) Rochalimaea"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Wolbachieae are not pathogenic for vertebrates, they infect arthropods only."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "Classical typhus fever is transmitted by which of the following arthropod?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ticks",
            "b) mites",
            "c) fleas",
            "d) lice"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Rickettsias synthesize ATP as a source of energy whereas Chlamydias cannot synthesize ATP."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "4.”Growing epicellularly” means ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) on the surface of host cells",
            "b) within the host cell",
            "c) engulfing the host cell",
            "d) damaging the cell membrane of host cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Classical typhus fever is caused by Rickettsia species and the arthropod vector which transmits the disease is lice."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus of Rickettsiaceae have a high resistance to heat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rickettsia",
            "b) Rochalimaea",
            "c) Coxiella",
            "d) Wolinella"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Growing epicellularly means growing on the surface of host cells. Rochalimaea grow epicellularly rather than in the cytoplasm or nucleus."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "C.burnetti causes which of the following diseases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q fever",
            "b) Trench fever",
            "c) Rocky Mountain spotted fever",
            "d) Typhoid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The organisms belonging to Coxiella have an unusually high resistance to heat [may survive a temperature of 62 degree C for 30 mins], probably due to the occurrence of endospore-like structures in the cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "Biting flies occur in which of the following place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Australia",
            "b) North America",
            "c) South America",
            "d) Africa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: C.burnetti is the causative agent of the Q fever, a type of pneumonia. It belongs to the family Rickettsiaceae."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Which is the most prevalent sexually transmitted disease in the US?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Syphilis",
            "b) AIDS",
            "c) Lymphogranuloma venerum",
            "d) Nongonococcal urethritis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Biting flies occur along the western slopes of the Andes mountains in South America. They transmit Oroya fever in humans."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "The smallest cells of mycoplasmas are about ___________ in diameter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 micrometre",
            "b) 0.3 micrometre",
            "c) 5 micrometre",
            "d) 1 metre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The smallest cells of Mycoplasmas are about 0.3 micrometre in diameter and the plasticity of these cells allow them to pass even through bacteriological filters."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "Mycoplasmas can be cultivated in vitro on nonliving media as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) facultative aerobes",
            "b) obligate aerobes",
            "c) facultative anaerobes",
            "d) microaerophiles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Because of the lack of a cell wall, mycoplasmas are not inhibited by even high levels of penicillin; however, they can be inhibited by antibiotics that affect protein synthesis, such as tetracyclines or chloramphenicol."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "The colonies of Mycoplasmas in agar plate can be observed by means of a _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) low-power microscope",
            "b) high-power microscope",
            "c) phase contrast microscopy",
            "d) bright-field microscopy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mycoplasmas can be cultivated in vitro on nonliving media (of rich composition) as facultative anaerobes or obligate anaerobes."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "What type of colonies are formed by Mycoplasmas on the agar plate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) colourless",
            "b) coloured",
            "c) lawn formation",
            "d) fried-egg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Colonies on agar plate are usually tiny and require observation by means of a low-power microscope. The colonies are embedded in the agar surface and usually have a characteristic fried-egg appearance."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "The mycoplasmas require which of the following substance for growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrogen",
            "b) Carbon",
            "c) Cholesterol",
            "d) Glucose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The colonies are embedded in the agar surface and usually have a characteristic fried-egg appearance. The colonies are usually very tiny."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "Which of the following family of bacteria are pathogenic for citrus and other plants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mycoplasmataceae",
            "b) Acholeplasmataceae",
            "c) Spiroplamataceae",
            "d) Anaplasmataceae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Mycoplasmas require cholesterol for growth and are parasites of the mucous membranes and joints of humans or animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "Lyticum flagellatum is an endosymbiont carried by certain strains of __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bacteria",
            "b) fungi",
            "c) viruses",
            "d) protozoa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The organisms of Spiroplasmataceae are pathogenic for citrus and other plants. They can be isolated from plant fluids and plant surfaces and from arthropods that feed on plants."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "L.flagellatum performs the function of synthesizing _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) vitamins",
            "b) hormones",
            "c) organic acids",
            "d) folic acid and toxins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lyticum flagellatum is an endosymbiont carried by certain strains of the protozoan Paramecium tetraurelia."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "The cocci belonging to the family Dienococcaceae occur mainly in _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tetrads",
            "b) diplococci",
            "c) streptococci",
            "d) staphylococci"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cocci belonging to the family Deinococcaceae occurs mainly in tetrads or cubical packets."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "The organisms belonging to the genus Deinococcus forms colonies of which color?",
        "Options": [
            "a) colourless",
            "b) blue",
            "c) red",
            "d) violet"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The family Deinococcaceae contains a single genus Deinococcus which forms red colonies."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "Among the following which is positive for coagulase test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Staphylococcus aureus",
            "b) Staphylococcus epidermidis",
            "c) Staphylococcus saprophyticus",
            "d) E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The family Micrococcaceae do not exhibit any unusual resistance to gamma and ultraviolet radiation. But the organisms belonging to family Deinococcaceae have an unusually high resistance to gamma and ultraviolet radiations."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "Which of the following species of streptococci belongs to Lancefield group N?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S.pyogenes",
            "b) S.mutans",
            "c) S.pneumoniae",
            "d) S.cremoris"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Staphylococcus aureus is positive for coagulase test which is a test for the ability of the bacteria to cause blood plasma to clot."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "S.pneumoniae produces which of the following type of colonies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) alpha-haemolytic",
            "b) beta-haemolytic",
            "c) non-haemolytic",
            "d) alpha-, beta-haemolytic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Streptococcus are catalase-negative. The organisms are homofermentative i.e., the predominant end product of sugar fermentation is lactic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the causative agent of dental caries?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S.pneumoniae",
            "b) S.pyogenes",
            "c) S.mutans",
            "d) S.faecalis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The streptococci are divided into categories known as the Lancefield groups based on differences in their cell-wall polysaccharides. S.cremoris belong to Lancefield group N and are harmless contaminants of milk and dairy products."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus of species occurs in human feces?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peptococcus",
            "b) Coprococcus",
            "c) Sarcina",
            "d) Ruminococcus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: S.pneumoniae are alpha-haemolytic i.e. colonies are surrounded by a cloudy, colorless or greenish zone of partially lysed erythrocytes."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "Which of the following are mesophilic saprophytes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B.polymyxa",
            "b) B.anthracis",
            "c) B.subtilis",
            "d) B.thuringiensis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacillus subtilis are mesophilic saprophytes and are widely distributed in nature. This means they can grow best within a temperature range of approximately 25 to 40 degrees Celsius."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "Which of the following causes “milky disease” of Japanese beetle grubs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B.thuringiensis",
            "b) B.popilliae",
            "c) B.sphaericus",
            "d) B.anthracis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: B.popilliae is a pathogenic species of Bacillus species that causes “milky disease” of Japanese beetle grubs."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "Which of the following species is associated with spoilage of canned goods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) B.stearothermophiles",
            "b) B.cereus",
            "c) B.subtilis",
            "d) B.sphaericus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: B.stearothermophilus is a thermophilic species having a maximum of 65 to 75 degrees Celsius. The endospores are highly resistant to heat and, therefore, this species is one of those associated with spoilage of canned goods."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus of species play an active role in the decomposition of urea?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacillus",
            "b) Sporosarcina",
            "c) Clostridium",
            "d) Desulfotomaculum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sporosarcinae are widely distributed in fertile soil, where they play an active role in the decomposition of urea."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "C.perfringens is the major causative agent of __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) botulism",
            "b) tetanus",
            "c) gas gangrene",
            "d) anthrax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Clostridium perfringens is the major causative agent of the wound infection known as gas gangrene."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "Which of the following Clostridium species has the ability to fix Nitrogen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C.difficile",
            "b) C.pasteurianum",
            "c) C.tetani",
            "d) C.thermosaccharolyticum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: C.pasteurianum is a mesophilic soil clostridium that is particularly noted for its ability to fix Nitrogen."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "Pseudomembranous colitis is a disease of _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) stomach",
            "b) wounds",
            "c) bowel",
            "d) limbs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The members of the genus Desulfotomaculum obtain energy by anaerobic respiration, with sulphate serving as the terminal electron acceptor and organic substrates such as lactic or pyruvic acid serving as the electron donors."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Which of the following Nonspore forming Gram-positive rods show a negative result for catalase test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lactobacillus",
            "b) Kurthia",
            "c) Brocothrix",
            "d) Renibacterium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lactobacillus which are strictly fermentative organisms show negative result for catalase test."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of the genus Caryophanon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) anaerobic species",
            "b) non-motile organism",
            "c) disk-shaped cells",
            "d) parasitic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Caryophanon is unusual as it is composed of large, disk-shaped cells arranged in trichomes. They are aerobic organisms and are motile by peritrichous flagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus of organisms causes meningitis in adults?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Erysipelothrix",
            "b) Listeria",
            "c) Caryophanon",
            "d) Brocothrix"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The species L.monocytogenes of the genus Listeria is a parasite and causes meningitis in adults and prenatal or postnatal disease in infants."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "Volutin granules stain which colour with dilute methylene blue?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Violet",
            "b) Blue",
            "c) Red",
            "d) Reddish purple"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Brocothrix are rods often occurring in long, kinked filaments and are facultatively anaerobic."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "The cell walls of Corynebacterium contain mycolic acid containing ______________ carbon atoms.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 to 3",
            "b) 100 to 150",
            "c) 32 to 36",
            "d) 20 to 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cells of Corynebacterium accumulate intracellular volutin granules (metachromatic granules) which stain reddish purple with dilute methylene blue."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "Cells of Arthrobacter in the stationary phase of growth are ____________ shaped.",
        "Options": [
            "a) rod",
            "b) irregularly",
            "c) coccoid",
            "d) rudimentary branching"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cell walls of Corynebacterium contain mycolic acids (corynemycolic acids) containing 32 to 36 carbon atoms."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus of species occur on the surface of certain cheeses such as brick and Limburger?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brevibacterium",
            "b) Microbacterium",
            "c) Cellulomonas",
            "d) Arthrobacter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cells of Arthrobacter in the stationary phase of growth are distinctly coccoid; when these are inoculated into fresh media, they give rise to rod-shaped cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus of organisms are normal inhabitants of the human mouth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Agromyces",
            "b) Arachnia",
            "c) Actinomyces",
            "d) Rothia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: B.linens of the Brevibacterium has its usual habitat on the surface of certain cheeses such as brick and Limburger, where it produces proteolytic enzymes that aid in the cheese-ripening process."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "The causative agent of leprosy is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) M.intracellulare",
            "b) M.leprae",
            "c) M.kansasii",
            "d) M.phlei"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The genus Rothia is aerobic,catalase-positive, and a normal inhabitant of the human mouth."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "The walls of Nocardioforms contains the sugars ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sucrose and galactose",
            "b) fructose and galactose",
            "c) sucrose and arabinose",
            "d) arabinose and galactose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A major characteristic of mycobacteria is that they are acid-fast; that is, once stained with aniline dyes, they are difficult to decolourize, even when treated with a mixture of acid and alcohol."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "Fungi are ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) prokaryotic",
            "b) eukaryotic",
            "c) prokaryotic and lack chlorophyll",
            "d) eukaryotic and lack chlorophyll"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:Fungi are eucaryotic spore-bearing protists that lack chlorophyll. They are of great practical and scientific interest to microbiologists."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Hyphal wall consists of microfibrils composed of ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hemicellulose or chitin",
            "b) cellulose",
            "c) lipids",
            "d) proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:a\nExplanation: The hyphal walls of fungi consist of microfibrils composed for the most part of hemicellulose or chitin; true cellulose occurs only in the walls of lower fungi."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "Coenocytic hyphae have ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) septate with uninucleate cells",
            "b) septate with multinucleate cells",
            "c) no septate",
            "d) no septate with uninucleate cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Coenocytic hyphae are also known as nonseptate hyphae and hence have no sep-ta."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "What are the dimensions of the filaments that the thallus of a fungus consists of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 micrometre",
            "b) 5 to 10 micrometre",
            "c) 1 metre",
            "d) 1 centimetre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The thallus or body of a fungus consists of filaments, 5 to 10 micrometre across, which are commonly branched."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "What do the term dimorphic mean?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bisexual",
            "b) Unisexual",
            "c) Exists in two forms",
            "d) Exists in single form"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The yeast cell or mould filament is surrounded by a true cell wall. The exception being the slime moulds, which have a thallus consisting of a naked amoeboid mass of proto-plasm."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "The crosswalls constrict which of the following parts and then grow inwards to form septum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hyphae",
            "b) lumen",
            "c) protoplasm",
            "d) plasmalemma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Some fungi are dimorphic, that is, they exist in two forms. Some pathogenic fungi have a unicellular and yeastlike form in their host, but when growing saprophytically in soil or in laboratory medium they have a filamentous mold form."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "Which of the following surrounds plasmalemma?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lumen",
            "b) wall",
            "c) protoplasm",
            "d) hyphae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Yeasts have no flagella or other organelles of locomotion."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "Which among the following are asexual spores?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blastospores",
            "b) Ascospores",
            "c) Basidiospores",
            "d) Zygospores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Blastospores are asexual spores and are formed by budding."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "Aplanospores are _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) motile sporangiospores",
            "b) nonmotile sporangiospores",
            "c) oidia",
            "d) chlamydospores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Aplanospores are nonmotile sporangiospores. Sporangiospores are single-celled spores and are formed within the sporangium."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "Which among the following are spores formed by budding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arthrospores",
            "b) Chlamydospores",
            "c) Blastospores",
            "d) Conidiospores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Blastospores are asexual spores and are formed by budding."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "Spores formed by sexual reproduction on a club-shaped structure are _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ascospores",
            "b) Zygospores",
            "c) Basidiospores",
            "d) Oospores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Basidiospores are single-celled spores borne on a club-shaped structure called a basidium."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "Asexual fruiting bodies have name such as ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) perithecium",
            "b) pycnidium",
            "c) antheridium",
            "d) apothecium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fruiting bodies are highly organized protective structures that surround the asexual and sexual spores. Asexual fruiting bodies have names such as acervulus and pycnidium."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "How many ascospores are present in each ascus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Four",
            "b) Six",
            "c) Two",
            "d) Eight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oospheres are eggs formed within a special female structure, the oogonium. There are one or more oospheres in each oogonium."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Which of the following spores are formed at the tips of sterigmata?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zygospores",
            "b) Oospores",
            "c) Basidiospores",
            "d) Blastospores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Ascospores are single-celled spores produced in a sac called an ascus. These are usually eight ascospores in each ascus."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "In which of the following process does the male nucleus migrates through a fertilization tube into the female gametangium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gametic copulation",
            "b) Gamete-gametangial copulation",
            "c) Gametangial copulation",
            "d) Somatic copulation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Basidiospores are formed exogenously at the tips of the special outgrowths called sterigmata. Usually four spores are formed at the tip of each sterigma."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Which of the following spores are formed by the disjointing of hyphal cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conidiospores",
            "b) Chlamydospores",
            "c) Oidia",
            "d) Zoospores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The two haploid nuclei of two mating types fuse together to form a diploid nucleus and this process is known as karyogamy."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Pathogenic fungi have a temperature optimum at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 to 37 degree celsius",
            "b) 22 to 30 degree celsius",
            "c) 37 to 42 degree celsius",
            "d) 42 to 50 degree celsius"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fungi grow over a wide range of temperatures. Pathogenic species have a higher temperature optimum, generally 30 to 37 degree Celsius."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Sabouraud media for the growth of fungi is composed of ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) glucose and ammonia",
            "b) maltose and peptone",
            "c) sucrose and peptone",
            "d) peptone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: One of the best known and oldest media for the growth of fungi is Sabouraud media that contains maltose and peptone as its principal ingredients."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "Sabouraud media has ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) high ph, low sugar concentration",
            "b) high ph, moderate sugar concentration",
            "c) low ph, high sugar concentration",
            "d) low ph, moderate sugar concentration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sabouraud media is widely used for the isolation of molds and certain yeasts. Its partial selective action is due to the high sugar concentration and low pH."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "What are the cell wall structural components of fungi?",
        "Options": [
            "a) peptidoglycan",
            "b) cellulose",
            "c) chitin",
            "d) chitin,cellulose, or hemicellulose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Yeasts and molds can grow in a substrate or medium containing concentrations of sugars that inhibit most bacteria; this is why jams and jellies may be spoiled by molds but not by bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "The optimum pH for the growth of fungi is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.8-9.0",
            "b) 12-14",
            "c) 3.8-5.6",
            "d) 1.0-2.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cell wall structural components of fungi are chitin, cellulose, or hemicellulose whereas the bacterial cell wall is composed of peptidoglycan."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "Which of the following are the oxygen requirements of molds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strictly aerobic",
            "b) Facultatively aerobic",
            "c) Anaerobic",
            "d) Microaerophilic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The optimum pH for the growth of fungi is 3.8-5.6. Acidic media (pH 5.6) are tolerated by molds but are inhibitory to most bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "Fungi are sensitive to which of the following antibiotics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) penicillins",
            "b) tetracyclins",
            "c) chloramphenicol",
            "d) griseofulvin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Moulds are strictly aerobic whereas yeasts are facultative organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "In the fungal classification system Ascomycetes come under the division of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gymnomycota",
            "b) Mastigomycota",
            "c) Amastigomycota",
            "d) Gymnomycota, Mastigomycota"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The class of Ascomycetes comes under the division of Amastigomycota which are terrestrial fungi."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Rhizopus stolonifer belongs to which class?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acrasiomycetes",
            "b) Zygomycetes",
            "c) Ascomycetes",
            "d) Deuteromycetes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Rhizopus stolonifer belongs to the class Zygomycetes and division Amastigomycota."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Which class of fungi among the following have motile cells with two laterally inserted flagella, one tinsel and the other whiplash?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chytridiomycetes",
            "b) Zygomycetes",
            "c) Deuteromycetes",
            "d) Oomycetes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Oomycetes class have motile cells with two laterally inserted flagella, one tinsel and anteriorly directed, the other whiplash and posteriorly directed."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "Which division of fungi lacks flagella?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mastigomycota",
            "b) Amastigomycota",
            "c) Gymnomycota",
            "d) Basidiomycetes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The division Amastigomycota or terrestrial fungi lack flagella. Mainly sexual spores are produced by the organisms of this division."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "5.Fruiting bodies of slime moulds are called ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) acervulus",
            "b) sori",
            "c) apothecium",
            "d) perithecium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fruiting bodies of slime moulds are called sori that are masses of spores."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "The taxa having the ending -mycetes is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Division",
            "b) Subdivision",
            "c) Class",
            "d) Order"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Class have the ending-mycetes. Division have the ending -mycota, subdivision ends with -mycotina whereas order ends with -ales."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "The common yeast Schizosaccharomyces follows which of the following asexual reproduction methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) binary fission",
            "b) budding",
            "c) fragmentation",
            "d) spore formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In Schizosaccharomyces, asexual reproduction is by binary fission. Sexual reproduction is by conjugation of compatible cells with the subsequent formation of ascospores."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "The structure which contains the zygote nuclei in Rhizopus stolonifer is is known as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) progametangia",
            "b) zygospore",
            "c) suspensor cell",
            "d) coenozygote"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The walls of the two contacting gametangia dissolve at the point of contact, the two protoplasts mix and the + and – nuclei fuse to form many zygote nuclei. The structure which contains them is called the coenozygote."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "The mature zygospore lies dormant for how many days?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4-5 days",
            "b) 1-3 months",
            "c) 1 year",
            "d) 20 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The wall around the coenozygote thickens and its surface becomes black and warty, forming the mature zygospore, which lies dormant for 1 to 3 or more months."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "Which of the following are acellular slime moulds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acrasiomycetes",
            "b) Myxomycetes",
            "c) Oomycetes",
            "d) Ascomycetes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Myxomycetes are acellular slime molds whose vegetative phase consists of a multicellular, wall-less plasmodium, which transforms into highly organized sporangia bearing sporangiospores."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Which fungi causes black wart disease of potato?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saprolegnia parasitica",
            "b) Synchytrium endobioticum",
            "c) Rhizopus stolonifer",
            "d) Saccharomyces cerevisiae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Synchytrium endobioticum is the most serious parasite of the class Chytridiomycetes that causes black wart disease of potato. The dark warts on the potatoes are galls in which the host cells have been stimulated to divide by the fungus."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Zygomycetes have which type of mycelia?",
        "Options": [
            "a) nonseptate",
            "b) septate with uninucleate",
            "c) septate with multi muclei",
            "d) white,nonseptate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Morphologically, the mycelia of Zygomycetes are usually white or gray and are nonseptate."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "In the life cycle of Rhizopus stolonifer,when the protoplasts and nuclei of both gametangia coalesce, the structure is known as ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) progametangia",
            "b) coenozygote",
            "c) zygospore",
            "d) zygote"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The walls between two gametangia dissolve and their protoplasts coalesce. Nuclei of both mating types fuse in pairs, producing many zygote nuclei. The structure that contains them is then called a coenozygote."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "Schizosaccharomyces versatilis is isolated from ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) grape juice",
            "b) cheese",
            "c) honey",
            "d) beer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Schizosaccharomyces versatilis is isolated from grape juice. It grows like yeast but it can also form a true mycelium."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "Legitimate copulation refers to ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) fusion between cells of same mating type",
            "b) fusion between cells of different mating type",
            "c) no fusion",
            "d) different sex cells are present within the same body"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fusion normally occurs only between cells of difffering mating types, a process termed as legitimate copulation. Such fusions result in diploid cells which form asci containing viable ascospores."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Neurospora sp. is important for the study of _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) human diseases",
            "b) antibiotics",
            "c) genetics and metabolic pathway",
            "d) plant diseases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Neurospora sp. which belongs to the class Ascomycetes is of particular interest to biologists because of its wide use in the study of genetics and metabolic pathways. Some species are also responsible for food spoilage and some are used in industrial fermentation."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "Cryptococcosis is a disease of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bacterial infection",
            "b) parasitic infection",
            "c) viral infection",
            "d) mycotic infection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cryptococcus neoformans is an important basidiomycetous pathogen of humans, causing cryptococcosis, a generalized mycotic infection involving the bloodstream as well as lungs, central nervous system and other organs."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "Aspergillus niger is used in the production of _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cheese",
            "b) citric acid",
            "c) gluconic acid",
            "d) citric acid and gluconic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It is an economically important fungi because they are used in a number of industrial fermentations, including the production of citric acid and gluconic acid in abundance."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "Endocarditis is caused by which of the following fungi?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Candida albicans",
            "b) Penicillium notatum",
            "c) Penicillium chrysogenum",
            "d) Agaricus campestris"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Candida albicans is often isolated from warm-blooded animals, including humans and becomes pathogenic and causes many serious infections. Endocarditis is caused by this organism and it is an infection of the heart.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "What do you mean by hypertrophy?",
        "Options": [
            "a) repeated cell division",
            "b) infection by zoospore",
            "c) increase in cell volume",
            "d) decrease in cell volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the wart disease of potato, when the host cell is infected by a zoospore, it reacts by undergoing hypertrophy,i.e., an increase in cell volume, and adjacent cells also enlarge to form the characteristic rosette."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Which of the following fungi causes severe epidemic of disease among fish in the natural environment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saprolegnia ferax",
            "b) Saprolegnia parasitica",
            "c) Neurospora crassa",
            "d) Neurospora sitophila"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Species of Saprolegnia are common in soil and fresh water; hence they are commonly called water molds. S.parasitica causes severe epidemics of disease among fish in the natural environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Rhizopus produces clusters of rootlike holdfasts called _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) stolons",
            "b) hyphae",
            "c) runners",
            "d) rhizoids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rhizoidal hyphae enter the substratum and serve to anchor the organism and to absorb nutrients, and the branched hyphae is the one on which reproductive organs are formed."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "Alginic acid is obtained from ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) brown algae",
            "b) red algae",
            "c) yello-green algae",
            "d) golden algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Alginic acid and its salts are obtained from the walls of brown algae, where they may represent as much as 25 percent of the dry weight. Laminaria, Fucus are some of the species producing this compound."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "Agar is obtained from the algal species of _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chondrus",
            "b) Gigartina",
            "c) Gelidium",
            "d) Laminaria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Species of Gelidium and Gracilaria belonging to red algae are extensively used for obtaining agar."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "Carrageenan is used as a ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) emulsifier",
            "b) solidifying agent",
            "c) binder",
            "d) emulsifier and binder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Carrageenan has been used as a stabilizer or emulsifier in foods such as ice-cream and other milk products. It is also used as a binder in toothpaste or in pharmaceutical products, as well as an agent in ulcer therapy."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "The famous Japanese dish sushi is made with the help of the red algae named ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nemalion",
            "b) Porphyra",
            "c) Chondrus",
            "d) Eucheuma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Porphyra is used as a food in Japan, where it is called “nori” and is usually processed into dried sheets. Nori is commonly toasted over a flame and sprinkled in soup or rice, or it is rolled around flavoured rice with fish or vegetables to make sushi."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "Which among the following is a pathogenic algae for humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Prototheca",
            "b) Chlorella",
            "c) Cephaleuros",
            "d) Acanthopeltis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:a\nExplanation: Prototheca has been found to be a probable pathogen of humans. It has been found in systemic and subcutaneous infections, as well as in bursitis."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "Agar and carrageenan are polymers of _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) glucose",
            "b) phosphoric acid",
            "c) starch",
            "d) galactose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Algae form the base or beginning of most aquatic food chains because of their photosynthetic activities and are therefore called primary producers of organic matter."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "Which of the following species are important for cervical dilation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Laminaria japonica",
            "b) Gracilaria",
            "c) Chondrus",
            "d) Gonyaulax catenella"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Agar and carrageenan are polymers of galactose, or galactose-containing compounds, with sulfated groups. Agar and carrageenan are both called sulfated galactans."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "Which of the following algae continues to be a significant food in China?",
        "Options": [
            "a) brown algae",
            "b) green algae",
            "c) red algae",
            "d) yellow algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stipe of the brown alga Laminaria japonica may be used by the physicians for cervical dilation and/or softening of the cervix (for example, in performing an abortion or placing a radium implant)."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "Which of the following species produces neurotoxin which causes the death of aquatic animals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorella",
            "b) Gonyaulax",
            "c) Prototheca",
            "d) Cephaleuros"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Red algae continue to be significant food in China. Such algae have been a food staple and delicacy for the Chinese for thousands of years."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "Chlorophyll d is present in the members of _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xanthophycophyta",
            "b) Phaeophycophyta",
            "c) Rhodophycophyta",
            "d) Chrysophycophyta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chlorophyll d is present only in the members of Rhodophycophyta. There are five chlorophylls a, b, c, d, e which are found in different organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "Fucoxanthin pigment is present in _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhodophycophyta",
            "b) Xanthophycophyta",
            "c) Phaeophycophyta",
            "d) Chlorophycophyta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fucoxanthin is present in Phaeophycophyta and gives it its characteristic colour brown. Other pigments like carotene and chlorophyll a and c are also present along with fucoxanthin."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "Phycoerythrin pigment is present in which algal division?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Xanthophycophyta",
            "b) Rhodophycophyta",
            "c) Chrysophycophyta",
            "d) Phaeophycophyta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Phycoerythrin and phycocyanin are biloproteins present in Rhodophycophyta. They are also present in cryptomonads."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "Chrysolaminarin is the reserved food of ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorophycophyta",
            "b) Phaeophycophyta",
            "c) Xanthophycophyta",
            "d) Bacillariophycophyta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Chrysolaminarin is the reserved food of Xanthophycophyta which is the yellow-green algae along with oils."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "Cell walls of diatoms are impregnated with _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chitin",
            "b) cellulose",
            "c) starch",
            "d) silica"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cell walls of diatoms are impregnated with silica, making them thick and very rigid; they are often delicately sculptured with intricate designs characteristic of the species or variety."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "Chloroplasts of algae embedded in the midst of the cytoplasm is known as ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) parietal",
            "b) asteroidal",
            "c) central",
            "d) peripheral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chloroplasts may be massive structures situated near the wall which are known as parietal or embedded in the midst of the cytoplasm which are known as asteroidal."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "Two lateral flagella are present in which of the following groups of algae?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhodophycophyta",
            "b) Xanthophycophyta",
            "c) Phaeophycophyta",
            "d) Bacillariophycophyta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Carotenes are linear, unsaturated hydrocarbons, and xanthophylls are oxygenated derivatives of these."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "Gullet is present in which algae?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Euglenoids",
            "b) Golden algae",
            "c) Dinoflagellates",
            "d) Green algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phaeophycophyta or the brown algae consists of two lateral flagella. Dinoflagellate or cryptomonads also consists of two lateral flagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "Which of the following are water-soluble pigments?",
        "Options": [
            "a) chlorophyll",
            "b) biloproteins",
            "c) carotenoids",
            "d) fucoxanthin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Euglenoids or Euglenophycophyta contain gullet which is anteriorly present. It contains 1, 2 or 3 equal or slightly apical flagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Carpogonia is the female sex organ in which of the algae?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhodophycophyta",
            "b) Xanthophycophyta",
            "c) Chrysophycophyta",
            "d) Chlorophycophyta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rhodophycophyta reproduces sexually heterogamously by the union of well-differentiated nonmotile male and female germ cells, the spermatia and carpogonia (female sex organs), respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "2.The xanthophyte walls are typically of _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chitin",
            "b) cellulose",
            "c) cellulose and pectin",
            "d) starch"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The xanthophye walls are typically of cellulose and pectin. The cellular storage product is an oil or (a branched glucan) chrysolaminarin."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "Chrysamoeba exists in which of the following forms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) nonmotile coccoid",
            "b) filamentous",
            "c) amoeboid",
            "d) motile amoeboid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Vaucheria has a very large macroscopic filamentous form. It is widely distributed on moist soil and water."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "Kelps are which of the following type of algae?",
        "Options": [
            "a) red algae",
            "b) yellow algae",
            "c) brown algae",
            "d) green algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Chrysamoeba is a strongly amoeboid genus with flagella. It belongs to the group of golden algae."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "Frustules are found in which of the following algae?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacillariophycophyta",
            "b) Chlorophycophyta",
            "c) Euglenophycophyta",
            "d) Rhodophycophyta"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Brown algae are structurally quite complex and kelps belong to this group. Kelps are large, the individual plants reaching a length of several hundred feet."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Which of the following are formed in pyrenoids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) oil",
            "b) glucose",
            "c) starch",
            "d) silica"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bacillariophycophyta or diatoms produce shells (cell walls) containing silica, some of which are very beautiful. Shells of diatoms are called frustules."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "9.In Chlamydomonas the most common method of sexual reproduction is ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) isogamy",
            "b) heterogamy",
            "c) oogamy",
            "d) spore formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Euglena has no cell wall containing cellulose. The outer membrane is an organized periplast."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a colonial green alga?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlamydomonas",
            "b) Chlorella",
            "c) Volvox",
            "d) Spirogyra"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The chloroplasts of green algae often contain dense regions called pyrenoids, on which surface starch granules are formed."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "pH range optimal for maximum metabolic activity of protozoa is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2-3",
            "b) 12-14",
            "c) 6-8",
            "d) 4-6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the majority of pH range of 6.0 to 8.0 is optimal for maximum metabolic activity. Some protozoa can tolerate a wide range of pH, for example, pH 3.2 to 8.7."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "Protozoa that eat other organisms are known as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) saprophytic",
            "b) holozoic",
            "c) parasitic",
            "d) mutualistic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Holozoic protozoa are protozoa that eat other organisms. Species of Paramecium are holozoic and they must have a supply of bacteria or other protozoa."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "What is the maximum temperature for protozoa?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 degrees C",
            "b) 10 degrees C",
            "c) 16 degrees C",
            "d) 25 degrees C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Most protozoa have an optimum temperature of between 16 and 25 degree C; the maximum temperature is between 36 and 40 degree C."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "The process in which protozoa attaches themselves to a host’s body is known as __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Endocommensalism",
            "b) Ectocommensalism",
            "c) Parasitic",
            "d) Mutualism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Ectocommensalism is often represented by protozoa which attach themselves to a host’s body. In commensalism the host is neither injured nor benefitted, but the commensal is benefitted."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "African sleeping sickness is caused by _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bacteria",
            "b) fungi",
            "c) protozoa",
            "d) viruses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Certain flagellates are present in the gut of termites and digest the woody material eaten by the termite to a glycogenous substance which can be used by the host cells. If deprived of these flagellates, the termite dies."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a function of protozoa?",
        "Options": [
            "a) acts as a link in the food chain",
            "b) used in manufacture of food products",
            "c) decomposition process",
            "d) to study cell cycles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Some protozoa causes diseases in animals, including humans. Some well-known protozoan diseases in humans are intestinal amoebiasis, African sleeping sickness, and malaria."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an aerobic protozoa?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Metopus",
            "b) Saprodinium",
            "c) Epalxis",
            "d) Vorticella"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Protozoa serve as an important link in the food chain of communities in aquatic environments. They also make use of the substances produced and organisms involved in the final decomposition stage of organic matter. Some species of protozoa have been used to study cell cycles and nucleic acid biosynthesis during cell division."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "Red snow of high altitudes is due to the presence of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bacteria",
            "b) protozoa",
            "c) algae",
            "d) fungi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vorticella is an aerobic protozoa involved in the aeration and flocculation steps of sewage treatment. Others are all anaerobic protozoa."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "When parasitic protozoa parasitize other protozoan it is known as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parasitism",
            "b) Mutualism",
            "c) Hyperparasitism",
            "d) Hypoparasitism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The red snow of high altitudes is due to the presence of several hematochrome-bearing flagellates or protozoa which are considered as algae by some biologists."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Leishmania donovani measures _____________ in length.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600 micrometre",
            "b) 1 to 4 micrometre",
            "c) 2 mm",
            "d) 2000 micrometre"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Leishmania donovani, the cause of human disease kala azar, measures 1 to 4 micrometre in length."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Plasmagel is known as __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cytoplasm",
            "b) endoplasm",
            "c) ectoplasm",
            "d) myonemes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Protozoan contractility is probably due to the fibrils. Submicroscopic protein fibrils are groups of parallel fibrils in the cytoplasm."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "Golgi bodies are also known as __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) dictyosomes",
            "b) kinetosomes",
            "c) blepharoplasts",
            "d) myonemes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Plasmagel is known as the ectoplasm. The cytoplasm is differentiated into endoplasm and ectoplasm. The ectoplasm is more gel-like and the endoplasm is more voluminous and fluid."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "How many haploid chromosomes are present in Spirotrichonympha polygyra?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60",
            "b) 7",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Golgi complexes are also known as dictyosomes which means piles of membranous sacs."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "Amoeba proteus have a diffuse layer of which of the following over the plasmalemma?",
        "Options": [
            "a) glucose",
            "b) chitin",
            "c) cellulose",
            "d) mucopolysaccharides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The micronucleus is concerned with reproductive ability whereas the macronucleus controls the metabolic activities and regeneration processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "Among the following which layer is directly apposed to the cell surface?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tests",
            "b) theca",
            "c) shells",
            "d) loricae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It has been shown that number of chromosomes is constant for a particular species of protozoan. Spirotrichonympha polygyra has 2 haploid chromosomes."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the actual opening in ciliates through which food is ingested?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cytosome",
            "b) oral groove",
            "c) peristome",
            "d) cytopharynx"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Amoeba proteus have a diffuse layer of mucopolysaccharides over the plasmalemma. This layer is thought to play an important role in pinocytosis or in adhesion of the cell to the substratum."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "Which of the following protective structures occur in the tentacles of suctorian protozoa?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mucocysts",
            "b) trichocysts",
            "c) toxicysts",
            "d) haptocysts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The theca is a secreted layer directly apposed to the cell surface. Tests, shells, and lorica are coverings that are loosely apposed to the cell surface. Tests, shells, and lorica are coverings that are loose-fitting."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of fission takes place in flagellates?",
        "Options": [
            "a) longitudinal",
            "b) right angle to the cell axis",
            "c) transverse",
            "d) cytoplasm protrudes from the aperture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In flagellates, with the exception of the dinoflagellates, fission is longitudinal along the major body axis. Since the flagella themselves are incapable of division, they must be regenerated from the basal bodies."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not take place in transverse fission?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fission occurs at the right angle to the long cell axis",
            "b) equatorial furrow appears",
            "c) cytoplasm protrudes from the aperture",
            "d) constriction occurs forming two daughter cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In transverse fission which is characteristic for ciliates, fission occurs at a right angle to the long axis of the cell. An equatorial furrow appears first which separates the surface cell layer into an anterior and a posterior half. A constriction follows, leading to the separation of two daughter cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "Plasmodium divides by which of the following method most commonly?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Binary fission",
            "b) Multiple fission",
            "c) Budding",
            "d) Regeneration"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In ciliates, during asexual binary fission the diploid micronucleus divides normally by mitotic division. The macronucleus undergoes DNA synthesis and divides into two portions without the regular reduplication of the chromosomes(amitosis)."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "Definite exogenous budding occurs in which of the following species of protozoa?",
        "Options": [
            "a) foraminifera",
            "b) radiolaria",
            "c) suctorians",
            "d) heliozoa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The malarial parasite, Plasmodium divides by the process of multiple fission where it is known as schizogony and serves to spread the parasite quickly in the host."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "When the gametes are morphologically alike, they are called ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) isogametes",
            "b) anisogametes",
            "c) macrogametes",
            "d) microgametes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The swarming daughter cells differ from the parent cell not only in a lower degree of differentiation but also in the possession of special locomotor organelles."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "Long,slender bodies with an oval nucleus and capable of producing new infection are known as _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ookinetes",
            "b) sporozoites",
            "c) anisogametes",
            "d) spermatozoa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Definite exogenous budding is seen in suctorians when a portion or portions of an adult sessile suctorian bud from the parent, develop cilia and swim away."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "Members of order Diplomonadida have how many flagella?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 to 4",
            "b) 6 to 8",
            "c) 2 to 8",
            "d) 1 to 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Members of the order Diplomonadida have bilateral symmetry and 6 to 8 flagella."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "Trypanosoma belongs to which of the following order?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kinetoplastida",
            "b) Retortamonadida",
            "c) Choanoflagellida",
            "d) Trichomonadida"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Trypanosoma belongs to the order Kinetoplastida which are grouped with other organisms due to the presence of kinetoplast (an extracellular region of DNA associated with the mitochondrion)."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "The Trichomonads found in the intestine are ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trichomonas buccalis",
            "b) Trichomonas hominis",
            "c) Trichomonas vaginalis",
            "d) Trichonympha campanula"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Trichomonas hominis are found in the intestine where they may be associated with diarrheal conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "African sleeping sickness is transmitted by which of the following agents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) biting insects",
            "b) sexual means",
            "c) tsetse fly",
            "d) bloodsucking insects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Trypanosoma rhodesiense are transmitted by the tsetse fly and causes African sleeping sickness."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "Which of the following protozoa construct shells of silica?",
        "Options": [
            "a) foraminiferans",
            "b) radiolarians",
            "c) heliozoida",
            "d) sporozoa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Amoebas carry on a special kind of respiration in the form of an exchange of gases between the cell and the surrounding fluid, for at rather regular intervals vacuoles apparently containing some carbon dioxide in solution are expelled from the cell through an opening that develops in the cell membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "The Sporozoa belongs to which of the following phylum?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ciliophora",
            "b) Labyrinthomorpha",
            "c) Microspora",
            "d) Apicomplexa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Radiolarians, like foraminiferans, are marine forms, but most of them construct shells of silica. Deposits of their skeletons are incorporated in rocks formed in areas where they have occurred in abundance."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "What is the shape of Paramecium?",
        "Options": [
            "a) circular",
            "b) slipper-like",
            "c) spindle shaped",
            "d) irregular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Sporozoa belongs to the phylum Apicomplexa. All sporozoa are parasitic for one or more animal species."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "Undigested particles are eliminated from the cell through the ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) gullet",
            "b) contractile vacuole",
            "c) cytoproct",
            "d) cell membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Paramecia are easily distinguished by their characteristic shape, which has been likened to that of slipper. The anterior end of the cell is rounded and the posterior end is slightly pointed giving it a slipper-like shape."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Which of the following comprises large cone-shaped protozoa?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Didinium",
            "b) Vorticella",
            "c) Stentor",
            "d) Colpoda"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Paramecium the undigested particles are eliminated from the cell through the cytoproct. Waste fluids are collected in the contractile vacuoles."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "The nucleic acid core of phages is covered by a protein coat known as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) capsomere",
            "b) capsid",
            "c) outer envelope",
            "d) nuclear membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All phages have a nucleic acid core covered by a protein coat or capsid. The capsid is made up of morphological subunits called capsomeres."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "The most complex type of bacterial virus has which of the following morphological features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) hexagonal head and tail fibres",
            "b) no contractile sheath",
            "c) hexagonal head but no tail",
            "d) hexagonal head, rigid tail with contractile sheath"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The most complex type has a hexagonal head, a rigid tail with a contractile sheath, and tail fibers."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for the bacteriophage MV-L2?",
        "Options": [
            "a) head is made up of large capsomeres",
            "b) head is made up of small capsomeres",
            "c) no contractile sheath is present",
            "d) filamentous form"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bacteriophage MV-L2 has a filamentous form. This type is found in some plant viruses."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "What is the shape of helical phages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) regular solids",
            "b) polyhedra",
            "c) rod-shaped",
            "d) icosahedral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pleomorphic viruses were recently discovered to have a lipid-containing envelope, have no detectable capsid, and possess double-stranded DNA (ds-DNA)."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Which of the following are said to have binal symmetry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) M13",
            "b) T4",
            "c) T7",
            "d) MV-L2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Helical phages are rod-shaped whereas cubical phages are regular solids or more specifically polyhedra."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a family of lambda phage viruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pedoviridae",
            "b) Microviridae",
            "c) Styloviridae",
            "d) Corticoviridae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: T-even coliphages such as T2, T4, and T6, are said to have binal symmetry because each virion has both an icosahedral head and a hollow helical tail."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "Which of the following coliphage has tadpole shape?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T1",
            "b) T4",
            "c) T5",
            "d) T7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The DNA of phage lambda is linear in the virion, but on entering the host cell the cohesive ends join to form a circle."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "Which of the following are filamentous phage of E.coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) f1",
            "b) T3",
            "c) f1 and fd",
            "d) T3 and T7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:Styloviridae is a family of lambda phage viruses that are non-enveloped and has dsDNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the first step in replication by bacterial phages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) adsorption",
            "b) penetration",
            "c) transcription",
            "d) assembly and release"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first step in the infection of a host bacterial cell by a phage is adsorption. The infection of a host bacterial cell cannot occur without adsorption."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "At what temperature incubation is required for the adsorption of phage T4 and DNA injection into E.coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50 degree C",
            "b) 15 degree C",
            "c) 37 degree C",
            "d) 80 degree C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phage T4 adsorption and DNA injection into E.coli spheroplasts require the phage particles to be incubated with spheroplasts at 37 degree C for 10 mins."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the correct sequence of events in replication by bacterial phage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) adsorption, pinning, DNA injection, sheath contraction",
            "b) adsorption, pinning, sheath contraction, DNA injection",
            "c) adsorption, absorption, sheath contraction, pinning",
            "d) absorption, adsorption, DNA injection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first step in the process of replication by bacterial phage is adsorption to the host cell. This is followed by pinning when the tail pins attach to the cell surface. Then the sheath contracts driving the tail core into the cell through the cell membrane and then the virus injects its DNA into the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "The delayed early genes codes for which of the following enzymes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) phage enzymes",
            "b) RNA polymerase",
            "c) nucleases",
            "d) oxidases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The protein coat, which forms the phage head, and the tail structure of the virus remains outside the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzymes transcribe late genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ligases",
            "b) nucleases",
            "c) RNA polymerase",
            "d) restriction enzymes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Delayed early genes code for phage enzymes which produce unique phage DNA constituents such as 5-hydroxymethylcytosines; which destroy precursors of cytosine deoxynucleotides so that no bacterial cytosine will be incorporated into phage DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "In the growth curve of plaque-forming units, the time from infection until lysis is known as ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) eclipse period",
            "b) rise period",
            "c) burst period",
            "d) latent period"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Delayed early genes code for second altered RNA polymerase that will transcribe the late genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "What is the colour of the plaque formed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) yellow",
            "b) opaque",
            "c) clear",
            "d) blue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: No newly released extracellular phages can be seen until lysis begins; the time from infection until lysis is the latent period."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "What does a viral DNA becomes after being associated with the bacterial chromosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) gene",
            "b) prophage",
            "c) plasmid",
            "d) plaque"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In lysogeny the viral DNA of the temperate phage, instead of taking over the functions of the cell’s genes, is incorporated into the host DNA and becomes a prophage in the bacterial chromosome, acting as a gene."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "In which of the following method, the viral particles are transmitted through lysis of cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lytic cycle",
            "b) Lysogeny",
            "c) Replication",
            "d) Translation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the lytic cycle after the infection of bacterial cells by phages, the viral particles are transmitted through lysis of cell and finally terminates."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the characteristic of repressor protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) basic protein",
            "b) acidic protein",
            "c) basic protein, molecular weight of 26000",
            "d) acidic protein, molecular weight of 26000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The temperate phage possesses a gene that codes for a repressor protein which makes the cell resistant to lysis initiated either by the prophage or by lytic infection by other viruses. The multiplication of the phage is repressed and lysogenization occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "Which of the following gene codes for an enzyme which directs the insertion of the phage DNA into the bacterial chromosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) recA gene",
            "b) cro gene",
            "c) int gene",
            "d) gal gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The repressor protein is an acidic protein with a molecular weight of 26000. It has been isolated from lambda phage and purified."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "Which of the following phage do not cause lysogeny?",
        "Options": [
            "a) T2",
            "b) T1",
            "c) lambda",
            "d) P1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Upon infection by lambda phage, the phage cro gene is transcribed, resulting in the synthesis of a protein repressor that inhibits the synthesis of the immunity repressor."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "The protein integrase is encoded by which of the following gene?",
        "Options": [
            "a) gal gene",
            "b) lambda gene",
            "c) bio gene",
            "d) cro gene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A lambda phage enzyme, coded by the int gene, directs the insertion of the phage DNA into the bacterial chromosome. It catalyzes a single site-specific recombination event, resulting in the insertion of the phage DNA into the cell genome."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "In which of the following phage prophage exists as a circular form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phage lambda type",
            "b) Phage P1 type",
            "c) Phage T2 type",
            "d) Phage T1 type"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phages like T2 that do not cause lysogeny are termed virulent. Phages produced by lysogenic strains are termed temperate phages, and the relationship between the phage and the bacterium is termed lysogeny."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "From which of the following animal was the material isolated which was used for the vaccination for the first time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cat",
            "b) cow",
            "c) pig",
            "d) goat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Jenner used the material isolated from cows to be used as vaccination and it provided protection against natural smallpox infection."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Vaccination was invented by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Jenner",
            "b) Pasteur",
            "c) Watson",
            "d) Crick"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1796 Jenner first vaccinated an 8-year old boy with material removed from cow and it gave protection against the smallpox virus."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Yellow fever virus can be attenuated by serial passage on cultures of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) embryonated eggs",
            "b) tissue",
            "c) chick embryo tissue",
            "d) pig embryo tissue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1892, Dmitrii Ivanowski discovered that the causative agent of tobacco mosaic disease was filterable. Viruses that can pass through porcelain filters are known as filterable viruses."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Effective poliomyelitis vaccines were developed by culturing the virus of poliomyelitis on the kidney cells of which animal?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cow",
            "b) monkey",
            "c) giraffe",
            "d) pig"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Max Theiler found in 1937 that virulent yellow fever virus can be attenuated by serial passage on cultures of chick embryo tissue."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "For which viral disease, vaccine has been recently developed through the use of tissue culture?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Measles",
            "b) Mumps",
            "c) Rabies",
            "d) S mallpox"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enders, Robbins, and Weller laid the foundation for the development of effective poliomyelitis vaccines by culturing the virus of poliomyelitis on monkey kidney cells in 1949."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Translation of mRNA into proteins takes place in the ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) host cell nucleus",
            "b) host cell cytoplasm",
            "c) viral nucleus",
            "d) viral cytoplasm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Among the virus diseases for which vaccines have been recently developed through the use of tissue culture is measles (rubeola)."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which of the following symmetry is exhibited by rod-shaped viruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) icosahedral",
            "b) helical",
            "c) complex",
            "d) circular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The animal and plant viruses are composed of a central core of nucleic acid surrounded by a capsid, which is made up of capsomeres. They exhibit a characteristic symmetry like the rod-shaped viruses have helical symmetry."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "The envelope surrounding the nucleocapsid of some animal viruses is made up of which of the following structures?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lipoproteins",
            "b) lipopolysaccharides",
            "c) peptidoglycan",
            "d) chitin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In some animal viruses the nucleocapsid is covered by an outer membranelike structure called the envelope, which is made up of lipoproteins and conceals the symmetry. They are sensitive to lipid solvents such as ether and chloroform."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Adenoviruses exhibit which of the following symmetry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) helical symmetry",
            "b) circular symmetry",
            "c) icosahedral symmetry",
            "d) complex structure symmetry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Adenoviruses which cause respiratory infections are examples of icosahedral viruses."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "The fringes on animal viruses like influenza virus is made up of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) lipoproteins",
            "b) glycoproteins",
            "c) cellulose",
            "d) polysaccharides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the influenza virus the nucleocapsid is a flexible structure packed within a fringed lipoprotein envelope. The fringes are actually spiked projections made of glycoproteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "Parvoviruses contain how many genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 genes",
            "b) 500 genes",
            "c) 40 genes",
            "d) 3 genes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Like bacteriophages, animal and plant viruses contain either DNA or RNA, but never both in the same virion."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "In papovaviruses, DNA occurs in which of the following forms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) linear dsDNA",
            "b) linear ssDNA",
            "c) supercoiled circular dsDNA",
            "d) supercoiled circular ssDNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If 1 kilobase is considered as the size of an average gene, small viruses like parvoviruses and picornaviruses contain perhaps 3 or 4 genes and large viruses contain several hundred."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "In which of the following viruses DNA forms hairpins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) parvoviruses",
            "b) herpesviruses",
            "c) poxviruses",
            "d) picornaviruses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In papovaviruses, DNA occurs as a supercoiled circular dsDNA. Supercoiling refers to the extra turns in the structure of dsDNA due to the action of the enzyme DNA gyrase."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "Which of the following are characteristics of the process viropexis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) phagocytic process",
            "b) plant viruses penetrate host cells through ectodesmata",
            "c) occurs by the enzyme RNA polymerase",
            "d) phagocytic process and occurs by the enzyme lysosomal proteases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In ssDNA parvoviruses the terminal bases of linear DNA exist as inverted repeat sequences that form hairpins. That is, the sequence of terminal bases on each strand of such DNA maybe represented as ABCD…….D’C’B’A’, where ABCD are complementary to A’B’C’D’."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Which of the following viruses carry minus-strand RNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) rhabdoviruses",
            "b) picornaviruses",
            "c) retroviruses",
            "d) tobacco mosaic viruses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Some plant viruses appear to have a genome of circular dsRNA. But the RNA in animal viruses exists only as linear double-stranded or single-stranded molecules."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "How many dsRNA segments are present in the reovirus genome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 3",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Reoviruses contain both the + and the — strands of dsRNA and its genome consists of 10 dsRNA segments. During uncoating ten mRNA molecules are transcribed from one strand of the dsRNA and pass into the host cell cytoplasm."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "Enterovirus belongs to which of the following family of viruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tymovirus",
            "b) Picornaviridae",
            "c) Reoviridae",
            "d) Closterovirus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enterovirus belongs to the family Picornaviridae and it has a virion size of 28 nm."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "Which of the following viruses possess an envelope?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Herpesvirus",
            "b) Reovirus",
            "c) Tobacco mosaic virus",
            "d) Papillomavirus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Rous sarcoma virus belongs to Retroviridae family, has a virion size of 100-120. It possesses icosahedral symmetry and consists of RNA as its genetic material."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "Which of the following viruses have a complex symmetry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alphavirus",
            "b) Mobillivirus",
            "c) Orthopoxvirus",
            "d) Parvovirus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Herpesvirus possesses an icosahedral symmetry and contains DNA as its genetic material. Its nucleocapsid is surrounded by an envelope."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "Cowpea virus belongs to which of the following group of viruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Comovirus",
            "b) Dianthovirus",
            "c) Cucumovirus",
            "d) Carlavirus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Orthopoxvirus posseses a complex symmetry and is surrounded by a coat. It consists of DNA as its nucleic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "For the cultivation of viruses the fertile chicken eggs should be incubated for how many day(s)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2-4",
            "c) 5-12",
            "d) 2-7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The family of Rhabdoviridae consists of ssRNA and they are enveloped. An example is vesicular stomatitis."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used for the production of vaccines against yellow fever?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tissue-culture method",
            "b) chick-embryo method",
            "c) through susceptible animals",
            "d) through appropriate media"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cowpea mosaic belongs to the Comovirus group of viruses. They are non-enveloped and possess ssRNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "The karyotype of cells formed from continuous cell lines is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) haploid",
            "b) diploid",
            "c) aneuploid",
            "d) haploid and diploid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the cultivation of viruses by embryonated chicken eggs, the fertile chicken eggs should be incubated for 5 to 12 days and then they can be inoculated through the shell aseptically."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "Which of the following inclusion bodies are present in the cytoplasm of the Purkinje cells of the cerebellum in the case of rabies infection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paschen bodies",
            "b) Guarnieri bodies",
            "c) Negri bodies",
            "d) Elementary bodies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Characteristic inclusion bodies are found in the cytoplasm of the Purkinje cells of the cerebellum and in certain other nerve cells in cases of rabies infection. These typical inclusion bodies are Negri bodies and is diagnostic of the disease."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "Bollinger bodies are found in the cytoplasm of cells infected by which of the following viruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) variola virus",
            "b) fowl pox virus",
            "c) rabies virus",
            "d) herpes virus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bollinger bodies are found in the cytoplasm of cells infected with fowl pox virus. It is a type of inclusion body produced by viruses in certain host tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "Scrapie is a chronic disease of which of the following animals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) sheep",
            "b) mouse",
            "c) mink",
            "d) cow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Intranuclear inclusions are found in chicken pox, herpes, and the polyhedra diseases of insects. Intranuclear and intracytoplasmic inclusions may be found in the same cell in instances of multiple infections."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "In which of the following categories of cancer solid tumors grow from derivatives of embryonal mesoderm?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leukemias",
            "b) Lymphomas",
            "c) Sarcomas",
            "d) Carcinomas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Scrapie is so named because the diseased animal tends to scrape against fixed objects. It is a chronic infection of the central nervous system of sheep."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "Which among the following is the family of RNA containing viruses that can cause cancer in animals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Herpesviridae",
            "b) Adenoviridae",
            "c) Papovaviridae",
            "d) Retroviridae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Sarcoma solid tumors grow from derivatives of embryonal mesoderm, such as connective tissues, cartilage, bone, muscle and fat."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Cancer of the lip of mouth have been associated with ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) HSV1",
            "b) HSV2",
            "c) EBV",
            "d) SV 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cancer has three major characteristics: hyperplasia, anaplasia, and metastasis. Anaplasia is structural abnormality of cells (these cells also have a loss of or reduction in their functions)."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "The Epstein-Barr virus (EBV) can induce tumors in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mouse",
            "b) monkey",
            "c) humans",
            "d) rodents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Among the viruses whose virions contain RNA, only some members of the family Retroviridae cause cancer in animals. These members replicate through a DNA intermediate."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "In which of the following situations will the logarithmic plot of survivors be constant?",
        "Options": [
            "a) physiological conditions are different",
            "b) cells of microbial population vary in size",
            "c) age and physiological conditions are uniform",
            "d) temperature conditions are different"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Logarithmic plot reveals that the death rate is constant when all conditions are strictly uniform, including the age and the physiological condition of all the microorganisms in the population."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "A suspension of E.coli exposed to heat treatment may yield a greater number of survivors if a plating medium of _____________ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) peptone",
            "b) trypticase soy agar",
            "c) deoxycholate agar",
            "d) potato dextrose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A suspension of E.coli exposed to heat treatment may yield a greater number of survivors if a plating medium of trypticase soy agar is used rather than a medium containing bile salts such as deoxycholate agar."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "The effectiveness of heat in killing microorganisms is much greater in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) acid",
            "b) alkali",
            "c) neutral",
            "d) acid and alkali"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: It takes time to kill the population and if we have many cells, we must treat them for a longer time to be reasonably sure that all of the bacteria are dead."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "A high concentration of which of the following compounds in the material generally increases the thermal resistance of microorganisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) proteins",
            "b) carbohydrates",
            "c) lipids",
            "d) salts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The environment has a profound influence on the rate as well as the efficacy of microbial destruction. The effectiveness of heat is much greater in acid than in alkali material."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "Which of the following show the maximum resistance to physical and chemical agents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Viruses",
            "b) Mold spores",
            "c) Bacterial spores",
            "d) E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The consistency of the material will markedly influence the penetration of the agent and high concentration of carbohydrates generally increases the thermal resistance of organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "How much time is required by the young cells to be killed by a lethal agent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24 hours",
            "b) 3-4 hours",
            "c) 30 mins",
            "d) 5 mins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In spore forming species, the bacterial spores are extremely resistant in comparison to growing vegetative cells to physical and chemical agents."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "Which of the following actions are not affected by antimicrobial agents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cell wall synthesis",
            "b) nucleic acid synthesis",
            "c) protein synthesis",
            "d) capsule formation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The young cells are all killed within 25 minutes but a considerable part of the more resistant, older cells still survives. Young, actively metabolizing cells are apt to be more easily destroyed than old, dormant cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Among the following which one is the most effective method of killing microorganisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) High temperature",
            "b) Low temperature",
            "c) High temperature, high moisture",
            "d) Low temperature, high moisture"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: High temperatures combined with high moisture are one of the most effective methods of killing microorganisms. It is important to distinguish between dry heat and moist heat in any procedure for microbial control."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "How much time is required by spores of Clostridium botulinum to be killed by moist heat at 1200C?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 hours",
            "b) 4 to 20 minutes",
            "c) 24 hours",
            "d) 6-7 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Spores of Clostridium botulinum are killed in 4 to 20 minutes by moist heat at 1200C, whereas a 2 hours exposure to dry heat at the same temperature is required."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "Which of the following conditions are required for the determination of thermal death time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) temperature is varied",
            "b) time is fixed",
            "c) temperature is fixed and time is varied",
            "d) temperature is fixed and time is not selected"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Vegetative cells are much more sensitive to heat than the spores because of the higher level of water activity in the vegetative cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "Which of the following apparatus is used to provide steam under regulated pressure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) autoclave",
            "b) laminar air flow",
            "c) incubator",
            "d) hot oven"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In thermal death time, the temperature is selected as the fixed point and the time is varied. It refers to the shortest period of time to kill a suspension of bacteria or spores at a prescribed temperature and under specific conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "The general pressure at which the autoclave is operated is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 Psi",
            "b) 20 Psi",
            "c) 15 Psi",
            "d) 40 Psi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The laboratory apparatus designed to use steam under regulated pressure is called an autoclave. It is essentially a double-jacketed steam chamber that can maintain steam under pressure and temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods is used for killing microorganisms of only certain types and not all microorganisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pasteurization",
            "b) Incineration",
            "c) Boiling water",
            "d) Fractional Sterilization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Generally the autoclave is operated at a pressure of approximately 15 Psi at 121.50C. It is not the pressure that kills the organisms but the temperature of the steam."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "Which of the following instruments is used to perform tyndallization?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Autoclave",
            "b) Steam Arnold",
            "c) Gas oven",
            "d) Incubator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the operation of an autoclave it is absolutely essential that the air in the chamber be completely replaced by saturated steam. If air is present, it will reduce the temperature obtained within the chamber substantially below."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "Which of the following actions occur due to low temperature?",
        "Options": [
            "a) coagulation of proteins",
            "b) death of microorganisms",
            "c) rate of metabolism is reduced",
            "d) denatures proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In pasteurization, milk, cream, and certain alcoholic beverages are subjected to a controlled heat treatment that kills microorganisms of certain types but does not destroy all organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "Which of the following are resistant to desiccation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) gonococci",
            "b) streptococci",
            "c) meningococci",
            "d) bacillus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For tyndallization or fractional sterilization the apparatus used is the Steam Arnold however an autoclave can also be used if a free-flowing steam is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "Passage of water from a low solute concentration into the cell is referred to as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) plasmoptysis",
            "b) plasmolysis",
            "c) isotonic",
            "d) hypertonic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Temperatures below the optimum for growth depresses the rate of metabolism and if the temperature is sufficiently low, growth and metabolism ceases. Low temperature are also useful for the preservation of cultures."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "Which of the following radiations have the energy to knock electrons away from molecules and ionize them?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-ionizing radiations",
            "b) Acoustic radiations",
            "c) Subatomic particles",
            "d) Ionizing radiations"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Streptococci are much more resistant to dessication, some survive weeks after being dried but species of Gram-negative cocci are very sensitive to dessication."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "Wavelengths around ___________ have the highest bactericidal efficiency.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150 Å",
            "b) 3900 Å",
            "c) 2650 Å",
            "d)1500 Å"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The passage of water from a low solute concentration into the cell is termed plasmoptysis. The pressure built up within the cell as a result of this water intake is termed osmotic pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "Which of the following inhibits DNA replication?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cathode rays",
            "b) UV light",
            "c) x-rays",
            "d) gamma rays"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gamma rays and x-rays are called ionizing radiations because they have enough energy to knock electrons away from molecules and ionize them. When such radiations pass through cells, they create free hydrogen radicals, hydroxyl radicals and some peroxides which causes intracellular damage."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "Which material is used for the Berkefeld filter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) diatomaceous earth",
            "b) asbestos pad",
            "c) porcelain",
            "d) sintered glass disks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ultraviolet portion of the spectrum includes all radiations from 150 to 3900 Å. Wavelengths around 2650 Å have the highest bactericidal efficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "A chemical agent that kills the microorganisms and is commonly applied to substances used on inanimate objects are _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antiseptics",
            "b) Sanitizer",
            "c) Disinfectants",
            "d) Antibiotics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Disinfectant is a chemical agent that kills the growing forms but not necessarily the resistant spore forms of disease-producing microorganisms. They are commonly applied to substances used on inanimate objects."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "An agent that prevents the growth of bacteria are known as __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bactericide",
            "b) Bacteriostatic",
            "c) Antimicrobial",
            "d) Antibiotic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An agent that prevents or inhibits the growth of bacteria are known as bacteriostatic agents and the condition is known as bacteriostasis."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the characteristics of a sanitizer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) destroys all microbial forms",
            "b) prevents the growth or action of microorganisms",
            "c) reduces the microbial population to safe levels",
            "d) kills all the bacteria and the bacterial spores"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: One of the characteristics of chemical agents is that they should be toxic to microorganisms at room or body temperature. In using the compound, it should not be necessary to raise the temperature beyond that normally found in the environment where it is to be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a chemical agent for microbial control?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radiations",
            "b) Antibiotics",
            "c) Antiseptics",
            "d) Germicide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sanitizer is an agent that reduces the microbial population to safe levels as prescribed by public health requirements. Usually it is a chemical agent that kills 99.9% of the growing bacteria and are generally applied to inanimate objects."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "The process of killing all microorganisms along with their spores is ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Disinfection",
            "b) Antisepsis",
            "c) Sanitization",
            "d) Sterilization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Radiations are physical agents for microbial control and include ionizing as well as non-ionizing radiations to kill the microorganisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "Which of the following are generally applied on living animal tissues?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antiseptics",
            "b) Disinfectants",
            "c) Preservatives",
            "d) Sanitizer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Chemical agents are not all equally effective against bacteria, fungi, and other microorganisms. Differences exist between Gram-positive and Gram-negative bacteria:\nEscherichia coli is much more resistant to cationic disinfectants than Staphylococcus aureus."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "How much percentage of the aqueous solution of phenol rapidly kills the vegetative cells of microorganisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 2%",
            "c) 5%",
            "d) 10%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Phenol is a very effective disinfectant. A 5% aqueous solution of phenol rapidly kills the vegetative cells of microorganisms; spores are much more resistant."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "The antimicrobial activity of phenolics is not reduced at which of the following conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) acidic pH",
            "b) alkaline pH",
            "c) low temperatures",
            "d) presence of soap"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The antimicrobial activity of phenolics is reduced at an alakaline pH and by organic material. Low temperatures and the presence of soap also reduce antimicrobial activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "Alcohol concentrations above 60% are effective against _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bacteria",
            "b) fungi",
            "c) germs",
            "d) viruses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Alcohol concentrations above 60% are effective against viruses; however the effectiveness is influenced considerably by the amount of extraneous protein material in the mixture. The extraneous protein reacts with the alcohol and thus protects the virus."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "Polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP) is a complex belonging to which group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phenolic compounds",
            "b) Iodophors",
            "c) Metals",
            "d) Aldehyde"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polyvinylpyrrolidone (PVP) is a complex belonging to iodophors. Iodophors are mixtures of iodine with surface-active agents which act as carriers and solubilizers for the iodine. They possess the germicidal characteristics of iodine."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "Which of the following agents irreversibly oxidize and inactivate proteins with sulphydral groups?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alcohol",
            "b) Phenol",
            "c) Iodine",
            "d) Chlorine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Iodine is an oxidizing agent and oxidizing agents can irreversibly oxidize and thus inactivate essential metabolic compounds such as proteins with sulphydral groups."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "Chlorinated lime is the alternative name for __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcium hypochlorite",
            "b) Sodium hypochlorite",
            "c) Chloramine-T",
            "d) Azochloramide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Calcium hypochlorite, Ca(OCl)2  is also known as chlorinated lime and it acts as an effective disinfectant like free chlorine."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "Solutions of sodium hypochlorite of a 1% concentration are used for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sanitizing dairy equipment",
            "b) personal hygiene and a household disinfectant",
            "c) household bleaches",
            "d) disinfecting open wounds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One of the advantages of chloramines is stability; they are more stable than the hypochlorites in terms of prolonged release of chlorine."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Which among the following is an example of an organic compound of mercury?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mercuric chloride",
            "b) Mercuric oxide",
            "c) Mercurochrome",
            "d) Ammoniated mercury"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Solutions of sodium hypochlorite of a 1% concentration are used for personal hygiene and as a household disinfectant and higher concentrations of 5-12% are also employed as household bleaches."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Which of the following agents cause death to the cell by coagulation of cytoplasmic proteins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alcohol",
            "b) Dyes",
            "c) Chlorine",
            "d) Heavy metals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Mercurochrome is an organic compound of mercury which are less irritating and less toxic than the inorganic mercury compounds. They are employed as antiseptics on cutaneous and mucosal surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an acridine dye?",
        "Options": [
            "a) crystal violet",
            "b) malachite green",
            "c) tryptoflavine",
            "d) brilliant green"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: High concentration of salts of heavy metals like mercury, silver, and copper coagulate cytoplasmic proteins resulting in damage or death to the cell. Salts of heavy metals are also precipitants and in high concentrations they cause the death of cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Gonococci are inhibited by tryptoflavine in dilutions of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1:200,000",
            "b) 1:300,000",
            "c) 1:1,000,000",
            "d) 1:10,000,000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gram-positive organisms are more susceptible to lower concentrations of triphenylmethane dyes than are Gram-negative ones."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "Ceepryn belongs to which of the following categories?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Anionic detergents",
            "b) Cationic detergents",
            "c) Nonionic detergents",
            "d) Ammonium salts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two examples of dyes derived from acridine are acriflavine and tryptoflavine. These compounds exhibit selective inhibition against bacteria, particularly staphylococci and gonococci."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "Which of the following agents are used as a preservative in ophthalmic solutions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) alcohol",
            "b) quaternary ammonium salts",
            "c) phenol",
            "d) aldehydes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gonococci are inhibited by tryptoflavine in dilutions of 1:10,000,000 to 1:50,000,000. They possess little, if any, antifungal activity."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "Which of the following methods is used for determining the decrease in the amount of growth?",
        "Options": [
            "a) test done on agar medium plate",
            "b) test done into an agar medium or broth",
            "c) test done by transfering water-soluble substances to sterile media",
            "d) by phenol-coefficient method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The chemical agent is incorporated into an agar medium or broth, inoculated with the test organism, incubated, and then observed for (i) decrease in the amount of growth or (ii)complete absence of growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "Liquid water-soluble substances appropriately diluted are dispensed into sterile test tubes, to which are added a measured amount of the test organism and then this is transferred into tubes of sterile media.This method helps in determining _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) whether the inhibitory action is bactericidal",
            "b) whether the inhibitory action is bacteristatic",
            "c) decrease in the amount of growth",
            "d) complete absence of growth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Liquid water-soluble substances appropriately diluted are dispensed into sterile test tubes, to which are added a measured amount of the test organism. At specified intervals, a transfer is made from this tube into tubes of sterile media that are then incubated and observed for the appearance of growth. It is necessary to ascertain whether the inhibitory action is bactericidal and not bacteriostatic."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as a test organism in the procedure of phenol-coefficient method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Escherichia coli",
            "b) Streptococcus faecalis",
            "c) Staphylococcus aureus",
            "d) Lactobacillus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: From laboratory evaluation of chemical antimicrobial agents it is found that there is increased growth in nutrient agar plates as the concentration of chemical agents is reduced."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "Which of the following chemical agents lack penetrating power?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Phenol",
            "b) Iodine",
            "c) Ethylene oxide",
            "d) Beta-propiolactone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the procedure of Phenol-Coefficient method the test organism employed is a specific strain of either Salmonella typhi or Staphylococcus aureus. This procedure is suitable for testing disinfectants miscible with water and exerting antimicrobial action in a manner similar to that of phenol."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "Which of the following agent is used to disinfect skin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chlorine",
            "b) Formaldehyde",
            "c) Quaternaries",
            "d) Ethylene oxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Beta-propiolactone is a chemical agent that is used for sterilizing instruments and heat-sensitive materials but it lacks the penetrating power."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the mode of action of formaldehyde?",
        "Options": [
            "a) interference with glycolysis",
            "b) shows oxidizing property",
            "c) combines with vital nitrogen compounds",
            "d) changes the permeability of cytoplasmic membrane"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Quaternaries like quaternary ammonium salts are used as a skin disinfectant due to its disinfectant property and detergent property. But it is not sporicidal in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "For sterilization of plastic syringes in hospitals which of the following agents are used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ethylene oxide",
            "b) dyes",
            "c) radiations",
            "d) heavy metals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Alcohols, phenols and heavy-metal salts are used to kill the microorganisms by causing denaturation of proteins and reducing the enzyme activity. "
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of a chemotherapeutic agent?",
        "Options": [
            "a) low toxicity for host cells",
            "b) high toxicity for the parasites",
            "c) less penetrating power",
            "d) does not affect the host’s natural defense mechanism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A chemotherapeutic agent must be able to come in contact with the parasite by penetrating the cells and tissues of the host in effective concentrations."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "Which was the first disease for which a chemotherapeutic agent was used?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Syphilis",
            "b) Malaria",
            "c) Small pox",
            "d) AIDS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Antiseptics and germicides such as phenol, coal-tar derivatives and many mercurial compounds are unsatisfactory as chemotherapeutic agents as they do not show selective toxicity for the parasite."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "Sulfanilamide was synthesized by which of the following research scientists?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Eisenberg",
            "b) Gelmo",
            "c) Ehrlich",
            "d) Domagk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Syphilis is the first known disease for which a chemotherapeutic agent was used. An arsenical compound known as Salvarsan was synthesized by Paul Ehrlich in 1910 to treat this disease."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "Which of the following chemothearpeutic agent is extensively used because of their antibacterial effectiveness in a wide range of bacterial infections?",
        "Options": [
            "a) arsphenamine",
            "b) sulfanilamide",
            "c) sulfonamide",
            "d) sulfadiazine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Domagk showed the therapeutic value of a group of compounds known as the sulfonamides and Sulfanilamide was the first compound in this group to be synthesized by Gelmo in 1910."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "The antibiotic penicillin was discovered by which of the following researchers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Emmerich and Low",
            "b) Gratia and Dath",
            "c) Alexander Flemming",
            "d) Vuillemin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sulfonamides are not specific for a special group of organisms, as arsphenamine is for Treponema, but are effective against a large variety of pathogenic organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "Which of the following antibiotic is not involved in the inhibition of specific enzyme systems?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penicillin",
            "b) Tetracycline",
            "c) Sulphonamides",
            "d) Chloramphenicol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sulfadiazine and sulfamerazine are extensively used because of their antibacterial effectiveness in a wide range of bacterial infections and because they are least likely to produce toxic reactions in the patient."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "Bacterial cells grown in a medium exposed to high osmotic pressure, changes shape from rod-shaped to __________ shaped.",
        "Options": [
            "a) spherical",
            "b) rod shaped",
            "c) irregular",
            "d) elongated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The high osmotic pressure prevents the cells from bursting. Rod-shaped cells become spherical because they lack the cell structure which imparts shape."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "Cell-wall biosynthesis is inhibited by antibiotics by inhibiting the biosynthesis of which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lipopolysaccharide",
            "b) cellulose",
            "c) peptidoglycan",
            "d) proteins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Antibiotics exert their microbial effect by inhibiting biosynthesis of the peptidoglycan polymer, resulting in the inhibition of cell-wall formation. This results in the inability of the bacterium to survive because of the absence of a protective covering."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "The crystalline sodium or potassium salts are slightly soluble in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ether",
            "b) dioxane",
            "c) water",
            "d) chloroform"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All penicillins have a common basic nucleus, a fused beta-lactam-thiazolidine ring with different side chains that give each its unique properties."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not affect the activity of penicillin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bile",
            "b) hydrochloric acid",
            "c) cysteine",
            "d) sodium hydroxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Natural penicillins can be prepared as salts of sodium, potassium, procaine, and other bases. The crystalline sodium or potassium salts are freely soluble in water, ester, ethers, ethyl alcohol, and dioxane but only slightly soluble in chloroform and benzene."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "Benzylpenicillin is the chemical name for which of the following penicillin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penicillin G",
            "b) Penicillin V",
            "c) Penicillin F",
            "d) Phenethicilin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The natural penicillins are inactivated by heat, cysteine, sodium hydroxide, penicillinase, and hydrochloric acid. They are not affected by the action of saliva or bile."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "Streptomyces orientalis produces which of the following antibiotics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cephalosporins",
            "b) Cycloserine",
            "c) Bacitracin",
            "d) Vancomycin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Peniciilin G is also known as Benzylpenicillin which is natural penicillin and has a basic core of 6-aminopenicillanic acid different side chain."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "Which of the following interferes with the regeneration of the monophosphate form of bactoprenol from the pyrophosphate form?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vancomycin",
            "b) Ampicillin",
            "c) Bacitracin",
            "d) Cephalosporins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ampicillin is another semisynthetic penicillin which is strongly bactericidal and lacks toxicity, but is not resistant to penicillinases."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "Polymyxins inhibits the growth of the microbes by carrying out which of the following actions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) inhibition of cell-wall synthesis",
            "b) damage to cytoplasmic membrane",
            "c) inhibition of nucleic acid and protein synthesis",
            "d) inhibition of specific enzyme systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Vancomycin is an antibiotic produced by Streptomyces orientalis. It is a complex chemical entity consisting of amino acids and sugars."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "Streptomycin is produced by which of the following organisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stretomyces noursei",
            "b) Streptomyces nodosus",
            "c) Streptomyces fradiae",
            "d) Streptomyces griseus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacitracin interferes with regeneration of the monophosphate form of bactoprenol from the pyrophosphate form. It is a polypeptide chemically."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "Antibiotic produced by Streptomyces rimosus is _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chlortetracycline",
            "b) oxytetracycline",
            "c) tetracycline",
            "d) doxycycline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: Polymyxins, gramicidins, and tyrocidines cause damage to cytoplasmic membrane. They adversely affect the normal permeability characters of the cell membrane."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "Which of the following inhibits protein synthesis by combining with the 50S subunit ribosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptomycin",
            "b) Tetracycline",
            "c) Chloramphenicol",
            "d) Penicillin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Streptomycin is produced by Streptomyces griseus, a soil organism isolated by Schatz, Bugie and Waksman, who reported on its antibiotic activities in 1944."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "Tyrocidines are more effective against ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gram-positive organisms",
            "b) Gram-negative organisms",
            "c) Mycoplasmas",
            "d) Spirochetes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Antibiotic produced by Streptomyces rimosus is oxytetracycline whereas Streptomyces aureofaciens produces chlortetracycline. They are broad spectrum antibiotics with similar antimicrobial spectra, and cross resistance of bacteria to them is common."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "Which of the following is the most accurate method for microbial assay of antibiotics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical assay",
            "b) Chemical assay",
            "c) Biological assay",
            "d) Chemical and biological assay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chemical-assay methods are generally more accurate and require less time than biological methods, but they are less sensitive, and caution must be used lest biologically inactive degradation products give misleading results."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "The international unit of penicillin is defined by how much amount of International Standard?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 mg",
            "b) 0.262 µg",
            "c) 0.5988 µg",
            "d) 0.5 mg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The international unit of penicillin is the amount of activity produced under defined conditions by 0.5988 µg of the International Standard, which is a sample of pure benzyl-penicillin."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "Pigs respond dramatically to the addition of which of the following antibiotics to their diet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) aureomycin",
            "b) terramycin",
            "c) penicillin",
            "d) oxytetracycline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Small paper disks impregnated with known amounts of chemotherapeutic agents are placed upon the surface of an inoculated plate. So after incubation in disk-plate methods, a zone of inhibition around the disk indicates that the organism was inhibited by the drug."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "Which of the following antibiotic have a sparing effect on the B12 in the diet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptomycin",
            "b) Tetracycline",
            "c) Anthramycin",
            "d) Chloramphenicol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It has been suggested that pigs respond dramatically to the addition of oxytetracycline to their diet because the antibiotic inhibits the growth of Clostridium perfringens in their intestines and prevents a chronic but subclinical toxemia."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "Nystatin is produced from the strain _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptomyces noursei",
            "b) Streptomyces aureofaciens",
            "c) Streptomyces kanamyceticus",
            "d) Streptomyces fradiae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Streptomycin may have a “sparing effect” on the B12 in the diet, making it available in greater quantities for utilization by the animals. "
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "Acycloguanosine is a nucleoside analog which is active against ___________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Influenza A virus",
            "b) HIV virus",
            "c) Herpes virus",
            "d) Influenza B virus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Some antibiotics are effective against plant pathogens and are attractive for the treatment of plant diseases. The extent of this practice is limited mainly by economic factors, i.e, the cost of the antibiotic."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "Which of the following has its antiviral action attributed to the interference of protein synthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Amantadine",
            "b) Interferons",
            "c) Acycloguanosine",
            "d) 5’-iododeoxyuridine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Nystatin is an antifungal agent produced during fermentation by a strain of Streptomyces noursei."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "Which of the following is effective in the control of tuberculosis in humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrofurans",
            "b) Nalidixic Acid",
            "c) Sibromycin",
            "d) Isoniazid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Griseofluvin is used in the treatment of many superficial fungal infections of the skin and body surfaces and is also effective in the treatment of systemic mycoses."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "Anthramycin is which of the following type of antibiotic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antiviral",
            "b) Antitumor",
            "c) Antifungal",
            "d) Antibacterial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Acycloguanosine is a nucleoside analog that is active against the herpes virus in animals. Its mode of action appears to be that of inhibition of nucleotide utilization."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "The association which involves the exchange of nutrients between two species is referred to as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mutualism",
            "b) syntrophism",
            "c) commensalism",
            "d) antagonism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Syntrophism is a mutualistic association that involves the exchange of nutrients between two species."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "The degradation of complex molecules in soil by fungi for utilization by bacteria is an example of which type of association?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neutralism",
            "b) Mutualism",
            "c) Commensalism",
            "d) Antagonism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Many bacteria are unable to utilize cellulose, but they can and do utilize the fungal breakdown products of cellulose e.g., glucose and organic acids. This phenomenon is referred to as commensalism."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of association is present among Staphylococcus aureus and Aspergillus terreous?",
        "Options": [
            "a) antagonism",
            "b) mutualism",
            "c) parasitism",
            "d) commensalism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Staphylococcus aureus produces a diffusable antifungal material that causes distortions and hyphal swellings in Aspergillus terreous. This is an antagonistic relationship between these two organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "Lytic enzymes which destroy are secreted by which of the following microorganism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fungi",
            "b) algae",
            "c) staphylococcus",
            "d) myxobacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Myxobacteria (slime bacteria) and streptomycetes are antagonistic because they secrete potent lytic enzymes which destroy other cells by digesting their cell wall or other protective surface layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "Fungi produces which of the following inhibitory toxic product?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cyanide",
            "b) fatty acids",
            "c) methane",
            "d) sulphides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Cyanide is produced by certain fungi in concentrations toxic to other microorganisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "Which of the following comes under the category of positive association?",
        "Options": [
            "a) neutralism",
            "b) parasitism",
            "c) commensalism",
            "d) ammensalism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The phenomenon of commensalism is a positive type of association because it refers to a relationship between organisms in which one species of a pair benefits, the other is not affected."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "The dominant mineral particles in most soils are compounds of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sodium",
            "b) potassium",
            "c) magnesium",
            "d) iron"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Parasitism is defined as a relationship between organisms in which one organism lives in or on another organism referred to as a host."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "Which of the following organisms are known to grow on the surfaces of freshly exposed rocks?",
        "Options": [
            "a) green algae",
            "b) diatoms",
            "c) cyanobacteria",
            "d) yeast"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The dominant mineral particles in most soils are compounds of silicon, aluminum, iron and lesser amounts of other minerals, including calcium, magnesium, potassium, sodium, nitrogen etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "Ammonia oxidizers and nitrite oxidizers are ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gram-negative chemolithotrophs",
            "b) Gram-positive chemolithotrophs",
            "c) Gram-negative photolithotrophs",
            "d) Gram-positive photolithotrophs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Oxidation of ammonia to nitrite by ammonia-oxidizing bacteria and oxidation of nitrite to nitrate by nitrite-oxidizing bacteria are both Gram-negative chemolithotrophs."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "How much time does nitrifying bacteria require to grow at an incubation of 250 to 300 C?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 day",
            "b) 2-3 days",
            "c) 15 days",
            "d) 1 to 4 months"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The process of removal of the amino group from amino acids is known as deamination. Alanine in presence of alanine deaminase gives pyruvic acid and ammonia as its deamination reaction products."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "Which among the following is not an ammonia-oxidizing bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nitrosomonas europaea",
            "b) Nitrosovibrio tenuis",
            "c) Nitrospina gracilis",
            "d) Nitrosococcus oceanus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For the growth of nitrifying bacteria a relatively large inoculum is used, and incubation is in the dark at 250 to 300 C for a period of 1 to 4 months."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Agrobacterium is involved in which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ammonification",
            "b) Nitrification",
            "c) Reduction of nitrate to ammonia",
            "d) Denitrification"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Nitrosococcus nitrosus is a type of ammonia-oxidizing bacteria. They usually have an extensive membrane system within their cytoplasm and frequently form cysts and zooglea."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "Which of the following conditions decreases the level of denitrification?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abundance of organic matter",
            "b) Acidic pH",
            "c) Elevated temperatures",
            "d) Availability of oxygen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Nitrospina gracilis is a nitrite-oxidizing bacteria. They are involved in the oxidation of nitrite to nitrate."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "Which of the following are not the features of component II of nitrogenase enzyme complex?",
        "Options": [
            "a) component II is nitrogenase reductase",
            "b) component II is known as the MoFe protein",
            "c) contains sulfur",
            "d) not active without component I"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The transformation of nitrates to gaseous nitrogen is known as denitrification. Species of several bacteria like Agrobacterium, Bacillus, Pseudomonas etc are involved in this process."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "Which of the following is symbiotic nitrogen fixing bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhizobium trifolii",
            "b) Clostridium pasteurianum",
            "c) Azotobacter sp.",
            "d) Escherichia coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The process of denitrification is enhanced in soils by the presence of abundance of organic matter, by elevated temperatures, by neutral or alkaline pH. The availability of oxygen has a dual effect on denitrification."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "Which among the following are the most important agents for carbon dioxide fixation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bacteria",
            "b) fungi",
            "c) algae",
            "d) protozoa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Green plants and algae are the most important agents of carbon dioxide fixation."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "Fresh air contains approximately ______ percent carbon dioxide by volume.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.01",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 0.03"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Fresh air contains approximately 0.03 percent carbon dioxide by volume. The end product, carbon dioxide, from the degradation of organic carbon compounds are released into the air and soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "Cellulose is degraded to cellobiose by the enzyme __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) cellulase",
            "b) beta-glucosidase",
            "c) hexokinase",
            "d) cellulose dehydrogenase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most abundant organic material in plants is cellulose. The initial enzymatic at-tack is by cellulase which splits this long-chain polymer of glucose to cellobiose which contains two glucose units."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "In carbon cycle flow of energy is _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) bidirectional",
            "b) linear",
            "c) cyclic",
            "d) irreversible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Under most natural systems of vegetation, e.g., forests, the amount of organic material in the soil remains approximately the same from year to year. This results from a balance established between the annual litterfall and death of the plants and the capacity of microorganisms to degrade these tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "Cysteine breaks down in presence of cysteine desulfurase  to give _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxaloacetic acid",
            "b) sulphuric acid",
            "c) pyruvic acid",
            "d) glyoxalate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In carbon cycle flow of energy is linear in unidirectional way through carbon dioxide in the atmosphere to organic forms of carbon in soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "Which of the following processes is performed by Thiobacillus thiooxidans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) converting sulphur to sulphates",
            "b) converting sulphur to sulphides",
            "c) converting sulphur to sulphites",
            "d) converting organic sulphur to inorganic sulphur"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cellobiose is split into glucose by the enzyme beta-glucosidase; glucose is metabolized directly by microorganisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "Sulphates are reduced to hydrogen sulphide by _____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Desulfotomaculum sp.",
            "b) Thiobacillus thiooxidans",
            "c) Photosynthetic sulfur bacteria",
            "d) Rhodospirillum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Degradation of proteins liberates amino acids, some of which contain sulphur released by the enzymatic activity of many heterotrophic bacteria. Cysteine breaks down in presence of cysteine desulfurase to give pyruvic acid, hydrogen sulphide and ammonia."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "The reduction of sulphates and sulphites to hydrogen sulphide is done by which group of bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) aerobic sulfate-reducing bacteria",
            "b) photosynthetic sulphur bacteria",
            "c) anaerobic sulphate-reducing bacteria",
            "d) heterotrophic bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Thiobacillus thiooxidans, an autotroph, is capable of oxidizing elemental sulphur to sulphates."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "Which among the following develop in the upper portion of the Winogradsky column?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sulfate-reducing bacteria",
            "b) Green-sulfur bacteria",
            "c) Purple-sulfur bacteria",
            "d) Thiobacilli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sulphates are reduced to hydrogen sulphide by soil microorganisms like Desulfotomaculum species. Like calcium sulphate gives us hydrogen sulphide and calcium hydroxide."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "Purple and green sulfur bacteria use ___________________ as the electron donor to reduce carbon dioxide.",
        "Options": [
            "a) S2-",
            "b) SO42-",
            "c) H2S",
            "d) Organic acids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A laboratory technique which facilitates isolation of various sulfur-metabolilizing bacteria is the Winogradsky column. The column contains mud, CaSO4, plant tissue, and water. It is exposed to daylight and incubated at room temperature."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Which among the following is a non-sulfur purple bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rhodomicrobium",
            "b) Thiobacillus",
            "c) Chromatium",
            "d) Chlorobium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Organic acids serve as the electron donors for the reduction of sulfates to sulfites to hydrogen sulfide by anaerobic sulfate-reducing bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "The moisture contained in clouds and precipitated as snow,hail,rain etc constitutes _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atmospheric water",
            "b) Surface water",
            "c) Groundwater",
            "d) Subterranean water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The moisture contained in clouds and precipitated as snow, sleet, hail and rain constitutes atmospheric water. The air is washed by atmospheric water."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "The surface waters are susceptible to contamination with microorganisms from _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) the air",
            "b) the surface runoff",
            "c) precipitation",
            "d) atmospheric water and the surface runoff"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The surface waters are susceptible to contamination with microorganisms from atmospheric water (precipitation), the surface runoff from soil and any wastes deliberately dumped into them."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "Which of the following is subterranean water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atmospheric water",
            "b) Surface water",
            "c) Groundwater",
            "d) Rainwater"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Groundwater is subterranean water that occurs where all pores in the soil or rock-containing materials are saturated."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "Wells less than  ___________  deep are considered to be shallow.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 ft",
            "b) 100 ft",
            "c) 50 ft",
            "d) 1000 ft"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wells are made by sinking a shaft into the ground to penetrate the groundwater level. Wells less than 100 ft deep are considered to be shallow."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Thermus aquaticus, a common bacterial inhabitant generally prevails in temperatures of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 00 C",
            "b) 30-400C",
            "c) 70-720C",
            "d) 80-850C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thermus aquaticus, a common bacterial inhabitant of hot springs has an optimum growth temperature of 70 to 720C."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Primary producers are found growing in which of the following layers of water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) upper layer",
            "b) middle layer",
            "c) intermediate layer",
            "d) bottom layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Hydrostatic pressure increases the boiling point of water. It affects chemical equilibrium which in turn results in lowering of pH and a change in the solubility of nutrients such as bicarbonate."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "The microorganisms from lakes and rivers can grow at a salt concentration of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5 to 4 percent",
            "b) 5 percent",
            "c) below 1 percent",
            "d) above 1 percent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In most aquatic habitats the primary producers i.e. algae have their growth restricted to the upper layers of waters through which light can penetrate."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "Which of the following compounds are required for the growth of saprophytic bacteria and fungi?",
        "Options": [
            "a) organic compounds",
            "b) nitrates",
            "c) phosphates",
            "d) mercury"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The degree of salinity in natural waters ranges from near zero in freshwaters to saturation in salt lakes."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Protozoa and other minute animal life are known as ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) plankton",
            "b) phytoplankton",
            "c) zooplankton",
            "d) mycoplankton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The aggregation of floating and drifting microbial life in the surface region of the aquatic ecosystem is called plankton. Protozoa and other minute animal life are known as zooplankton."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "Microbial inhabitants of the bottom region of a body of water are referred to as ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) phytoplankton",
            "b) benthic organisms",
            "c) zooplankton",
            "d) mycoplankton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Microbial inhabitants of the bottom region of a body of water are referred to as the benthic organisms. The richest region of an aquatic system in terms of numbers and kinds of organisms is the benthic region."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Which of the following places shows the presence of Geothermal vents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coasts of California",
            "b) Coasts of Peru",
            "c) Galapagos islands",
            "d) Pacific ocean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Most phytoplanktonic organisms are motile, possess some structural features or contain oil droplets which give them buoyancy."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "Large spiraling surface currents in the ocean that tend to aggregate and retain nutrients are known as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) benthic region",
            "b) upwelling",
            "c) geothermal vents",
            "d) gyres"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: It has been calculated that geothermal vents such as the one near the Galapagos Islands account for most of the nutrients dissolved in the oceans of the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "Which of the following techniques is used for identification and enumeration of algae, bacteria, protozoa?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Microscopic examination",
            "b) Submerged-slide technique",
            "c) Membrane-filter technique",
            "d) Enrichment-culture technique"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gyres are large spiraling surface currents in the ocean that tend to aggregate and retain nutrients, wastes, and microorganisms. Gyres have only been appreciated in recent years, through the use of satellite imagery."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "Which of the following techniques can be used to separate different-size fractions of the aquatic microbial community?",
        "Options": [
            "a) submerged-slide technique",
            "b) fluorescent antibody technique",
            "c) membrane-filter technique",
            "d) by measuring biochemical activity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Many aquatic microorganisms will not grow on the usual laboratory media such as nutrient agar or nutrient broth and consequently, cannot be isolated."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "Which of the following zones have considerable rooted vegetation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) littoral zone",
            "b) limnetic zone",
            "c) profundal zone",
            "d) benthic zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is usually a fairly large littoral zone along the shore which has considerable rooted vegetation and includes regions where light penetrates to the bottom."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "Which of the following layer is composed of soft mud or ooze?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Photic zone",
            "b) Limnetic zone",
            "c) Benthic zone",
            "d) Profundal zone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The benthic region is composed of soft mud or ooze at the bottom. Profundal region exists at much greater depths of the water body whereas the littoral zone is present along the shore."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "In which of the following seasons does the nutrient concentration falls at a drastically lower level?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Winter",
            "b)  Spring",
            "c) Summer",
            "d) Autumn"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Occurrence of algal blooms during the spring and autumn results in lowering the nutrient concentration during summers."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "The coastal adjunct of the marine ecosystem is __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) stream",
            "b) estuary",
            "c) river",
            "d) lake"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The drastic environmental changes in streams and rivers created by rapidly expanding urbanization on the one hand and changes in farming practices on the other make it impossible to generalize upon typical or characteristic microbial flora."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "The Chesapeake Bay, one of the world’s major estuarine system serves as the receiving basin for how many rivers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An estuary is the coastal adjunct of the marine ecosystem. It is a semi-enclosed coastal body of water which has a free connection with the open sea."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "In regions of the estuary that are nutritionally poor, it is more likely to find which of the following organisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) coliforms",
            "b) appendaged bacteria",
            "c) viruses",
            "d) fecal streptococci"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Chesapeake Bay, one of the world’s major estuarine system serves as the receiving basin for nine major rivers, draining much of southern New York State, Pennsylvania, Maryland and Virginia."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "The characteristic color of the Red Sea is associated with heavy blooms of __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) diatoms",
            "b) cyanobacteria",
            "c) dinoflagellates",
            "d) chlamydomonads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In regions of the estuary that are nutritionally poor, one is likely to find the budding and/or the appendaged bacteria, in addition to pseudomonads."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "Which of the following genus of bacteria is not found in fresh waters?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pseudomonas",
            "b) Flavobacterium",
            "c) Aeromonas",
            "d) Vibrio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The characteristic color of the Red Sea is associated with heavy blooms of a cyanobacterium, Oscillatoria erythraea, which contains the pigments phycoerythrin and phycocyanin."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "The primary producers in the marine system are ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) protozoa",
            "b) cyanobacteria",
            "c) fungi",
            "d) cyanobacteria and eukaryotic algae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The primary producers in the marine system are cyanobacteria and eukaryotic algae which predominate in the phytoplankton."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "The biological activity of an aquatic ecosystem is dependent upon which of the following factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) number of primary producers",
            "b) amount of chemical energy produced",
            "c) rate of primary production",
            "d) number of deaths of organisms"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The primary producers through photosynthesis, are capable of transforming radiant energy into chemical energy (organic compounds)."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "n which of the following water bodies, the role of photosynthetic organisms is considerably reduced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lakes",
            "b) Ponds",
            "c) Estuaries",
            "d) Streams"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The biological activity of an aquatic ecosystem is dependent upon the rate of primary production performed by the photosynthetic organisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "Which of the following aquatic organisms contribute in a small amount to the shallow estuary food web?",
        "Options": [
            "a) benthic algae",
            "b) bacteria",
            "c) protozoa",
            "d) nematodes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In shallow estuaries the role of photosynthetic organisms as primary producers is considerably reduced. Plant growth from the shoreline contributes leaves, stems, and roots of vegetation and other organic detritus."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "Which among the following are referred to as the “pasture of the sea”?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fishes",
            "b) algae",
            "c) nematodes",
            "d) phytoplankton"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Phytoplankton and benthic algae make a small contribution to the food supply in the food web of shallow estuaries."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "What amount of dry organic matter is produced by deep ocean areas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1g",
            "b) 10g",
            "c) 0.5g",
            "d) 100g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plankton, particularly phytoplankton, has been referred to as the “pasture of the sea”. Fish, whales, and squids feed directly on plankton or on larger plankton-feeding animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "Which among the following factors are limiting the growth of phytoplankton organisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbon dioxide",
            "b) radiant energy",
            "c) water",
            "d) radiant energy,nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The term fertility of oceans is used to express the capacity for the production of organic matter by the organisms present in these waters."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "Which among the following oceans is the most richest in life?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Antarctic Ocean",
            "b) Atlantic Ocean",
            "c) Pacific Ocean",
            "d) Indian Ocean"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The terrestrial environment produces 1 to 10 g of dry organic matter per square meter per day compared to 0.5 g for the deep ocean areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "In which of the following water bodies, fertility is high?",
        "Options": [
            "a) open sea",
            "b) coastal regions",
            "c) lakes",
            "d) rivers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors generally limiting growth are radiant energy, nitrogen and phosphorus, and the trace elements. The nitrogen, phosphorus and trace elements are made available through the mineralization reactions of microorganisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "Which of the following product is not obtained from dissimilation of organic matter under aerobic conditions?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ammonium",
            "b) sulphate",
            "c) methane",
            "d) phosphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Antarctic Ocean is described as being richer in life than any other major oceanic area. The richness of nutrients in this region is attributable to the mixing of the waters of the Atlantic, Pacific, and Indian Oceans."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Which of the following organism have siliceous skeletons?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Foraminifera",
            "b) Coccolithophores",
            "c) Radiolaria",
            "d) Cyanobacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Although coastal and estuarine regions provide a less stable physical environment, their fertility exceeds that of the open sea because of the large amounts of nutrients available."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "Which of the following forms of water is the most contaminated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Underground water",
            "b) Rainwater",
            "c) Surface water",
            "d) Water stored in ice caps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Surface water should not be used for drinking purposes unless it is subjected to purification since there is constant danger of contamination and consequent transmission of disease."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "Alum is used for which of the following purification process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sedimentation",
            "b) Filtration",
            "c) Disinfection",
            "d) Ozonation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sedimentation is enhanced by addition of alum (aluminum sulphate) at the treatment plant, which produces a sticky flocculent precipitate."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "The coliform group of bacteria includes all the __________________ bacilli.",
        "Options": [
            "a) aerobic",
            "b) anaerobic",
            "c) aerobic, non-sporulating",
            "d) aerobic, gram-negative, non-sporulating"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sanitary surveys reveal whether water is being produced under conditions in which potable water would ordinarily be produced. However, potability can be determined only by chemical and bacteriological laboratory tests."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "Which of the following organism does not belong to coliform group of bacteria?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Salmonella",
            "b) Serratia",
            "c) Enterobacter",
            "d) Proteus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The coliform group of bacteria includes all the aerobic and facultatively anaerobic, gram-negative, non-sporulating bacilli that produce acid and gas from the fermentation of lactose."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "Which of the following acts as a carbon source for Enterobacter aerogenes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peptone",
            "b) Sodium citrate",
            "c) Yeast extract",
            "d) Tryptone"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Coliform group of bacteria consists of E.coli and Enterobacter aerogenes. All others belong to the enteric group."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "What will be the plate count of good quality water?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 per ml",
            "b) 50 per ml",
            "c) 100 per ml",
            "d) 1000 per ml"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coliforms, fecal streptococci and Clostridium perfringens are normal inhabitants of the large intestine of humans and other animals and are consequently present in feces."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "Among the following which microorganism acts as a representative of fecal streptococci group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptococcus faecalis",
            "b) Streptococcus bovis",
            "c) Streptococcus equinus",
            "d) Streptococcus faecium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Enterobacter aerogenes will grow in a chemically defined medium in which sodium citrate is the only carbon compound as it is capable of utilizing it."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "Thiobacillus can produce an acidity in the range of pH __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the standard plate count method, water of good quality is expected to give a low count, less than 100 per ml."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "In which of the following organism does iron secreted to form stalks or ribbons attached to the cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sphaerotilus",
            "b) Gallionella",
            "c) Thiobacillus",
            "d) Streptococcus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Streptococcus faecalis is representative of the fecal streptococci group and are abundantly present in the large intestine of humans. Their occurrence in water is indicative of fecal pollution. "
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "Which of the following sewerage systems carry domestic and industrial wastewater?",
        "Options": [
            "a) sanitary sewers",
            "b) storm sewers",
            "c) combined sewers",
            "d) storm and combined sewers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sanitary sewers carry domestic and industrial wastewater for its ultimate treatment and disposal."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a strict anaerobe?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enterobacter",
            "b) Alcaligenes",
            "c) Pseudomonas",
            "d) Methanosarcina"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The magnitude of the BOD is related to the amount of organic material in the wastewater-i.e., the more oxidizable organic material, the higher the BOD."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "In which of the following treatment involve oxidation of organic constituents of the wastewater?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary treatment",
            "b) Secondary treatment",
            "c) Advanced treatment",
            "d) Final treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Methane producers are strict anaerobes e.g., Methanobacterium, Methanosarcina, Methanococcus. They produce methane and carbon dioxide as end products."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "The upper region of the trickling filter is favorable for the growth of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) fungi",
            "b) protozoa",
            "c) algae",
            "d) bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Secondary or biological treatment is done to adsorb and ultimately oxidize organic constituents of the wastewater, i.e, to reduce the BOD."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "Activated sludge usually employs an aeration period of ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 hour",
            "b) 24 hours",
            "c) 10-15 hours",
            "d) 4-8 hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The upper region of the trickling filter is favorable for the growth of algae, and at times their growth may become so extensive that it impairs the operation of the filter."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "Trickling filter is used in which of the following wastewater treatment processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary treatment",
            "b) Secondary treatment",
            "c) Advanced treatment",
            "d) Final treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The activated sludge process usually employs an aeration period of 4 to 8 hours, after which the mixture is piped to a sedimentation tank."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "Belt filter presses are used in which of the following process?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Thickening",
            "b) Stabilization",
            "c) Dewatering",
            "d) Disposal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Oxidation ponds also called lagoons are shallow ponds which are 2 to 4 ft in depth designed to allow algal growth on the wastewater effluent."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "Which of the following gases are produced in large amounts during sludge digestion?",
        "Options": [
            "a) methane",
            "b) carbon-dioxide",
            "c) hydrogen",
            "d) nitrogen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The trickling filter is used in secondary treatment in which a stationary microbial culture is fed by a continuous supply of nutrients. It is used for filtration processes."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "Which of the following organism occurs on the skin of fresh poultry?",
        "Options": [
            "a) pseudomonads",
            "b) staphylococci",
            "c) micrococci",
            "d) enterococci"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pseudomonads constitute the major contaminants on the skin of freshly dressed poultry."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "What is the pH of the bananas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.3",
            "b) 5.0",
            "c) 7.0",
            "d) 12.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pH of fruits is relatively acid ranging from 2.3 for lemons to 5.0 for bananas. This restricts bacterial growth but does not retard fungal growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "At what temperature pasteurization of milk takes place?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 650 C",
            "b) 370 C",
            "c) 62.80 C",
            "d) 450 C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Raw milk of good sanitary quality will develop a clean, sour flavour. This change is brought about mainly by Streptococcus lactis and S.cremoris."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "Which among the following is a gas producer organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptococcus lactis",
            "b) Lactobacillus fermentum",
            "c) Micrococcus luteus",
            "d) Clostridium butyricum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The holding method of pasteurization exposes milk to a temperature of 62.80 C for 30 mins."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Which among the following group of microorganisms are found in the ducts of cow’s mammary glands?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coliforms",
            "b) Lactobacilli",
            "c) Micrococci",
            "d) Microbacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Clostridium butyricum causes fermentation of lactose with accumulation of gas. The gas may be a mixture of carbon dioxide and hydrogen or only carbon dioxide in case of yeast fermentation."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "The coloration of the milk is caused by which of the following organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pseudomonas sp.",
            "b) Bacillus sp.",
            "c) Penicillium sp.",
            "d) Streptococcus sp."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Micrococci such as Micrococcus luteus, Micrococcus varians are found in the ducts of cow’s mammary glands and dairy utensils. They are acid producers and are weakly proteolytic."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "In which of the following biochemical types of microorganisms a slime layer or capsule is formed on the cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acid producers",
            "b) Gas producers",
            "c) Ropy or stringy fermentation",
            "d) Proteolytic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pseudomonas sp. may produce coloration of milk. End products of proteolysis may impart abnormal flavor or odor to the milk."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "Which of the following type of spoilage occurs in fresh meat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Souring",
            "b) Greening",
            "c) Putrefaction",
            "d) Moldy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In Ropy or stringy fermentation, organisms synthesize a viscous polysaccharide material that forms a slime layer or capsule on the cells. They include Alcaligenes viscolactis, Enterobacter aerogenes, etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "Spoilage of bread is caused by which of the following microorganism(s)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saccharomyces",
            "b) Rhizopus",
            "c) Leuconostoc",
            "d) Pseudomonas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Pathogen from infected cow are transmitted through milk to humans or cow and causes tuberculosis brucellosis, mastitis."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "The thermophilic anaerobe spoilage of low and medium acid canned products are caused by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacilllus stearothemophilus",
            "b) Clostridium thermosaccharolyticum",
            "c) Bacillus thermoacidurans",
            "d) Clostridium sporogenes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Fresh meat is spoiled by putrefaction and is caused by Alcaligenes, Clostridium, Proteus vulgaris etc. In putrefaction, the protein foods are degraded by proteolytic microorganisms to give amino acids, amines, ammonia and hydrogen sulphide."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "The temperatures used for canning foods ranges from ____________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-20 degree C",
            "b) 20-60 degree C",
            "c) 60-100 degree C",
            "d) 100-121 degree C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The temperatures used for canning foods ranging from 100 degrees C for high-acid foods to 121 degrees C for low-acid foods."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "In the high-temperature short-time (HTST) method of pasteurization, milk is exposed to a temperature of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 132 degree F",
            "b) 145 degree F",
            "c) 161 degree F",
            "d) 120 degree F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The HTST process employs equipment capable of exposing milk to a temperature of 161 degrees F (71.7 degrees C) for 15 secs."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism survive at -9 to -17 degree C?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Salmonella",
            "b) Staphylococci",
            "c) Bacilli",
            "d) Clostridium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sterilization exposes milk to ultrahigh temperatures for very short periods of time, for example, 300 degrees F (148.9 degrees C) for 1 to 2 seconds."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism is eliminated in canned foods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mycobacterium tuberculosis",
            "b) Coxiella burnetii",
            "c) Clostridium botulinum",
            "d) Lactobacillus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Species of Salmonella survive for longer periods of time at -9 to -17 degree C which is unlike the situation in which microbial count of most frozen foods decreases during storage."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "Phosphatase enzyme present in milk is destroyed in which of the following processes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sterilization",
            "b) Canning",
            "c) Dehydration",
            "d) Pasteurization"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most important organism to be eliminated in canned foods is the spore forming anaerobe Clostridium botulinum, which is capable of producing a very potent lethal toxin."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "Which chemical is used to inhibit mold growth in bread?",
        "Options": [
            "a) benzoic acid",
            "b) nitrates",
            "c) sorbic acid",
            "d) lactic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Phosphatase is an enzyme present in raw milk and in many tissues which are destroyed by adequate pasteurization."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "Acetic acid and lactic acid are used for __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) curing meats",
            "b) preservation of color",
            "c) preservation of pickles",
            "d) inhibiting mold growth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Jellies and jams are rarely affected by bacterial action because of high sugar content. However it is uncommon to find mold growth on the surface of jelly which has been exposed to air."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is used for treatment of water used for the depuration of shellfish?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chemicals",
            "b) Radiation",
            "c) Low temperature",
            "d) Osmotic pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Sorbic acid and propionic acid are used to inhibit mold growth in bread. They are organic in nature."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "Which of the following microbe is used in the production of blue cheese?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptococcus thermophilus",
            "b) Lactobacillus bulgaricus",
            "c) Penicillium roqueforti",
            "d) Rhizopus stolonifer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For the production of blue cheese or Roquefort cheese, it is necessary to inoculate the curd with the microorganism, Penicillium roqueforti which brings about the necessary changes."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "Bacterial cell grown on hydrocarbon wastes from the petroleum industry are a source of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) carbohydrates",
            "b) proteins",
            "c) vitamins",
            "d) fats"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Most commercial sweet, sour, mixed pickles are made from fermented salt-stock pickles. The other major type of pickled cucumber is the fermented dill pickle."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "Yeast-cell crops harvested from the vats are used to produce which of the following compounds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) alcoholic beverages",
            "b) enzymes",
            "c) antibiotics",
            "d) organic acids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The microorganisms can be cultivated on industrial wastes or by-products as nutrients and yield a large cell crop that is rich in protein. Bacterial cell grown on hydrocarbon wastes from the petroleum industry are a source of protein in France, Japan, Taiwan, and India."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "How many tons of protein can be produced by algae grown in pond in a year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Yeast-cell crops harvested from the vats used to produce alcoholic beverages have been used as a food supplement for generations."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "What is the range of protein content in yeast cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 69%",
            "b) 12-15%",
            "c) 20-40%",
            "d) 40-50%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Algae grown in ponds can produce 20 tons (dry weight) of protein per acre per year."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism have high vitamin content?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bacteria",
            "b) yeast",
            "c) algae",
            "d) protozoa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The protein content of microbial cells is very high. Yeast cells have a protein content in a 40 to 50 percent range."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "The principal microorganism for yogurt is ______________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptococcus thermophilus",
            "b) Leuconostoc citrovorum",
            "c) Lactobacillus acidophilus",
            "d) Streptococcus lactis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Some microorganisms, particularly yeasts, have a high vitamin content. The growth medium for yeast cells consists of hydrocarbons supplemented with mineral salts."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "Which of the following products have higher acidity and lacks aroma?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cultured buttermilk",
            "b) Cultured sour cream",
            "c) Bulgarian milk",
            "d) Acidophilus milk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Streptococcus thermophilus and Lactobacillus bulgaricus are among the principal microorganisms responsible for producing yogurt by fermentation."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "Shredded cabbage is the starting product for which of the following fermented food?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sauerkraut",
            "b) Pickles",
            "c) Green olives",
            "d) Sausage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: For production of Bulgarian milk by Lactobacillus bulgaricus, incubation of inoculated milk at 37 degree C is carried out and the product differs from commercial buttermilk in having higher acidity and lacking aroma."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a desired characteristic of the organism to be used for industrial application?",
        "Options": [
            "a) should produce less amount of product",
            "b) should be readily available",
            "c) should grow rapidly",
            "d) should be nonpathogenic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The organism to be used must be able to produce appreciable amount of the product. It should be readily available and should grow rapidly and vigorously. It should be nonpathogenic."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "Industrial fermentation are performed in large tanks of capacity ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 gal",
            "b) 1000 gal",
            "c) 50,000 gal",
            "d) 10,000 gal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Industrial fermentation are performed in large tanks; capacities of 50,000 gal are not unusual."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "Solvents and enzymes are found in which of the following categories of microbial products?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pharmaceutical chemicals",
            "b) Commercially valuable chemicals",
            "c) Food supplements",
            "d) Alcoholic beverages"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Solvents, enzymes, and intermediate compounds for the synthesis of other substances are representative of the kinds of substances produced commercially by microorganisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzymes cut the DNA molecule at a particular nucleotide sequence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) restriction endonuclease",
            "b) exonuclease",
            "c) ligase",
            "d) polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Restriction endonuclease cut double-stranded DNA molecules at particular nucleotide sequences and thus produce a well-defined DNA fragment for a given enzyme and a given DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "Which of the following product is used for the treatment of blood clots?",
        "Options": [
            "a) insulin",
            "b) interferon",
            "c) urokinase",
            "d) somatostatin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The endonuclease Eco R1 cuts the plasmid DNA and the donor DNA in a manner such that the ends of each are identical and self-complementary."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "VP3 protein is isolated from which of the following viruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) TMV",
            "b) HIV",
            "c) HRV",
            "d) FMDV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pharmaceutical industry has already produced several products for human therapy by the help of genetic engineering such as urokinase that is used for the treatment of blood clots; human insulin and interferons."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism produces dextran?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacillus polymyxa",
            "b) Bacillus thuringiensis",
            "c) Leuconostoc mesenteroides",
            "d) Streptomyces olivaceus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Leuconostoc mesenteroides is the producer organism for dextran which acts as a stabilizer in food products and as a blood plasma substitute."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "Which of the following carbohydrates are mainly present in whey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) glucose",
            "b) lactose",
            "c) fructose",
            "d) sucrose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Whey represents a satisfactory medium for the growth of certain bacteria since it contains lactose, nitrogenous substances including vitamins, and salts."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "What temperature is necessary for the production of vinegar?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 43 degree C",
            "b) 60 degree C",
            "c) 10-13 degree C",
            "d) 15-34 degree C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Lactobacillus bulgaricus grows rapidly and is homofermentative and thus is capable of converting the lactose to the single end product-lactic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "Which of the following product is used for the treatment of pernicious anemia?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insulin",
            "b) Streptokinase-streptodornase",
            "c) Cobalamin",
            "d) Sorbose"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For vinegar production it is necessary to keep the temperature between 15 and 34 degree C, the optimum for growth and metabolism of the acetobacters."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "Diaminopimelic acid (DAP) is produced by which of the following microorganism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E.coli",
            "b) Enterobacter aerogenes",
            "c) Bacillus subtilis",
            "d) Streptococcus equisimilis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Cobalamin or vitamin B12 is used for the treatment of pernicious anemia and also for food and feed supplements."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "Which of the following raw materials are important for the production of glutamic acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) glycerol",
            "b) corn-steep liquor",
            "c) tryptone",
            "d) biotin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The advantage of microbial fermentation processes is that the biologically active forms of the amino acids i.e. L optical isomers are produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "Insulin was isolated from which of the following organs of animals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) small intestine",
            "b) tongue",
            "c) pancreas",
            "d) stomach"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Production of lysine involves two stages among which the first stage is the formation of diaminopimelic acid (DAP) by E.coli."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "Which of the following yeast is used for the production of riboflavin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saccharomyces cerevisiae",
            "b) Eremothecium ashbyi",
            "c) Saccharomyces rouxii",
            "d) Candida utilis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For glutamic acid the medium generally consists of carbohydrate, peptone, inorganic salts, and biotin; the concentration of biotin has a significant influence on the yield of glutamic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "Which of the following product utilizes whey as its raw material?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lactic acid",
            "b) acetic acid",
            "c) glutamic acid",
            "d) lysine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Commercial insulin for the therapy of diabetes was isolated from animal pancreatic tissue."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "Which among the following are not used as raw materials for alcohol production?",
        "Options": [
            "a) corn",
            "b) molasses",
            "c) whey",
            "d) grapes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Corn, molasses, sugar beets, potatoes, and grapes are some of the common raw materials employed throughout the world for alcohol fermentation."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "What is the pH required for the production of baker’s yeast?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 2",
            "b) 4 to 5",
            "c) 7 to 8",
            "d) 10 to 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: It is imperative that the culture be one that grows vigorously and has a high tolerance for alcohol as well as a capacity for producing a large yield of alcohol."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "The leavening or rising of dough is due to which of the following gases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) oxygen",
            "b) carbon dioxide",
            "c) hydrogen",
            "d) sulphur dioxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the manufacture of baker’s yeast, the medium is adjusted to an acid pH of 4 to 5, which helps retard bacterial growth."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "Which of the following instrument is used for the recovery of yeast cells?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fermenter",
            "b) centrifuge",
            "c) filter press",
            "d) mash storage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The carbon dioxide produced during the fermentation by baker’s yeast is responsible for the leavening or rising of the dough."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "Which of the following product is used as a food condiment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Baker’s yeast",
            "b) Ethanol",
            "c) Wine",
            "d) Soy sauce"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The cells are finally recovered on a filter press, small amounts of vegetable oil are added as a plasticizer, and then this mass of cells is molded into blocks."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "Which of the following yeast can be used to produce microbial protein?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saccharomyces cerevisiae",
            "b) Candida milleri",
            "c) Eremothecium ashbyi",
            "d) Candida utilis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Soy Sauce is produced by the yeast Saccharomyces rouxii and is used as a food condiment."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "Gluconic acid is produced by which of the following molds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aspergillus niger",
            "b) Rhizopus nigricans",
            "c) Aspergillus terreus",
            "d) Rhizopus oryzae"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aspergillus niger is the producer organism for gluconic acid which is used as a pharmaceutical product, textiles, leather, or in photography."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "Fermentation of rice is carried out by which of the following microorganisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bacteria",
            "b) yeasts",
            "c) molds",
            "d) protozoa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Molds are used for the fermentation of rice to produce a variety of oriental foods and food additives."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "Which of the following techniques is used to improve penicillin production?",
        "Options": [
            "a) fed-batch fermentation",
            "b) submerged-culture technique",
            "c) continuous fermentation",
            "d) batch fermentation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fleming isolated the mold Penicillium notatum which yielded only a few units of penicillin per milliliter. So isloation of a better penicillin-producing mold species, Penicillium chrysogenum helped in increasing the yield."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "Which of the following product acts as a substrate for the production of citric acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) molasses",
            "b) corn-steep liquor",
            "c) barn",
            "d) oyabeen meal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Penicillin production can be improved by the development of the submerged culture technique i.e., cultivation of the mold in large volumes of liquid medium through which sterile air is forced."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzymes is used to hydrolyze starch to dextrin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) invertase",
            "b) pectinase",
            "c) amylase",
            "d) protease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Many sugars may serve as the substrate for the production of citric acid, however, molasses is generally used."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzyme is used in the process of bating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) invertase",
            "b) pectinase",
            "c) amylase",
            "d) protease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Amylases hydrolyze starch to dextrin and sugars and are used in preparing adhesives, clarifying fruit juices, manufacturing pharmaceuticals etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "Invertase causes hydrolysis of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) starch",
            "b) sucrose",
            "c) proteins",
            "d) pectins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Proteases are used for bating i.e. treatment of hides to provide a finer texture and grain in leather processing."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "Rhizopus nigricans produces which of the following products?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Citric acid",
            "b) Fumaric acid",
            "c) Gibberellic acid",
            "d) Lactic acid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A variety of substances including paper, wood chips, ceramic, glass beads, and ion-exchange resins have been used to immobilize enzymes."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "Bacterial chromosome has the capacity to code for ____________ different proteins.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 900",
            "b) 300",
            "c) 1500",
            "d) 3500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: It has been estimated that bacterial chromosomes have the capacity to code for approximately 3500 different proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "Which is the functional unit of inheritance?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA",
            "b) Chromosome",
            "c) Gene",
            "d) RNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A gene is a functional unit of inheritance; it specifies the formation of a particular polypeptide as well as various types of RNA. The chromosome is divided into genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "Populations of cells descending from a single cell are known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mutants",
            "b) clones",
            "c) wild-type cells",
            "d) parent cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Populations of cells descending from a single cell are known as clones but a cell or an organism which shows the effects of a mutation is called a mutant."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "The replacement of a purine by a pyrimidine or vice versa is known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tranversion",
            "b) transition",
            "c) base-pair substitution",
            "d) missense mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transversion is a type of point mutation is the replacement of a purine by a pyrimi-dine or vice versa."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "Sickle cell anemia is which type of mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) nonsense mutation",
            "b) missense mutation",
            "c) deletion mutation",
            "d) insertion mutation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A good example of a missense mutation in humans is the disease sickle cell anemia. A single base substitution in the codon for the sixth amino acid of normal hemoglobin A  changes the sixth amino acid from glutamic acid to valine, thus forming the characteristic hemoglobin S of sickle cell anemia."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "Which of the following mutations result in frameshift mutation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) missense mutation",
            "b) transition",
            "c) transversion",
            "d) insertion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In neutral mutation the altered gene triplet produces a mRNA codon that specifies the same amino acid because the codon resulting from mutation is a synonym for the original codon."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Which of the following mutagen causes a break in the phosphodiester backbone of the nucleic acid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UV light",
            "b) X-rays",
            "c) Nitrous acid",
            "d) base analogs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Insertion and deletion mutations result in a shift of the reading frame caused by the addition or loss of one or more nucleotides."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "Acridine orange is which type of mutagen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) base analog",
            "b) chemical compounds",
            "c) intercalating agents",
            "d) transposons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When x-rays interact with DNA, the result is usually a break in the phosphodiester backbone of the nucleic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "Photoreactivation can cause repair of DNA damaged by which of the following mutagens?",
        "Options": [
            "a) UV rays",
            "b) X-rays",
            "c) Nitrous acid",
            "d) Base analogs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Although similar in structure, base analogs do not have the same hydrogen-bonding properties as the normal bases. They can therefore introduce errors in a replication which results in mutation."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzyme is used to join the DNA fragments together?",
        "Options": [
            "a) polymerases",
            "b) exonuclease",
            "c) endonuclease",
            "d) ligase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Acridine orange is an intercalating agent that can intercalate between the base pairs in the central stack of the DNA helix and distort the structures and cause subsequent replication errors."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "What is the mutation rate for E.coli per bacterium per cell division?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.8 x 10-6",
            "b) 5.8 x 10-9",
            "c) 5.8 x 10-8",
            "d) 5.8 x 10-7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Photoreactivation mechanism is used for repairing damage caused by UV radiation.A special enzyme designated PRE, induced by visible light, splits or unlinks the dimers formed because of exposure to UV light and restores the DNA to its original state."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "The transfer of genes from one cell to another by a bacteriophage is known as __________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Recombination",
            "b) Conjugation",
            "c) Transduction",
            "d) Transformation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In bacteria, genetic recombination results from three types of gene transfer among which transfer of genes from one cell to another by a bacteriophage is known as transduction."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "Bacterial recombination causes transformation of the recipient cell to _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) donor cell",
            "b) merozygote",
            "c) zygote",
            "d) recipient cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Genetic recombination is the formation of a new genotype by reassortment of genes following an exchange of genetic material between two different chromosomes that have similar genes at corresponding sites. These are called homologous chromosomes and are from different individuals."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "Which of the enzymes are used to cut the recipient DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) endonuclease",
            "b) exonuclease",
            "c) ligases",
            "d) polymerase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The recipient cell becomes a merozygote, a zygote that is a partial diploid and then recombination can take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "The transfer of naked DNA from one cell to another is referred to as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transduction",
            "b) Lysogeny",
            "c) Transformation",
            "d) Conjugation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Transfer of genes between cells that are in physical contact with one another is known as conjugation."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "The cell in which the F factor carries along with it some chromosomal genes are known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) F+ cell",
            "b) F— cell",
            "c) F’ cell",
            "d) F’’’ cell"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Endonuclease acts on the recipient DNA causing nicks and excision of a fragment of DNA to be replaced by donor DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "What are bacteriocins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) proteins",
            "b) toxins",
            "c) plasmid",
            "d) sex factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The transfer of cell-free or ‘naked’ DNA from one cell to another is called transformation."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "The first demonstration of recombination in bacteria was achieved by _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lederberg and Tatum",
            "b) Luria and Delbruck",
            "c) Joshua and Lederberg",
            "d) Luria and Tatum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first demonstration of recombination in bacteria was achieved by Lederberg and Tatum in 1946 in a brilliant and remarkable experiment that opened the door to a whole new world of microbiology."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "Which type of E.coli strain was chosen to prove the experiment of conjugation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) prototrophs",
            "b) auxotrophs",
            "c) polyauxotrophs",
            "d) autotrophs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In a regular cycle of sexual reproduction, there is an opportunity for different mutants of a species to mate with each other and produce new individuals with new combinations of mutations, i.e., to produce recombinants."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "What is the shape of DNA in the male cells of E.coli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) linear",
            "b) supercoiled",
            "c) circular",
            "d) relaxed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When Lederberg and Tatum did their experiments, they used polyauxotrophs (mutants with more than one nutritional requirement) so that back mutation to the wild type does not occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "Which of the following cells of E.coli are referred to as F—",
        "Options": [
            "a) Male cells",
            "b) Female cells",
            "c) Both male and female cells",
            "d) Neither male nor female cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In conjugation it is possible for large segments of the chromosome, and in special cases the entire chromosome to be transferred."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "What is the frequency of formation of recombinants in a F+ X F— cross?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Male cells contain a small circular piece of DNA, which is in the cytoplasm and not part of a chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "The F factor DNA is sufficient to specify how many genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Female cells lack the sex factor or F factor (fertility factor) and are labeled as F—. They are recipient cells. "
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "Which of the following is true for an Hfr X F— cross?",
        "Options": [
            "a) frequency of recombination high, transfer of F factor low",
            "b) frequency of recombination high, transfer of F factor high",
            "c) frequency of recombination low, transfer of F factor high",
            "d) frequency of recombination low, transfer of F factor low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The formation of recombinants in a F+ X F— cross occurs at a low frequency— about one recombinant per 104 to 105 cells.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "Which of the following can be used as a measure to construct a linkage map of the Hfr chromosome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) frequency of recombination",
            "b) time of entry",
            "c) locus of mutation",
            "d) transfer of F factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The F factor DNA is only sufficient to specify about 40 genes that control sex-factor replication and synthesis of sex pili."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "The Hfr chromosome is transferred to the F— cell in a _____________ fashion.",
        "Options": [
            "a) circular",
            "b) coiled",
            "c) dimer",
            "d) linear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In an Hfr X F— cross, the frequency of recombination is high and the transfer of F factor is low as here the F factor of the Hfr is rarely transferred during recombination."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "How much time is required to inject a copy of the whole Hfr E.coli genome?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24 hrs",
            "b) 30 mins",
            "c) 100 mins",
            "d) 48 hrs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Each gene enters the F— cell at a characteristic time, and a linkage map of the Hfr chromosome can be constructed using time of entry as a measure."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "How much time is taken by the new DNA to make whole phage particles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24 hours",
            "b) 60 mins",
            "c) 2 mins",
            "d) 10-20 mins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Within 10 to 20 minutes, depending on the phage, the new DNA combines with the new proteins to make whole phage particles, which are released by the destruction of the cell wall and lysis of the cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "When viral genome can become integrated into the bacterial genome they are known as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) temperate phage",
            "b) prophage",
            "c) bacteriophage",
            "d) episome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When viral genome can become integrated into the bacterial genome they are known as prophages. They carry DNA that can behave as a kind of episome in bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "Which of the following role is performed by a bacteriophage in transduction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) vector",
            "b) donor",
            "c) recipient",
            "d) episome"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bacteriophages inject their nucleic acid usually DNA into the bacterium where it replicates rapidly and also directs the synthesis of new phage proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "What is the frequency of defective phage particles in progeny phage produced?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 10-1",
            "c) 10-5",
            "d) 1000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bacterial transduction is the transfer by a bacteriophage, serving as a vector, of a portion of DNA from one bacterium (donor) to another (a recipient)."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "Fragments transferred by a bacteriophage contains how many genes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 50",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 100"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Any part of the bacterial chromosome may be incorporated into the phage head during phage assembly and is usually not associated with any viral DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "What is the correct order when coliphage P1 is grown in a thr+ leu+ aziR host is used to infect a thr- leu- azi- recipient bacterial cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) thr+ leu+ aziR",
            "b) thr– leu+ aziR",
            "c) thr+ leu– aziR",
            "d) thr– leu– aziR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The frequency of such defective phage particles is about 10-5 to 10-7 of the progeny phage produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "How many percent of thr+ transducing phages also carry leu+?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 5%",
            "c) 3%",
            "d) 15%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Generalized transduction provides a means for mapping bacterial genes, since the fragments transferred by a bacteriophage are often large enough to contain 100s of genes."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "When the phage transduces only those bacterial genes adjacent to the prophage in the bacterial chromosome then it is known as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) generalized transduction",
            "b) specialized transduction",
            "c) restricted transduction",
            "d) conjugation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: When coliphage P1 is grown in a thr+ leu+ aziR host is used to infect a thr– leu– azi– recipient bacterial cell then if Leu+ recombinants are selected, about 50 percent of these are also AzR.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "What are the characteristics of rough pneumococci strain?",
        "Options": [
            "a) noncapsulated and pathogenic",
            "b) noncapsulated and nonpathogenic",
            "c) capsulated and pathogenic",
            "d) capsulated and nonpathogenic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Griffith injected mice with a few rough (noncapsulated and nonpathogenic) pneumococci and a large number of heat-killed smooth cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "In Griffith’s experiment which of the following strains of pneumococci was isolated from dead mice?",
        "Options": [
            "a) live rough cells",
            "b) dead rough cells",
            "c) live smooth cells",
            "d) dead smooth cells"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: When Griffith injected mice with a mixture of a few rough and a large number of heat-killed smooth cells of pneumococci, then the mice subsequently died of pneumonia, and live smooth cells were isolated from their blood."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "Which of the following things was identified as the transforming principle?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DNA",
            "b) RNA",
            "c) Proteins",
            "d) Carbohydrates"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Griffith showed in his experiment that DNA was the transforming principle that transformed the living rough bacteria into pathogenic smooth ones."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "What should be the minimum weight of DNA that is required for a successful transformation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 daltons",
            "b) 100,000 daltons",
            "c) 300,000 daltons",
            "d) 8 million daltons"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Transformation is the process whereby cell-free or naked DNA containing a limited amount of genetic information is transferred from one bacterial cell to another."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "How many DNA molecules are transferred after each transformation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 50",
            "d) infinite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Molecular weights of DNA in the range of 300,000 to 8 million daltons have been shown to result in successful transformation."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "Which of the following enzymes acts on the DNA after its entry into the cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ligases",
            "b) endonucleases",
            "c) deoxyribonucleases",
            "d) exonucleases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Each transformation results from the transfer of a single DNA molecule of double-stranded DNA."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "Which among the following species have not been transformed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacillus",
            "b) Neisseria",
            "c) Rhizobium",
            "d) Aspergillus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: After DNA entry into a cell, one strand is immediately degraded by deoxyribonucleases, while the other strand undergoes base pairing with a homologous portion of the recipient cell chromosome."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "In which phase of growth does the recipient cell take up the donor DNA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) lag phase",
            "b) early logarithmic phage",
            "c) late logarithmic phage",
            "d) stationary phage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bacterial species that have been transformed include, besides Streptococcus pneumonia, those in the genera Bacillus, Haemophilus, Neisseria, and Rhizobium."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "Who among the following was successful in raising 17 germ-free chickens for 40 days?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pasteur",
            "b) Schottelius",
            "c) Cohendy",
            "d) Reyniers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In 1912, Cohendy at the Pasteur Institute raised 17 germ-free chickens for 40 days and concluded that vertebrate life is possible in the absence of microorganisms."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "Within how many days after birth a stable flora develops?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 day",
            "b) 7 days",
            "c) 30 days",
            "d) 7-14 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The initial flora may change considerably in composition during the first few days or weeks after birth until a stable flora becomes established and forms the normal flora."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "How many day-old embryonated eggs were used by Reyniers to rear first germ-free animals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 50",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Animals that are either germ-free or that live in association with one or more known organisms are said to be gnotobiotic."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "Which among the following was the first germ-free animal to be reared?",
        "Options": [
            "a) guinea pigs",
            "b) rats",
            "c) chickens",
            "d) monkey"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first germ-free animals reared by Reyniers were chickens obtained by sterilizing the shells of 20-day-old embryonated eggs."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "Which of the following vitamins are not required by normal animals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vit K",
            "b) Vit B",
            "c) Vit C",
            "d) Vit A"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first germ-free animals reared by Reyniers were chickens obtained by sterilizing the shells of 20-day-old embryonated eggs with an effective germicide and placing them in sterile containers."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "Pseudomembranous colitis is caused by the strains of which of the following microorganism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Streptococcus mutans",
            "b) Clostridium difficile",
            "c) Streptococcus salivarius",
            "d) Clostridium botulinum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The germ-free animals require higher levels of Vitamin K, which normal animal do not require."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "Where does the Streptococcus mutans adhere to the body site?",
        "Options": [
            "a) intestinal tract",
            "b) tongue",
            "c) teeth",
            "d) hairs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Germ-free animals require higher levels of B vitamins than do normal animals, and they require vitamin K, which normal animals do not require."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism produces colicins in the intestine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) E.coli",
            "b) B.subtilis",
            "c) Clostridium botulinum",
            "d) Streptococcus salivarius"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pseudomembranous colitis is a severe disease caused by excessive growth of toxin-producing strains of Clostridium difficile. "
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "Which of the following viruses are termed as ‘orphan’ viruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) retroviruses",
            "b) echoviruses",
            "c) coxsackieviruses",
            "d) adenoviruses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Certain human intestinal viruses were discovered only by noting their cytopathogenic effects in tissue cultures; thus they were termed as ‘orphan’ viruses or echoviruses."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "Which of the following causes the disease acne vulgaris?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Staphylococcus epidermis",
            "b) Diphtheroids",
            "c) P.acnes",
            "d) E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The relatively dry surface of the skin is inhibitory to microbial growth. Moist regions of the skin have higher numbers of normal flora."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "Which of the following bacteria are found in the nose?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Haemophilus sp.",
            "b) S. pneumoniae",
            "c) Corynebacterium sp.",
            "d) S. epidermidis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the deep sebaceous glands are found lipophilic anaerobic bacteria such as Propionibacterium acnes which is associated with the skin disease known as acne vulgaris."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "The microorganisms stick to which of the following regions of the respiratory tract?",
        "Options": [
            "a) nasal baffle",
            "b) nasopharynx",
            "c) mucus",
            "d) oropharynx"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bacteria most frequently and most consistently found in the nose are S. epidermidis and S. aureus."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "Saliva generally has a microbial population of  _______ bacteria per milliliter.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 1000",
            "c) 105",
            "d) 108"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Microorganisms will impinge on and stick to the thin moist layer of highly viscous mucus that overlies the surface of the respiratory tract."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "Fusobacterium belongs to which type of bacterial group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) aerobes",
            "b) facultative anaerobes",
            "c) obligate anaerobes",
            "d) microaerophilic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bacteria that manage to travel the air passages all the way to the alveoli of the lungs are usually engulfed and destroyed by phagocytic body cells known as alveolar macrophages."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "Which enzyme is required for the production of glucan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) glycosyl transferase",
            "b) glucoisomerase",
            "c) hexokinase",
            "d) glucose-6-phosphatase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Saliva itself generally contains transient microbes from other sites of the oral cavity, particularly from the upper surface of the tongue, and generally has a microbial population of about 108 bacteria per milliliter. "
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism is found in the gingival crevices at puberty?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lactobacillus",
            "b) Treponema sp.",
            "c) Actinomyces",
            "d) S.mutans"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: As the first teeth appear, obligate anaerobes, such as species of the genera Bacteroides and Fusobacterium, become more evident because the tissue surrounding the teeth provides an anaerobic environment."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "Enterococci is found in which part of the intestine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) duodenum",
            "b) jejunum",
            "c) ileum",
            "d) large intestine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Glucan is formed only in the presence of the disaccharide sucrose by means of an enzyme called glycosyl transferase located on the surface of the cocci."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "Which body part contains the largest microbial population?",
        "Options": [
            "a) stomach",
            "b) small intestine",
            "c) large intestine",
            "d) mouth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Probably as a result of hormonal changes, anaerobic bacteria, especially oral spirochetes like Treponema sp. and Bacteroides melaninogenicus, colonize the oxygen-deficient gingival crevices at puberty."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a Gram-positive bacilli?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacteroides",
            "b) Eubacterium",
            "c) Lactobacillus",
            "d) Bifidobacterium"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the jejunum there are occasionally found species of enterococci, lactobacilli, and diphtheroids."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "Which microorganism among the following can live as a commensal but can also be pathogenic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trichomonas hominis",
            "b) Entamoeba histolytica",
            "c) Endolimax",
            "d) Iodamoeba"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the human body the colon or large intestine has the largest microbial population. It has been estimated that the number of microorganisms in stool specimens is about 1011 organisms per gram wet weight."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "Degree of pathogenicity is referred to as _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) infection",
            "b) virulence",
            "c) avirulent",
            "d) attenuated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Various strains of pathogenic species differ with regard to their degree of pathogenicity, i.e., with regard to their virulence."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "Which type of strains are used in vaccines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) virulent",
            "b) avirulent",
            "c) attenuated",
            "d) non-pathogenic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Attenuated strains are widely used as vaccines to elicit immunity to various diseases."
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "Which of the following characteristics of the microorganism does not help in causing infectious disease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) must enter the host",
            "b) must metabolize in the host tissue",
            "c) must resist host defenses",
            "d) must not damage the host"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The LD50 dose can be determined more precisely than LD100 dose because the rate of change in mortality versus change in dose is greatest around the point of 50 percent mortality."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "When the infection occurs suddenly and with severe intensity it is known as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) chronic",
            "b) fulminating",
            "c) acute",
            "d) localized"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pathogenic microorganism after entering the host must also damage the host to cause any infectious disease."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "Tuberculosis is which type of infection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) acute",
            "b) chronic",
            "c) primary",
            "d) secondary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Microbial adherence or attachment of the pathogen to some surface of the host is selective: various pathogens attach only to certain tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "Where does Streptococcus pyogenes infects in the body to cause infection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cervix",
            "b) small intestine",
            "c) urethra",
            "d) throat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fulminating type of infection occurs suddenly and with severe intensity. An example is cerebrospinal meningitis caused by Neisseria meningitidis."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "Vibrio cholerae adheres to the epithelial cells of the small intestine by means of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pili",
            "b) proteins",
            "c) hemagglutinin",
            "d) hydrogen bonds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chronic infections are those diseases which has a long duration like tuberculosis disease."
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "Poliovirus attaches to central nervous system by means of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) pili",
            "b) proteins",
            "c) hemagglutinin",
            "d) hydrogen bonds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Streptococcus pyogenes, the causative agent of streptococcal sore throat, attaches specifically to the epithelial cells of the throat by means of cell wall proteins."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism causes infection in burns?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pseudomonas aeruginosa",
            "b) Clostridium perfringens",
            "c) Borrelia sp",
            "d) Streptococcus sp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Burns often become infected by Pseudomonas aeruginosa or other aerobic or facultatively anaerobic bacteria from the surrounding."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism causes relapsing fever in humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pseudomonas aeruginosa",
            "b) Clostridium perfringens",
            "c) Borrelia sp.",
            "d) Streptococcus sp."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: V. cholerae, the causative agent of cholera, multiplies on the epithelial layer of the small intestine where it produces a toxin that causes the loss of fluid from the epithelial cells and kills the cells."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism participates in active penetration into the body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clostridium perfringens",
            "b) Shigella",
            "c) Borrelia sp.",
            "d) Pseudomonas aeruginosa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Borrelia sp. cause relapsing fever in humans when the spirochetes are introduced through the bite of a tick or a body louse."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "Bacillary dysentery is caused by which of the following microorganism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clostridium perfringens",
            "b) Borrelia sp.",
            "c) Shigella",
            "d) Pseudomonas aeruginosa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In bacillary dysentery, Shigella bacteria penetrate into and kill the epithelial cells of the colon, then spread to adjacent cells, which are in turn killed."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "In which of the following body part does the influenza virus does not penetrate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) small intestine",
            "b) nasopharynx",
            "c) trachea",
            "d) bronchi"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Wounds and burns represent one passive mechanism and they can introduce pathogens directly into the underlying tissues."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "Which of the following is an arthropod?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clostridium perfringens",
            "b) Borrelia sp.",
            "c) Shigella",
            "d) Pseudomonas aeruginosa"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bacillary dysentery is caused by Shigella bacteria which penetrate into and kill the epithelial cells of the colon, then spread to adjacent cells, which are in turn killed."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "Gas gangrene is caused by which of the following microorganisms?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Staphylococcus aureus",
            "b) Clostridium perfringens",
            "c) Pseudomonas aeruginosa",
            "d) E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Anaerobic bacteria, Clostridium perfringens, causes wound infection gas gangrene."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "Which of the following condition is false for tissue invasion by C.perfringens?",
        "Options": [
            "a) anaerobic condition of the wound",
            "b) production of large amounts of hydrogen gas",
            "c) production of small amounts of hydrogen gas",
            "d) release of toxins"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The characteristic lesion, abscess caused by Staphylococcus aureus, is a walled-off cavity in the tissues containing the staphylococci, numerous white blood cells, etc. This is a type of localized infection."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "What is the shape of the lymph nodes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) tubular",
            "b) circular",
            "c) cuboidal",
            "d) ovoid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Production of large amounts of hydrogen gas by the bacteria contributes to the rapidity of tissue invasion."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "Lymph enters a lymph node by several _________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) lymphatic trunks",
            "b) lymphatic vessels",
            "c) lymphatic ducts",
            "d) arteries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Amputation of an affected limb is often the only way to stop the spread of C.perfringens to the rest of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "Which microbe causes the disease erysipelas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S. pyogenes",
            "b) C. perfringens",
            "c) Pseudomonas aeruginosa",
            "d) E.coli"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Lymph nodes are ovoid structures ranging in size from one to several millimeters and are widely distributed throughout the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of a bubo?",
        "Options": [
            "a) inflamed",
            "b) sore when infected",
            "c) small",
            "d) free from bacteria"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Lymph enters a lymph node by any of several lymphatic vessels, passes through the lymph node along tortuous, winding channels, and emerges via a single efferent lymph vessel."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "Where does Neisseria meningitidis reach after entering the body?",
        "Options": [
            "a) kidney",
            "b) intestine",
            "c) nasopharynx",
            "d) meninges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Erysipelas, an inflammatory disease of the skin is caused by S. pyogenes. The painful lesions are spread by invasion of the lymphatic system of the subepidermal tissue."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism can cause acute renal failure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leptospira",
            "b) Salmonella typhi",
            "c) Neisseria meningitidis",
            "d) Bacillus anthracis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The lymph node removes nearly all of the bacteria that enters it, and it may become inflamed, enlarged, and sore when infected and in this condition it is sometimes called a bubo."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "Which of the following disease is caused by the pathogen directly infecting the lymphatic system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) meningitis",
            "b) typhoid fever",
            "c) renal failure",
            "d) anemia"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Neisseria meningitidis present in the nasopharynx can reach the meninges (membranes that cover the brain and spinal cord) by means of transient bacteremia."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "Which of the following disease is an example of septicemic infection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) typhoid fever",
            "b) meningitis",
            "c) anthrax",
            "d) renal failure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: By means of bacteremia, spirochetes of the genus Leptospira can reach the kidneys, where they may eventually cause acute renal failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "Which bacteria has an unusual capsule among the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Haemophilus influenzae",
            "b) Klebsiella pneumoniae",
            "c) Streptococcus pneumoniae",
            "d) Bacillus anthracis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The capsule of B. anthracis is unusual in that it is composed of a polypeptide rather than a polysaccharide."
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "For Clostridium botulinum type A toxin, 1 MLD for a mouse is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5 X 10-5 µg",
            "b) 4 X 10-5 µg",
            "c) 6 X 10-2 µg",
            "d) 5 µg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Clostridium botulinum type A produces the most potent toxin known: 1 MLD for a mouse is 2.5 X 10-5 µg of the purified toxin."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "What is the chemical nature of endotoxins?",
        "Options": [
            "a) protein",
            "b) polysaccharide",
            "c) lipopolysaccharide",
            "d) lipid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Endotoxins are lipopolysaccharide in nature and are released from cell walls of lysed Gram-negative bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "Which type of toxin is tetanus toxin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) enterotoxin",
            "b) neurotoxin",
            "c) cytotoxin",
            "d) endotoxin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Exotoxins are heat-labile in nature and are inactivated easily by boiling which is not the case with endotoxins."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a plasmid-mediated toxin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) diphtheria toxin",
            "b) botulism toxin",
            "c) tetanus toxin",
            "d) food-poisoning toxin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tetanus toxins affect nerve tissues and are hence termed as neurotoxins. It comes under the broad category of exotoxins."
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "Which amino acid is an inhibitory transmitter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) alanine",
            "b) tyrosine",
            "c)  glycine",
            "d) phenylalanine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Plasmid-mediated toxin is the enterotoxin made by food-poisoning strains of S.aureus. Plasmid carries the gene for the toxin."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "Which toxin causes paralysis of muscles?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diphtheria toxin",
            "b) Botulinum toxin",
            "c) Tetanus toxin",
            "d) Cholera toxin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: By means of the B region the toxin binds to the membrane of a tissue cell. The A region consists of the enzymatic activity and catalyzes the reaction that inactivates elongation factor 2 (EF-2), a factor essential for elongation of polypeptide chain during protein synthesis."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "How many B subunits are present in cholera toxin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: To render neurons temporarily insensitive to stimulation, it is accomplished in the central nervous system by the action of a chemical called an inhibitory transmitter, viz., the amino acid glycine."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong regarding the effects of cholera toxin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) loss of fluid from the body",
            "b) pH of blood remains constant",
            "c) hemoconcentration",
            "d) bicarbonate ions are lost from blood"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The botulinum toxin binds to the axon near the neuromuscular junction and prevents the secretion of acetylcholine; thus the muscle cannot contract and paralysis occurs."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "Which of the following toxin is a hemolysin?",
        "Options": [
            "a) diphtheria toxin",
            "b) botulism toxin",
            "c) tetanus toxin",
            "d) streptolysin O"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Cholera toxin consists of one A subunit and five B subunits. The B subunits are responsible for attachment of the toxin to the surface of the epithelial cells of the small intestine."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "Hylauronidase enzyme is produced by which of the following organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) C. perfringens",
            "b) S. pyogenes",
            "c) S. aureus",
            "d) Mycoplasma"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Since bicarbonate ions are lost from the blood, the pH of the blood falls, which may lead to death by acidosis."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "Which of the following has the ability to bind antibodies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Coagulase",
            "b) Streptokinase",
            "c) Protein A",
            "d) Hydrogen Peroxide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Streptolysin O (SLO) is a hemolysin, causing beta hemolysis around the colonies on blood-agar plates incubated anaerobically. It also acts as a leukocidin."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "LT toxin is produced by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) S. aureus",
            "b) E.coli",
            "c) B. anthracis",
            "d) C. perfringens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Hylauronidase enzyme is produced by the gas gangrene causing organism C. perfringens and has been thought to enhance penetration of the host tissues by hydrolyzing hyaluronic acid."
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "Syphilis is caused by which of the following organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Treponema pallidum",
            "b) Treponema pertenue",
            "c) Treponema endemicum",
            "d) Treponema carateum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:Treponema pallidum causes syphilis disease in humans which is a venereal or congenital disease in humans."
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "Which of the following terms stand for damage to the spinal cord during tertiary stage of syphilis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lymphadenopathy",
            "b) Malaise",
            "c) Paresis",
            "d) Tabes dorsalis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Tabes dorsalis results from damage to the spinal cord: the patient becomes uncoordinated and has loss of reflexes, uncontrollable urination, loss of perception, and sensation, blindness and loss of hearing. "
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a specific test for detecting antitreponemal antibodies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VDRL",
            "b) RPR",
            "c) TPH",
            "d) Widal Test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Two widely used specific tests are the fluorescent treponemal antibody (FTA) and the T. pallidum hemagglutination (TPH) test."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "In which body part does the C. jejuni causes infection?",
        "Options": [
            "a) mouth",
            "b) stomach",
            "c) small and large intestine",
            "d) limbs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: C. jejuni causes acute exudative and hemorrhagic inflammation of the wall of the small and large intestine."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "Which disease is caused by P. pseudomallei organism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) melioidosis",
            "b) diarrhea",
            "c) gastroenteritis",
            "d) typhoid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: P. pseudomallei are a tropical and subtropical soil organism that can cause a disease known as melioidosis in a large variety of animals and occasionally in humans."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "Which of the following antibiotics is most effective?",
        "Options": [
            "a) streptomycin",
            "b) tetracycline",
            "c) gentamicin",
            "d) ampicillin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: P.aeruginosa is resistant to many common antibiotics, although gentamicin and carbenicillin often are effective."
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism occurs in swine?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brucella melitensis",
            "b) Brucella abortus",
            "c) Brucella suis",
            "d) Legionella pneumophila"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Pontiac fever is a less severe disease characterized by fever, chills, headache, dry cough and muscle pain and is self limiting and nonfatal."
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "Which drug is used for the treatment of brucellosis in humans?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Erythromycin",
            "b) Tetracycline",
            "c) Carbenicillin",
            "d) Gentamicin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Brucella suis occurs in swine. They are mainly parasites and pathogens of domestic animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "Which of the following capsular polysaccharides is used for preparing a vaccine against meningococcal meningitis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) serovar A",
            "b) serovar B",
            "c) serovar C",
            "d) serovar A and C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Tetracycline is the drug of choice for the treatment of brucellosis in humans. No vaccine is available for human immunization."
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "Thayer-Martin medium is used for isolation of organism for which disease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) diphtheria",
            "b) meningococcal meningitis",
            "c) gonorrhea",
            "d) gastroenteritis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The organism will not grow on ordinary culture media because such media contain toxic substances such as unsaturated fatty acids. Starch must be added to absorb these toxic substances."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "Which of the following strains causes acute gastroenteritis in newborns and infants?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enteropathogenic strains",
            "b) Enteroinvasive strains",
            "c) Enterotoxigenic strains",
            "d) Both enteropathogenic and enterotoxigenic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A vaccine is available for epidemic control of meningococcal meningitis and consists of the purified capsular polysaccharides of serovars A and C; the serovar B polysaccharide appears not to be highly immunogenic."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "Which of the following toxins cause damage to the tissue cells by its phospholipase action?",
        "Options": [
            "a) alpha toxin",
            "b) delta toxin",
            "c) protein A",
            "d) coagulase"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Delta toxin damages tissue cells by its action as a phospholipase. It is produced by human strains of S. aureus."
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "Which of the following microorganism causes lesions in the form of abscesses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Staphylococcus aureus",
            "b) Streptococcus pyogenes",
            "c) Streptococcus pneumoniae",
            "d) Clostridium perfringens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Staphylococcus aureus causes localized infections in which the characteristic lesion is a walled-off fort called the abscess— a cavity filled with pus cells (neutrophils), dead tissue, and bacteria."
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "Streptococus pyogenes comprises which Lancefield group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) B",
            "c) C",
            "d) D"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Antibiotics have difficulty in reaching the staphylococci and may have to be administered to a patient for a long period in order to be effective."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "Which of the following microbe does not belong to Group D enterococci group?",
        "Options": [
            "a) S. faecalis",
            "b) S. faecium",
            "c) S. durans",
            "d) S. bovis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Streptococus pyogenes comprises Lancefield group A. This organism causes several diseases like sore throat, scarlet fever etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "Which of the following immunity is protective against infection by S.pyogenes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) cell-mediated immunity",
            "b) antigen-antibody immunity",
            "c) humoral immunity",
            "d) no cure present"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: S. bovis belongs to Group D nonenterococci group. All other above microbes belong to Group D enterococci group."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "Puerperal fever is a streptococcal infection of the ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) kidney",
            "b) skin",
            "c) uterus",
            "d) heart"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Scarlet fever is similar to the pharyngitis except for the skin rash that appears because of the erythrogenic toxin."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a major virulence factor of Streptococcus pneumoniae?",
        "Options": [
            "a) polysaccharide capsule",
            "b) M protein",
            "c) streptolysin O",
            "d) streptolysin S"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The only type of immunity that is protective against infection by S. pyogenes is humoral immunity: antibodies against M proteins act as opsonins, enhancing phagocytosis of the streptococci."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "Which drug is used for the treatment of anthrax?",
        "Options": [
            "a) erythromycin",
            "b) penicillin",
            "c) tetracycline",
            "d) ampicillin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Puerperal fever, sometimes called puerperal sepsis, is a streptococcal infection of the uterus of a mother and is acquired at childbirth."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "Which of the following organisms produces neurotoxin as a virulence factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bacillus anthracis",
            "b) Clostridium tetani",
            "c) Streptococcus pneumoniae",
            "d) Staphylococcus aureus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Clostridium tetani produces only one virulence factor which is a powerful neurotoxin. It is the causative agent of tetanus."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "Clostridium perfringens type A occurs as a natural flora of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) stomach",
            "b) mouth",
            "c) intestine",
            "d) eyes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Booster immunizations should be given every 10 years to maintain an adequate level of antitoxin to protect against tetanus."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "__________________ is a hyaluronidase that may aid invasiveness of C.perfringens.",
        "Options": [
            "a) alpha toxin",
            "b) theta toxin",
            "c) µ toxin",
            "d) √ toxin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Clostridium perfringens type A occurs as part of the normal flora of the human intestine."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "What pressure of oxygen is used in the treatment involving the use of hyperbaric oxygen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 100",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The µ toxin is a virulence factor produced by C.perfringens and is a hyaluronidase that may aid invasiveness."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "Which of the following temperature is suitable for the multiplication of clostridia spores?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 109 to116 degree F",
            "b) 100 degree F",
            "c) -2 to 16 degree F",
            "d) 30-40 degree F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the treatment involving the use of hyperbaric oxygen, the patient is placed in a chamber containing 3 atmospheres pressure of pure oxygen several times a day for half-hour periods."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "Which serovar of C. botulinum occurs mainly in the sediments of the Great Lakes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) B",
            "c) E",
            "d) F"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the meat or poultry is cooked at a temperature that does not kill the spores and is subsequently kept at a temperature of 109 to 116 degree F for atleast 2 hours, the clostridia may multiply."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "Toxin A involved in pseudomembranous colitis is a type of _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) endotoxin",
            "b) enterotoxin",
            "c) cytotoxin",
            "d) neurotoxin"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Serovar E occurs mainly in the sediments of Great Lakes and along the coasts of western North America and northern Japan."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "Which of the following inactivates IgA antibodies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cord factor",
            "b) Diphthin",
            "c) Neuroaminidase",
            "d) K antigens"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Patients with botulism are treated with polyvalent antitoxin (i.e., antitoxin against toxin types A, B, and E) to neutralize any toxin that has not yet become fixed to nerve tissue."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "Erythrasma is caused by which of the following microorganism?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Corynebacterium diphtheriae",
            "b) Corynebacterium ulcerans",
            "c) Corynebacterium minutissimum",
            "d) Listeria monocytogenes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Toxin A is an enterotoxin which causes fluid accumulation in the bowel. It is a type of exotoxin and is involved in pseudomembranous colitis."
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "Schick Test is used for detection of which of the following disease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Diphtheria",
            "b) Tuberculosis",
            "c) Erythrasma",
            "d) Botulism"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Diphthin is a protease which inactivates IgA antibodies. It is a virulence factor produced by C.diphtheriae."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "Which among the following species causes tuberculosis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mycobacterium leprae",
            "b) Mycobacterium kansasii",
            "c) Mycobacterium bovis",
            "d) Mycobacterium ulcerans"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Corynebacterium minutissimum is a species which causes a skin disease called erythrasma."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "Polioviruses belong to which of the following groups?",
        "Options": [
            "a) enteroviruses",
            "b) rhinoviruses",
            "c) foot and mouth disease viruses",
            "d) retroviruses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polioviruses belong to the enteroviruses because they are found in the intestines and excreted in the feces. They cause mainly intestinal infections and sometimes infections of the respiratory tract; neurological disease may also be produced."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "Where does polioviruses multiply first?",
        "Options": [
            "a) skin",
            "b) oropharynx",
            "c) lymph nodes",
            "d) spinal cord"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Polioviruses multiply in the oropharynx or intestinal mucosa, pass to the lymphatic system and eventually reach the bloodstream."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "At what pH values are the rhinoviruses destroyed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7",
            "b) 12-13",
            "c) 1-4",
            "d) 5-7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Salk virus is 70 to 90 percent effective and is administered in a series of three intramuscular injections."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "Complement- fixation is done for laboratory diagnosis of which of the following disease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poliomyelitis",
            "b) Mumps",
            "c) Measles",
            "d) FMD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Rhinoviruses differ from enteroviruses by being destroyed at pH values of less than 5 (such as would occur in the stomach) and by having an optimal growth temperature at 33 degrees C."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "Yellow fever is caused by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Alphaviruses",
            "b) Rubellaviruses",
            "c) Flaviviruses",
            "d) Pestiviruses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Laboratory diagnosis of FMD is done by complement-fixation, virus-neutralization, or mouse-inoculation tests."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "Which of the following viruses consists of a helical nucleocapsid?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Picornaviruses",
            "b) Togaviruses",
            "c) Adenoviruses",
            "d) Coronaviruses"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Eastern equine encephalitis has a high mortality rate (50 to 70 percent), whereas western equine encephalitis virus infections are seldom fatal (3%)."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "Which drug is used to cure influenza caused by type A strains?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Penicillin",
            "b) Amantadine",
            "c) Ampicillin",
            "d) Tetracycline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Yellow fever is caused by flaviviruses that differ from others in causing a disease in which the liver, kidney, and other organs are affected."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "Which of the following is incorrect with respect to Paramyxoviruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) large (125 to 250 nm)",
            "b) core of single-stranded (—) RNA",
            "c) rna is segmented",
            "d) hemagglutinin and neuraminidase activities occur together"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Coronaviruses have a helical nucleocapsid and contain single-stranded RNA of the (+) type."
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "Crimean-Congo hemorrhagic fever is transmitted by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mosquitoes",
            "b) ticks",
            "c) biting flies",
            "d) rabbits"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A synthetic drug, amantadine, can prevent and even help to cure influenza caused by type A strains; it acts by preventing the penetration and uncoating of the virus after it attaches to a host cell."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "What is the shape of the Rhabdoviruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bullet",
            "b) circular",
            "c) brick shaped",
            "d) ovoid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The paramyxoviruses are larger (125 to 250 nm), the RNA is segmented and only the (—) strand is present, and the hemagglutinin and neuraminidase activities occur together in a single kind of surface glycoprotein (HN)."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "What is the shape of the nucleoid of poxviruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) circular",
            "b) brick-shaped",
            "c) irregular",
            "d) dumbbell-shaped"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Poxviruses contain double-stranded DNA, protein, and lipid and have a dumbbell-shaped nucleoid surrounded by two membrane layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "The fatality rate for variola minor is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10-30%",
            "b) 1-5%",
            "c) 0.1-0.3%",
            "d) 60-80%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The less virulent variola minor (alastrim) has a fatality rate of only 0.1 to 0.3 percent which is very less in comparison to that of variola major."
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "Which strain of adenoviruses can cause cancer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Subgroup I",
            "b) Subgroup II",
            "c) Subgroup III",
            "d) Subgroup IV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For diagnosis of Smallpox viruses the use of light microscopy to demonstrate inclusion bodies i.e., Guarnieri bodies in stained cells is carried out."
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "MDV virus affects which of the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) chickens",
            "b) cattle",
            "c) humans",
            "d) birds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Adenoviruses particularly those of subgroup IV can cause cancer or are oncogenic when inoculated into immunodeficient animals (newborn hamsters)."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "Which drug is used for healing genital herpes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) acyclovir",
            "b) penicillin",
            "c) erythromycin",
            "d) tetracycline"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One of the animal herpesviruses is Marek’s disease virus (MDV), which affects the epithelium of feather follicles in chickens."
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "Mononucleosis is caused by which of the following viruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VZV",
            "b) HSV",
            "c) EBV",
            "d) HIV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: HSV-2 has been recognized as the causative agent of primary and recurrent disease involving the genital tract."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "What is the size of papillomaviruses?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 nm",
            "b) 45 nm",
            "c) 2 nm",
            "d) 55 nm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Topical application of the drug acyclovir can shorten the healing time in primary genital herpes but has little effect in the treatment of the recurrent form."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "SV 40 causes diseases in which animals?",
        "Options": [
            "a) monkeys",
            "b) rabbits",
            "c) humans",
            "d) cattle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Epstein-Barr Virus (EBV) is the causative agent of infectious mononucleosis, a self-limiting disease that occurs in up to 80 percent of the population."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "Dermatophytic diseases attributed infections to ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) humans",
            "b) insects",
            "c) monkeys",
            "d) birds"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Dermatophytic diseases attributed infections to insects and thus the Romans called these infections tinea, meaning “small insect larva”."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "Ringworm of the scalp is known as ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tinea capitis",
            "b) tinea pides",
            "c) tinea unguium",
            "d) onychomycosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Fungus diseases that occur on the nails, skin, hair, and mucous membranes are referred to as superficial mycoses or dermatomycoses."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "Black piedra is a fungus infection of the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) skin",
            "b) foot",
            "c) hair",
            "d) nails"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The dermatologists frequently used a terminology based on the part of the body involved, for example, tinea capitis is ringworm of the scalp."
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "Which of the following causes epidemic ringworm of the scalp in children?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Microsporum audouinii",
            "b) Trichophyton rubrum",
            "c) Candida albicans",
            "d) Epidermophyton floccosum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Black piedra is a fungus infection of hair, characterized by dark brown or black nodules on the hair shaft."
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "Tinea versicolor is caused by _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Piedraia hortae",
            "b) Trichosporon beigelii",
            "c) Malassezia furfur",
            "d) Candida albicans"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Microsporum audouinii is a dermatophyte that causes epidemic ringworm of the scalp in children."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "Moniliasis disease is caused by ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Histoplasma capsulatum",
            "b) Blastomyces dermatitidis",
            "c) Coccidioides immitis",
            "d) Candida albicans"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Malassezia furfur causes tinea versicolor, a generalized fungus infection of the skin covering trunk and sometimes other areas of the body."
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "Blastomyces brasiliensis causes which of the following disease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) North American blastomycosis",
            "b) South American blastomycosis",
            "c) Histoplasmosis",
            "d) Sporotrichosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The systemic mycoses are caused by many air-borne organisms that enter the body through the respiratory tract. They may however enter by other portals."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "Which of the following disease is an infection of the reticuloendothelial system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cryptococcosis",
            "b) Moniliasis",
            "c) Histoplasmosis",
            "d) Coccidioidomycosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Candida albicans causes Moniliasis that may infect any body tissue. It is found on mucous membranes of intestinal tracts."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not grow in Sabouraud’s glucose agar media?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Histoplasma capsulatum",
            "b) Coccidioides immitis",
            "c) Sporothrix schenckii",
            "d) Blastomyces dermatitidis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Blastomyces brasiliensis causes South American blastomycosis which is most famous in Brazil. Lesions are most commonly found in the mouth and gastrointestinal tract and in the lymph nodes of the neck."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "Animals that are routinely infected with a protozoan or parasite are termed as _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) definitive host",
            "b) intermediate host",
            "c) reservoir host",
            "d) parasitic host"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: An animal (or human) that is routinely infected with a protozoan or parasite which can also infect humans is termed as a reservoir host."
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "Laboratory diagnosis of Entamoeba histolytica depends on identification in the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) blood",
            "b) urine",
            "c) saliva",
            "d) stool"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: For the malaria protozoa, the mosquito is the definitive host, and humans or other vertebrates are the intermediate hosts."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "African sleeping sickness is caused by which of the following protozoa?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Entamoeba histolytica",
            "b) Trypanosoma gambiense",
            "c) Leishmania donovani",
            "d) Plasmodium vivax"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Laboratory diagnosis of Entamoeba histolytica depends on identification in the stools. Search for the amoeba should be made as soon as possible after the stool is passed to be sure of the presence of living, motile forms."
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "After how many days of infection by mosquitoes do the symptoms for malaria occur?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1-2",
            "b) 3-5",
            "c) 10-16",
            "d) 20-30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: African sleeping sickness is caused by Trypanosoma gambiense and is transmitted by flying bite."
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "The schizonts enter which body part?",
        "Options": [
            "a) bloodstream",
            "b) spleen",
            "c) mouth",
            "d) liver"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Of the four species of Plasmodium protozoa that cause malaria in humans, P. falciparum and P. vivax are the two that most commonly cause infections."
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "How much time does it take for the rupture of infected erythrocytes with P. vivax?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24 h",
            "b) 48 h",
            "c) 72 h",
            "d) 96 h"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Symptoms usually occur 10 to 16 days after infection by the mosquitoes."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "The disease espundia is caused by which of the following protozoa?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leishmania brasiliensis",
            "b) Leishmania donovani",
            "c) Leishmania tropica",
            "d) Phlebotomus sp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The sporozoites quickly enter the liver, where they divide and develop into multinucleated forms known as schizonts."
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "Leishmania organism are transmitted to humans by ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) sandflies",
            "b) tsetse flies",
            "c) mosquitoes",
            "d) bugs"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rupture of infected erythrocytes at the completion of schizogony occurs every 48 h with P. vivax and P. ovale."
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "What is the incubation period for kala azar disease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24 h",
            "b) 1 month",
            "c) 2-4 months",
            "d) 7 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Leishmania brasiliensis causes the disease espundia which can then cause the infection for the disease leishmaniasis."
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "African sleeping sickness is caused by _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trypanosoma cruzi",
            "b) Trypanosoma gambiense",
            "c) Trichomonas vaginalis",
            "d) Leishmania tropica"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: Leishmania organism are transmitted to humans by the bites of sandflies (genus Phlebotomus) harbored by dogs and other animals that serve as reservoirs for the parasites."
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "Chagas’ disease is transmitted to humans by ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) tsetse fly",
            "b) mosquitoes",
            "c) reduviid bugs",
            "d) sandflies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Clinically, kala azar has a variable incubation period, usually 2 to 4 months. Onset may be gradual or sudden, and the source of the disease may be acute or chronic."
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "Where are the protozoa present during the acute stage of Chagas’ disease?",
        "Options": [
            "a) blood",
            "b) spleen",
            "c) liver",
            "d) stool"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: African sleeping sickness is caused by Trypanosoma gambiense and Trypanosoma rhodesiense."
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "Nystatin is effective in curing ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Deep mycoses",
            "b) Dermatophyte infections",
            "c) Systemic mycoses",
            "d) Candida infections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Nystatin is effective in topical Candida infections but not in deep mycoses or even dermatophyte infections."
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "5-fluorocytosine is which type of antibiotic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) polyene",
            "b) pyrimidine antimetabolites",
            "c) imidazole",
            "d) antibacterial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Polyene antibiotics like the nystatin and amphotericin B act on the plasma membrane of the fungus, combining with membrane sterols, and cause leakage of intracellular potassium and other metabolites."
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "Which of the following antibiotics causes inhibition of ergosterol biosynthesis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) amphotericin B",
            "b) 5-fluorocytosine",
            "c) ketoconazole",
            "d) miconazole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: 5-fluorocytosine is a type of pyrimidine antimetabolite which is especially effective in the treatment of yeast infections."
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "Miconazole is active against which of the following fungal infections?",
        "Options": [
            "a) coccidioidomycosis",
            "b) cryptococcosis",
            "c) moniliasis",
            "d) sporotrichosis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mechanism of action for ketoconazole is inhibition of ergosterol biosynthesis, an important step in the synthesis of fungal cell walls and membranes."
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "Which drug is used for the treatment of leishmaniasis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) chloroquine phosphate",
            "b) metronidazole",
            "c) suramin",
            "d) sodium stibogluconate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Miconazole is very active against coccidioidomycosis and paracoccidioidomycosis. It reacts with cytoplasmic membranes and causes them to leak."
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "Which of the following animallike flagellates has a flagellum originating from the midportion of the cell?",
        "Options": [
            "a) amastigote",
            "b) promastigote",
            "c) epimastigote",
            "d) trypomastigote"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The antibiotic griseofulvin is active against the dermatophyte infections (superficial skin infections) but not against the deep mycoses (systemic diseases caused by fungi)."
    }
]